Ultimate Truth

Publishing information

Copyright © 2018 Anvita Ramakant Sawant

First Edition: September 2018

Published by

ZEN PUBLICATIONS

A Division of Maoli Media Private Limited

60, Juhu Supreme Shopping Centre,

Gulmohar Cross Road No. 9, JVPD Scheme,

Juhu, Mumbai 400 049. India.

Tel: +91 9022208074

e-mail: info@zenpublications.com

Website: www.zenpublications.com

For information, permissions and requests, please contact Amit Ramakant Sawant

e-mail: asawant@som.umaryland.edu

Website: www.ramakantmaharaj.net

ISBN 978-93-87242-14-2

Printed at Repro India Limited

All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic or mechanical, including photocopying, recording, or by any information storage and retrieval system without written permission from the Copyright Holder or her representative, Amit Ramakant Sawant, except for the inclusion of brief quotations in a review.

CONTENTS

Preface

Acknowledgements

Introduction

PART ONE

Talks from Nashik: March to November 2017

1.THE DIAGNOSIS

1.

Who wants happiness and peace?

2.

Why is there fear?

3.

Why is life so painful? I am depressed and worried

4.

Why can’t I find happiness and peace?

5.

Why is my peace disturbed?

6.

Why are these bad thoughts coming?

7.

Why do we have so many questions?

8.

What do we really want?

9.

What do you mean by “real happiness”?

10.

How did everything come about?

11.

What is the meaning of life?

12.

So, my mistake was to identify with the body-form?

13.

Why is there pressure to go searching here and there for Truth?

14.

How can we leave all our problems behind?

2.THE PRINCIPLE OF SPIRITUALITY

15.

Why do I need spirituality?

16.

What is the principle behind spirituality?

17.

Is spirituality useful?

18.

What is the secret of spirituality?

19.

What do we mean by spirituality?

20.

What is that Secret Asset?

21.

What is Reality?

22.

What is illusion, and what is Reality?

23.

Is duality an illusion?

24.

What do you mean by identification?

25.

What is Conviction?

26.

How will Spontaneous Conviction appear?

27.

What is this body?

28.

How is this world illusory?

29.

If the Identifier is invisible, how do you identify the Identifier?

30.

If the Seer disappears from the body, what happens to the world?

31.

You say, that nothing has happened, and nothing is going to happen?

32.

What is Brahma Dnyan?

33.

Why are there disciples and Masters?

34.

Why do we bow to the Master?

35.

Who, or what, is holding this food-body?

36.

Who is acting within the body?

37.

Do we need God?

38.

Who wants Realization?

39.

Who is the Master addressing?

40.

“I” am doing this or that. Where is that “I”?

41.

Who says “I am Brahman”?

42.

I don’t know why I focus on the darkness, and not the light?

43.

How can I identify myself?

44.

What do you mean by refreshing our memory?

45.

What is the mind, ego and intellect?

46.

What is illusion?

47.

What is sin?

48.

What exactly do we need to know?

49.

What is spiritual awareness?

50.

After reading all these spiritual books, where do you stand?

51.

I do have knowledge, but, it is not practical knowledge

52.

What do you mean by “I don’t know”?

53.

Does spirituality mean dissolving all our concepts?

54.

What do you mean by knowledge?

55.

What is spiritual knowledge?

56.

Who wants spiritual knowledge?

57.

Why are there still some questions?

58.

Why do these concepts appear?

59.

How can I discard all these concepts?

60.

Why do I need meditation, a Master, and all this spiritual knowledge?

61.

Why spiritual books and Masters?

62.

Why is a Master needed?

63.

What exactly is this body-form?

64.

Why is Conviction necessary?

65.

How do I identify myself?

66.

What is the best way to go beyond, or prior to, all this?

67.

How do we absorb this Truth, totally and completely?

68.

So, we need to put in effort, but not struggle?

69.

How can I Realize?

70.

Is it possible to identify what I am positively? It seems we can only know what we are not...?

71.

What do you mean by total involvement?

72.

What does Selfless Self mean?

73.

You often mention “glimpses of I”?

74.

You never talk about death?

75.

What kind of changes will take place?

76.

How do I concentrate on the Concentrator that is formless?

77.

“Be strong! Have courage!” What does that mean?

78.

Even though I am convinced intellectually, I still have material needs

79.

Can we know anything?

80.

If I am not the body, what am I?

81.

What value does this body have?

82.

What is our lifestyle based on?

83.

I know I’m not the body, but still I want a long, and happy life?

84.

Is it okay to follow my family tradition, of devotion to Rama and Krishna?

3.THE MEDICINE: MANTRA, MEDITATION, DEVOTION

85.

How can I digest the knowledge?

86.

How can I control this crazy mind?

87.

What is meditation?

88.

What is the principle of meditation?

89.

Is meditation absolutely necessary? I am averse to it

90.

Why do you insist on continuous meditation?

91.

Why the Naam Mantra?

92.

Why do we have Naam Mantra meditation?

93.

Will the Naam Mantra help my spirituality?

94.

Why is the Naam Mantra required?

95.

In the beginning, I must put in some effort?

96.

So, will the Naam Mantra help me to identify myself?

97.

I cannot come to India to receive the Naam Mantra...

98.

A casual approach to meditation is futile

99.

How do I practise the Mantra, and how does it work?

100.

So, we recite the Mantra “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”?

101.

Do I recite the Mantra aloud, or silently in my mind?

102.

When I recite the Mantra, do I have to pay attention to the meaning of the Mantra?

103.

Does meditation mean repeating the Naam Mantra, or sitting in one place and meditating?

104.

I have been reciting the Mantra for a few months. Should I continue?

105.

Nisargadatta Maharaj said: “the purpose of the Mantra is to surrender the seen to Brahman” How is this done?

106.

What is the minimum time for meditation?

107.

Will meditation make me spiritually strong?

108.

Does meditation mean that I have to sit for four hours?

109.

Some days I cannot even recite the Mantra for half an hour. What then?

110.

Do I just close my eyes for a few minutes?

111.

When I recite the Mantra, should I concentrate on the words, the sound, the breath, the Master, or just Selfless Self?

112.

While we are going through this meditation process, can we read books?

113.

Can you say something about devotion?

114.

Should we keep the sadhana going till our last breath, or only until Spontaneous Conviction is reached?

115.

Would you say, that meditation is letting go of our attachment to thoughts?

116.

What do you think of other kinds of meditation, like Buddhist meditation?

117.

What does concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator mean?

118.

When I recite the Naam Mantra, do I need to fight the illusory world?

4.THE PROGNOSIS

119.

What are the results of meditation?

120.

What are the changes that will take place after Conviction?

121.

After tasting the nectar, how is it reflected?

122.

How do I know if Brahman is absorbed in me?

123.

You say, that I am the architect of my life?

124.

If we compare a realized person to a non-realized person…?

125.

What do you mean when you say “the body touch dissolves”?

126.

If this is a dream, can we do anything we want?

127.

Why is devotion needed after Realization?

128.

Nisargadatta Maharaj used to pray after Realization. Why?

5.EXHORTATIONS AND WARNINGS

129.

Be brave, and live like a lion!

130.

You must have the courage to accept the Reality

131.

Spirituality gives you courage

132.

You say we need courage, but I don’t feel that I am a very courageous person…

133.

“Bless me! Bless me! I need a blessing!” Why are you begging?

134.

Why do we search for a Master?

135.

Why do we need to listen to a Master?

136.

How can anyone transfer power to you?

137.

Why go here and there?

138.

Why are we running after a mirage of spirituality?

139.

What does spirituality mean? Touching the Master’s feet, clapping, garlands?

140.

We are not doing any miracles

141.

Why does Nisargadatta say this, and Ramana Maharshi say that?

142.

“Oh, I am a spiritual man, how can I spend time with my wife, my father, my parents?”

143.

What is the use of this knowledge?

144.

Some people want to become sannyasins

145.

Is your Master realized, or not?

146.

Reading books and dry discussion, will not serve your purpose

147.

What is the point of counting beads?

148.

Nisargadatta Maharaj said, “Don’t mix with such elements which will distract you from Reality”. What did he mean?

6.TROUBLESHOOTING

149.

I don’t understand the second part of the Mantra. Are the syllables of the second part, the reverse of the first part?

150.

When I recite the Mantra, my mind is always trying to hold onto something

151.

I already have a Mantra. If I take your Mantra, does this mean that, I am starting all over again from the beginning?

152.

In the first two or three months, after receiving the Mantra, I couldn’t concentrate on the meditation, there

was a lot ofconfusion and depression

153.

I took the Mantra, and it has no effect

154.

That Conviction is not happening to me

155.

I face so many difficulties, how can I concentrate, and just be the witness?

156.

Every time I feel closer to Selfless Self, it is, as if something comes in the way

157.

I have the feeling that I am coming closer and closer to my Selfless Self, but then I fall…

158.

I am far too attracted to women…

159.

We feel very good when we hear these talks. Why does this not last?

160.

If some illusion or dream arises, should I try to stop it with the Mantra?

161.

When I meditate, a lot of thoughts are coming up. How do I make the mind still?

162.

When there are challenges, can I still stay with the sense that my real identity is Selfless Self?

163.

I feel trapped in the body, in maya

164.

What are the things that are blocking us, Maharaj?

165.

When I came two years ago, this knowledge was being absorbed very easily, but not anymore

166.

Why is Realization so hard?

167.

I just have this desire for closure of this whole spiritual search, rather than continue to meditate, do Self-enquiry and listen to teachers

168.

I have problems with my family. Why is my son not studying?

7.MISCELLANEOUS

169.

If there is no Realization, what happens?

170.

As long as I recite the Mantra, I will be able to accept whatever comes my way? Is that right?

171.

You say, there is nothing, but I think there is something else, there is a sense of beingness…

172.

How can it be said that the waking life is no different from a dream?

173.

If I do this sadhana, will I make progress?

174.

Should I eat vegetarian food, or not?

175.

What comes first, the Absolute, or food?

176.

What is the significance of Hari Narayana?

177.

Every question is answered in your books, so I can’t make up any questions

178.

Can we say that Ultimate Truth uses the body to know Itself?

179.

It is said in spiritual science, that your last desire takes you to another dream

180.

You are talking about the new world. What about the old world?

181.

Is that also another thought…that which wants peace?

182.

Is meditation and Self-enquiry the same thing?

183.

How important is Self-enquiry? And, is there an end to it?

184.

What is enquiry?

185.

Where does the body and the Spirit come from?

186.

What is Self-knowledge? Is it a direct sense of the primary “I”?

187.

Spontaneous waves of light occasionally appear. Do these experiences enable Self-enquiry, or are they just mind-body-knowledge to be discounted?

188.

Once, when I was on holiday in Tokyo, I went to a Buddhist temple. It was very peaceful. Is that okay, Maharaj?

189.

Maharaj, the body feels like it is vibrating. Is this good?

190.

When do I get liberation, mukti?

191.

What will happen after my death?

192.

After that continuous hammering, what happens to the

personality, does it dissolve with the body?

193.

Is there a God?

194.

Sometimes in meditation, I am aware of the colour blue. I wonder if that is why Shiva, Rama and Krishna are depicted in blue?

195.

I wonder if, when I die, when I leave this body, I will realize that Selfless Self?

Final Plea From Sri Ramakant Maharaj

PART TWO

Excerpts of Talks from U.S.A.: September to October 2016

Introduction From Sri Ramakant Maharaj

September 12, 2016, Silver Spring, U.S.A.

1.

The Quest to Find the Jewel of “Who Am I?”

2.

You Have Forgotten Your Identity

3.

Investigate Yourself

4.

Who is Watching the Dream?

5.

Know, That You Are the Central Point of the Universe

6.

You Are Your Own Master!

September 16, 2016, Silver Spring, U.S.A.

7.

You Are Nobody, and You Are Everybody

8.

Do Not Underestimate Yourself

9.

All Questions Are Body-Based

10.

I Am Nothing to Do With the World

11.

Why Did Spirit Forget Itself?

12.

Is Love a Concept?

13.

Mind Means the Flow of Thoughts

14.

Body-Based Knowledge

15.

Egoistic Meditation

16.

One Master

17.

The Naam Mantra

18.

Playing with Words

19.

The Six Signs of Realization

September 17, 2016, Silver Spring, U.S.A.

20.

Meditation is the Anti-Virus Software

21.

Selfless Self Has No Concerns

22.

There is No Difference Between You and I

23.

Knowledge is Free of Charge

24.

Come Forward!

September 18, 2016, Silver Spring, U.S.A.

25.

Nothing is Happening

26.

Meditation, Prayers and Bhajans

27.

Be Simple, Be Normal

28.

The Body is a Magic Box

29.

If you are Realized, Make Others Realized

30.

Spirituality Gives You Courage

Guidance From Sri Ramakant Maharaj

October 03, 2016, Columbia, U.S.A.

31.

All Miraculous Experiences Appear Upon Your Presence

32.

Power is Inbuilt in You

33.

The Master Appears

34.

The Ball is in Your Court

35.

Devotion is Acceptance

36.

No Hard and Fast Rules

37.

Physical Needs Have Nothing to do With Reality

38.

The Mantra is a Concept

October 17, 2016, Columbia, U.S.A.

39.

Slowly, Silently, Permanently

40.

Read Your Story

41.

What You See is Illusion, That Through Which You See is Reality

42.

There is Fire Everywhere

43.

Why Fill Your Pockets?

44.

Whatever Experience Appears is Illusion

45.

Presence is a Prerequisite

46.

We Love Ourselves the Most

47.

I Am Sharing This Knowledge With the Grace of My Master

October 26, 2016, Columbia U.S.A.

48.

In the Beginning, There is Bound to be a Struggle

49.

Stop All This Thinking. Be Totally Blank!

50.

There is no Waking, and There is no Sleeping

51.

The Great Saint is Within You

52.

Where Everything Ends, There You Are

53.

You Are Ultimate Truth

Encouragement From Sri Ramakant Maharaj

PART THREE

How The Master Changed My Life

Glossary

PREFACE

“Everyone should be enlightened!” is the clarion call of our Beloved and Great Sadguru, Sri Ramakant Maharaj.

Ultimate Truth will transform the reader. It is not just another book of spiritual knowledge. Using words as a medium, the Master places the reader’s Identity before him. Maharaj’s boundless compassion, and relentless drive, to bring the suffering of all beings to an end, radiate from each page.

Here, the reader will find the rarest, clearest, and most powerful teaching, that is not only comprehensive, but practical. They emanate from the “Direct Spontaneous Knowledge and Experience of a rare Self-Realized Jnani”.

Maharaj focuses on the needs of the seekers of our time: transform the easily available intellectual knowledge into actual, living knowledge. He is a lawyer that gives the courage to fight one’s case for freedom. He is a doctor that helps dispel the disease and recover the original health. He is, as he once said, the garbage man, calling for your trash!

It is the greatest fortune that you have encountered this unparalleled book, that is imbued with infinite wisdom, and the strongest exhortation for liberation.

But as Maharaj says again, and again, “Only You Can Make it Happen, Have Courage, Nothing is Impossible, the Ball is in Your Court – Smash it!”

Ultimate Truth is a crown jewel, in the casket of treasures, that Maharaj has given to us during His lifetime. It will lead you to uncover the True Treasure of your Selfless Self: at last you know yourself in a real sense! There is the Conviction that you are unborn, and therefore, immortal. Your life is filled with causeless, permanent happiness and peace. You are ever free of worldly suffering!

In 2016, Maharaj repeatedly expressed the wish to have a new book with his talks published, so that all aspects of his teaching are covered, that no question remains unanswered, that there is no place for doubts for devotees in the future. He would often conclude his talks with, “What you recorded, you type it – it will be useful for other devotees”.

The Master saw a beta version of this book just before He took Mahasamadhi on the 31st August 2018. Though the body has gone, He is with us, closer than ever before.

Per His wish, the book is presented for the first time on the day of the commemoration of the Mahasamadhi of his beloved Master, Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj, at Ranjit Ashram, 18th of September 2018.

The first print of the book was sent to the press on Guruvar (Thursday, Guru’s day in Indian Calendar), 6 September 2018

ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS

We wish to express our gratitude to Sadguru Sri Ramakant Maharaj, and to Ranjit Ashram. Special thanks are due to the following:

Gopal (Luc Bonameau), Joseph Tonelli, Dimitri Belos, Bertlee Garced, Chhaya Loomes, Saraswati (Anne van Nie), Rami Kowaluru, Rahul Pandav, David Bowen, Jim Nowak, and Muru Chauhan for recording and transcribing the Master’s Talks, organising the material, gathering the questions from seekers.

John Richards, Michael Reginato, and Amit Sawant (Maharaj’s son) in the U.S.A. for recording, transcribing, editing and arranging the Talks of Part 2.

Deepak Dhangar for co-ordinating and organizing the project, as well as liaising with the publishers, Zen Publications.

Thanks to Anvita R. Sawant (Maharaj’s wife) for the proofreading, to Yogesh Sharma and Zen Publications for the quick print of a beta book for Maharaj to see before his Mahasamadhi.

And last but not the least, all of us, including the readers, owe a special thanks to Ann Shaw (editor of Selfless Self) for the final editing. Despite personal illness, which involved prolonged hospitalization, Ann worked tirelessly for over two months to ensure that the final editing and formatting of the book was completed and delivered to the publishers so that they could meet the deadline of September 18th.

Sincere apologies for any omissions and errors.

Jai Sadguru!

INTRODUCTION

Ultimate Truth consists of 3 parts: Talks from Ranjit Ashram in Nashik, India, between March and November 2017, and Talks from the Master’s U.S.A. visit in 2016. (Bold text is used to hammer home the teachings.) The final section, “How the Master Changed my Life” contains personal sharings, from seekers, whose lives have been transformed forever, by Maharaj’s teachings.

There are around 250 questions. Those ultimate, and fundamental, questions of our existence, as well as the more commonplace, everyday ones, are answered with uncompromising power, clarity and directness, that leave nothing to the imagination. There is no hiding place from Truth!

These profound teachings, that take the reader beyond knowledge, are conveyed in a simple, light and effective way. Ultimate Truth leaves no stone unturned, so that all the questions that are posed by seekers, are finally exhausted. How to achieve Self-Realization is presented simply, and logically, flavoured with the Master’s own unique brand of humour!

Our most humble and compassionate Master, tirelessly shared these teachings, again and again, expecting nothing in return. He had one wish only: to put an end to our needless suffering, once and for all! Even in His final talk, when he was visibly frail, and his voice was very feeble, his focus remained steadfast: liberation for his devotees. With great poignancy, he pleaded: “Please accept the Reality”.

We humbly bow, with deep and overflowing gratitude, at the feet of our Great Master, Sri Ramakant Maharaj. Ultimate Truth is a timely gift to the world!

– The contributors

PART ONE Talks from Nashik March to November 2017

1 THE DIAGNOSIS

“You are posing as a somebody, a something, and you are trying to live within the circle of illusory concepts. And because of this, life is painful. It is intolerable.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

1. Who wants happiness and peace?

The body does not want happiness and peace. Spirit does not want happiness and peace. So, who wants happiness and peace? When the Spirit touched with the body, the concepts began to appear. They started creeping in, and growing, one by one. Prior to beingness, there were no concepts, no language, and no words, such as peace, happiness Spirit or Presence. There was nothing. Who is going to be looking for happiness and peace, after leaving the body? Everything comes from nothing, and everything goes back to nothing. This Reality must be established within you. Many seekers can talk very knowledgeably about Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God and the Masters, but they do not have any Self-knowledge! This kind of intellectual, or theoretical entertainment, is completely meaningless.

Who wants happiness? Does the body-form want happiness? Does the Spirit or Presence? Who wants happiness? Find out! Who is enjoying happiness? Who is expecting peacefulness? Who is under the pressure of fear? You must find out, because unless you undergo Self-enquiry or Self-investigation, and receive answers to these questions, you will not be able to identify yourself. And, sadly, you will continue with your tragic and painful, illusory life.

Roaming here and there, from Kanyakumari, to the Himalayas, and approaching endless Masters, without using any discrimination whatsoever, is totally meaningless, and it is such a waste of your time and energy. Reading countless books is also meaningless. Why? Because the Source of this world lies within you. “You Are the Source of This World.” But you do not know, that you are the Source. You are unaware of your spiritual existence. You are unaware of your immensity.

Whatever knowledge you may have, and whatever you may be doing to find happiness, is coming from your body-base. It is coming from your “I am the body-form” stance. You consider yourself to be the body-form, and therefore, your search is driven by the ego, which has assumed the pose of a separate individual. Accumulating knowledge only serves to enlarge the ego. Sometimes, you will experience temporary relief from the stresses of life, but this relief is only temporary because your base, your viewpoint, your perspective is body-based, and therefore, illusion. It is a fact, that the body is not your identity at all.

What is the purpose of spirituality? Prior to beingness, there was no spirituality. After the body expires, there will be no spirituality either. Find out how your spirituality is helping you – if, it is, in fact, helping you! What is your conclusion, after reading and studying all these books? There must be a conclusion. Don’t just keep reading and reading. “You Have Read All the Books, But, You Have Not Read the Reader.”

It is pointless to keep reading and reading, without identifying the Reader. Identify the Reader! Identify the Searcher! What are you looking for? Who is looking? What are you getting out of spirituality? There must be a conclusion. Is your knowledge practical knowledge? Will it stop you shaking and trembling on your deathbed? How deep does it go? Find out!

I am not telling you to stop reading books, or to stop visiting Masters. I am asking you to try and identify yourself. Ask yourself, “Who wants all these things?” “That Unidentified Identifier is Already Within You.” But we have forgotten our true identity. When the Spirit touched with the body, all your discomfort and dis-ease began. And so, your expectations for happiness suddenly arose. In India, we give honey to the young children. We give them something sweet, to make them feel better when they are upset or crying. Similarly, we try to make ourselves feel better using different means: comfort food, comforting relationships, stimulating company, family support, etc. We find whatever we can, to ease our discomfort, and ameliorate our suffering.

We carry with us some illusory hope, that we can obtain happiness from this illusory world. That is an impossibility!

Unless you try to identify your Selfless Self, you will not be able to find real happiness, true happiness.

Where were such words as “happiness” and “peacefulness” prior to beingness? The Spirit, or Presence, that is acting within the body, does not need these. Spirit does not need anything. We have so many needs and wants, simply because we consider ourselves to be separate body-forms with separate identities: “I am the body. I am somebody. I am Chinese. I am Indian. I am Japanese”, or whatever. This is not your identity at all. To identify yourself in a real sense, a process of reciting the Mantra and meditation is essential. With this practice, you will regain your Original Identity, called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, That you are! And, after Spontaneous Conviction, you will be able to face any challenge head-on. Nothing will be able to touch you because you will know, truly know, that you have nothing to do with this illusory world. You will be solid, immovable, and established in your own status, your true status of Ultimate Truth.

How were you prior to beingness? And, how will you be when you leave the body? You were formless, stateless, thoughtless. That Stateless State is your real Identity, your pure Identity. The outcome of the meditation practice, and consistent hammering is a return to your original state. This state has always been there. It has never altered. It cannot change because it is changeless. You have been unaware of your true nature because of the body-form, which covered over your Presence with layers of illusion.

When all the concepts of fearlessness, happiness, unhappiness, depression, tension, etc, etc, disappear spontaneously, you will be in that Original Stateless State – the way you were prior to beingness. The true purpose of spirituality is the removal of ignorance. Spiritual knowledge dissolves and demolishes all the body-based concepts. At present, you are not able to identify yourself. Instead, you are identifying yourself in the body-form, as the body-form. This is not your identity at all. The Naam Mantra is required to dissolve all the concepts. It will establish your true identity within you.

Reciting the Mantra will bring about miraculous changes. For example, currently, if someone criticizes you, you may feel upset and hurt. However, after Spontaneous Conviction arises, whether someone praises you, or abuses you, will be of no consequence whatsoever to you. Any castigations that are made in your direction, will just wash over you. You will remain untouched, and non-reactive, at all times, because you will know, not even know, but you will be convinced, that, “I am not the body. I was not the body. I am not going to remain the body”.

Adopting this new stance, and altering your whole perspective, means that you will have no cause to worry about anything ever again. There will be no more suffering. How will this be possible? Because you will know, that you have nothing to do with this whole illusory world. When you are convinced that you are separate from the world, you will be able to live like that. This knowledge is not theoretical knowledge, it is practical knowledge, that is to be applied to your daily life.

Having said that, even though you have nothing to do with the body-form, this does not mean that you are to neglect your body. Not at all! Take good care of your body and attend to its needs. Your parents and relatives, your work, and your ability to earn, are all part of your bodily existence, your earthly life. Live a simple and normal life. Work is necessary to earn money, otherwise you will not be able to survive. Don’t be a beggar, and expect, or demand money from anyone. Stand on your own two feet.

While you are attending to your routine, daily life, and to your physical health, it is most important that you attend to your spiritual health too. Be passionate! Have that burning desire to find out, “Who am I?” That is the question. That is the main question: “If I am not the body, if I was not the body, if I am not going to remain the body, then, who am I?”

“The Questioner, is Itself, the Ultimate Truth, the Final Truth. The Invisible Questioner is the Answer.” The Invisible Questioner has been called Brahman, Atman Paramatman, or God. Who, or what, is that Brahman, Atman, Paramatman? It cannot be defined. It is nameless. It can be compared to the space or the sky. Your Presence is just like the space or sky, but you are subtler, even more subtle than that. You are formless, omnipresent.

After Spontaneous Conviction: “I am not the body. I was not the body. I am not going to remain the body”, your Original Identity will be exposed. And then, in spite of living in this illusory world, you will remain unconcerned with the world. This is the purpose of spirituality.

2. Why is there fear?

It is the nature of the Spirit, because the Spirit only knows itself through the body-form. The Spirit does not know that, “I am Spirit”. Presence does not know that, “I am Presence”. It knows itself only through the body-form. It is attached to the body, and therefore wishes to continue with the known, ie, life in the body, for as long as possible. For example, say, you poured water over a few ants, they would immediately start running away, looking for an escape. Why? Because even the smallest, and the subtlest Presence, wants its body to survive. It is the nature of Spirit or Presence because the body-form is all that it knows, either as a man or a woman, animal, insect or some other being.

You fear losing the body because you have identified with it, and accepted it, as your Reality. The body is not permanent. It is not your Reality. You do not know yourself. You may know many things, but you do not know yourself. Spirituality teaches you how to identify, and know yourself in a real sense. Spirituality gives you the knowledge, so that you can emerge from ignorance.

We know ourselves in the body-form, and that is illusion. But, at the same time, don’t neglect your body, or your duties.

Carry out your responsibilities. If you are a businessman or an employee, or, if you have a family, attend to the tasks at hand. Attend to your responsibilities. However, at the same time, during the course of this life, try to identify yourself. Try to find the answer to the question, “Who am I?” Know yourself in a real sense.

Some day or other, willingly or unwillingly, you will leave the body, and the body will embark, on its last journey to the cemetery! But, the good news is that you are not the body. The Conviction that you are not the body will arise spontaneously, and then you will be free from any fears associated with the concept of death.

After Conviction, you will know that the body-form was never your identity, and will never be your identity. There is nothing to fear. What have you to fear? Who is afraid? Your fearful thoughts will pass. Don’t struggle with them! Let them go!

Meditation will bring your struggles to an end, so that all your fears will disappear for good. Spirituality gives you the strength and courage, the power and the energy, to live life free of struggle, to live life spontaneously. Live life bravely. Live with your light. Live by that light. Live as that light. Don’t be a coward! You will leave the body one day. No one can escape from this fate. So, prepare for that day! This is the idea behind spirituality, and the meditation practice because through meditation, all the illusory concepts, such as death, and the fear of death, will simply dissolve.

What is meditation? It means non-stop recitation of the Naam Mantra. This priceless Mantra came from Dattatreya. Theoretically, we know that, “I am Brahman”, but theory is not sufficient. Literal knowledge or bookish knowledge is not enough because theoretical knowledge can easily be forgotten. Therefore, material knowledge, literal knowledge, or dry knowledge, will not help you.

Be practical! Practicality is most important. Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj carried on working in his shop, till he was 70 or 75 years old. He did not leave his job, or abandon his duties, saying, “Oh I am a spiritual man. I am a Master. I will not continue with my business”. No! I was also working in a bank.

Stand on your own feet, and don’t depend on anyone else. Don’t depend on body-based knowledge, or, on your routine life. Don’t depend on spirituality outside of you either, because spirituality is inbuilt in you. You are already a spiritual man, or a spiritual woman. You are not the body-form. Why, therefore, do you wish to go here, and there, in search of spirituality?

So, “Be With You” all the time. You must find the courage to stay away from “bad company”, or those elements that can have a negative influence on you, and as a result, distract you from your Reality.

There are so many teachers and Masters in the world today, who charge vast amounts of money for their spiritual talks. I am not criticizing them, but, it is happening. Here, we are not running a business, or trying to profiteer from seekers. There is absolutely no commercialization of spirituality. Our Lineage places great emphasis on sharing this knowledge, free of charge. We are not withholding anything. We are sharing all the knowledge. How can you charge for knowledge that is yours! It is your innate knowledge.

We are pointing out that except your Selfless Self, there is no God. This is direct knowledge. It is very, very simple knowledge. All these Lineage Masters have shared the same, very basic, and simple knowledge, that there is nothing except your Selfless Self. So, why are you still going elsewhere to find your identity? Where is Peter? Where is John? [laughter] You are here, and nowhere else.

That which you have been searching for, is Itself the Ultimate Truth. Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. Be strong! Be spiritually strong – not egotistically strong. When you are spiritually invincible, (and physically strong), no one, absolutely no one, will be able to impress you with his own ideas or concepts.

When you know yourself in a real sense, it does not matter where you live. You can be anywhere in the world, living as the Ultimate Truth that you are. You need not go searching again. If you have sufficient time, you can visit this ashram. You don’t need to stay for lengthy periods. Just remember, that you don’t have to travel to Ranjit Ashram, [often referred to as Nashik Ashram] because “Wherever You Are, There is Your Ashram”. You may be living in a large townhouse, or you may be living in a small cottage, somewhere out in the country. Where you are is of no consequence. Your ashram is with you at all times, wherever you go.

You do not need a variety of exercises to identify yourself. All you need for Conviction is strict meditation. This practice is most important. It is the foundation. Through it, you will truly know that you are not the body-form. With this Conviction, all your fears will melt away, because you will no longer be attached to the body-form. You will know that deep down, at the very core of your being, you are eternal. You are unborn. There is no death for you. There is only death for the five element body.

3. Why is life so painful? I am depressed and worried

You find life miserable and intolerable because you have become a slave of your mind. Was there any depression, worry or pain, prior to beingness, prior to the body-form? Was there any anger? No! There was nothing. And, when the body expires, what will be left? We keep trying to extract happiness, from many different external sources because we find our body-based-knowledge unbearable.

The gist of spirituality is: “Except your Selfless Self there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman”. You are Atman. You are Paramatman. You are God! This means that everything is to be found within you. Happiness is not to be found in this illusory world. It is to be found in you because you are the Source of happiness. You do not know that You are Almighty God.

Directly, or indirectly, you are considering yourself to be the body-form. The body-form is not your identity at all. You are basically formless. It is an open fact. Prior to beingness, or, say, prior to a hundred years, you had no form. You had no knowledge about yourself. You did not know yourself at all. But now, because of the body-form, you know, that you are.

When the body eventually expires, dissolves or disappears, the known will dissolve back into the unknown. There will not be any trace of your identity left. Where will your pain, or depression be then? Who wants peace? Who wants a tension-free life? Who wants a fearless life? All these requirements exist because life in the body is, in fact, unstable and unbearable.

Why is a Master needed? Because you have forgotten your Identity. In order to have the Conviction that you are not the body, meditation is needed. Reading books, and listening to various Masters is not enough. It is only dry spirituality, dead spirituality. It is not practical spirituality. Here, we are teaching practical spirituality. Don’t abandon your work and family for spirituality. Your routine life and spirituality can co-exist perfectly. Be normal! Be humble! Live as a good human being. And, at the same time, try to identify yourself. This human body is such a golden opportunity to identify yourself in a real sense. Be careful not to miss out, and lose this valuable time, this wonderful opening, to find out who you really are.

Be firm! Be courageous and accept your Reality. I am placing Reality before you because your body-identity is temporary. You must be brave! Have courage! Yes, of course, there may be some depression or worry, and other calamities that may come your way, but even with these difficulties, know that they are only passing clouds. They are temporary bodily vibrations.

Don’t become a victim of your own self-created psychology, worrying all the time: “Oh! What will happen? What if this happens? What if that happens?” Nothing is happening. Nothing has ever happened, and nothing is going to happen because there is no doer, and there is no deed. You are not the doer. You have not done anything. You are unborn! Fact! Accept it!

Your Presence is like the sky or space. The sky does not know that it is the sky. Does it announce itself in this way, “I am sky?” The sky does not have any family members. Does the sky have a wife, a mother, or a father? Similarly, you are everywhere, like the sky. In fact, you are subtler than the sky because you can identify it. As you are listening to what I am saying just now, you may not believe it to be true, but in time, you will.

Don’t be anxious or depressed. You are unaware of your value, your true worth. You have great importance. “Your Presence is Invaluable Presence.” Your greatness lies within you, but you are ignoring it, neglecting it. You are underestimating yourself, always worrying, “Oh, dear! What is going to happen to me?” You are worried about the past, the future, or the present. And it is all a waste of your energy because there is no past, no present, and no future! These are the concepts. Nothing has ever happened. These are just the concepts, that we have blindly accepted. You can erase them now!

Don’t depend on anyone, or anything, outside of yourself. There is no need to say, “Oh God bless me”, because you are already whole and complete. You are completely independent. A Master is needed because you have forgotten your Identity. Your Spontaneous Presence is itself your Master. Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence within this body is the Master. I am placing this open fact before you. It is your Truth. Therefore, don’t torture yourself with pain, guilt or worry. Be brave! Have some guts! Everything comes and goes. It may be good or bad. Forget it all! Do not give so much importance to everything. Instead, find out how to come out of all these illusory circumstances.

To make this human life bearable, you have to identify yourself. You need not go anywhere to find yourself. Try to please your own Inner Master. The Master is within you. “The Finder Itself is the Master.” Read Selfless Self, I Am That, and other spiritual books, like Master of Self-Realization. They will help you. They are really good books for spiritual information and spiritual identification. They will help your Conviction.

A lack of confidence is causing your spiritual malaise. Be brave, and try to find stability. You are lacking in confidence and willpower. Don’t underestimate yourself. Be confident: “Yes! I can do it! Nothing is going to stop me”. Confidence is most important in life. Discard everything: “I am not the body. I was not the body. I am not going to remain the body”. And in time, whenever problems arise, they will not sting you, because you will be convinced that they are related to the body only – and you are not that! Whatever appears to be going on, is going on with the body, and therefore, cannot touch you. When you know that everything is illusion, you will find yourself forgiving and forgetting, anything and everything, that happens in your life. You will notice, an increase in tolerance and patience, as well as many other changes taking place.

We are worried and depressed, because we are measuring ourselves in the body-form. We have mistakenly accepted the body-form as our identity. This should be erased, dissolved. Everything will melt with meditation.

Meditation is needed at the initial stage. The Spirit is very sensitive, so when it is hammered with, “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”, over and over, again and again, a purification process takes place. You are hammering the ego, and saying, “You are a liar! You are not male or female, you are Brahman!”. This is how the Naam Mantra works. With repetition, the illusory layers that have covered your Reality over a lifetime, are gradually, and effectively removed. After continuous hammering, eventually, you will come to the realization: “Yes! I Am That! Why worry? Why be depressed? Everything is illusion. It is all a dream, a long dream. And you will laugh at yourself, pondering and reflecting on your life, asking, “Who was in pain? Who was depressed? Who was worried?

In the morning, we chant: “Shivoham Shivoham” which reminds us that everything is illusion. There is no Master, no disciple, no father, no mother. You have nothing to do with this illusory world. Shankaracharya says, “To say ‘I’ is illusion, to say ‘you’ is illusion, to say ‘Brahman’ is also illusion”. The entire world is illusion, therefore, considering yourself as the body-form is also illusion.

You may have accepted that you are not the body-form, but maybe only intellectually. This knowledge must be absorbed, and then there will be Spontaneous Conviction. There will be no more pain, depression or worries.

4. Why can’t I find happiness and peace?

There is always tension and fear around us because we are not identifying ourselves in a real sense. Since childhood till today, we have been identifying ourselves, as men and women. We have been trying to know ourselves, using the body-form. This mistaken identity, this illusion that you are the body-form, must dissolve. You may have some knowledge about Reality, that you are Brahman, but your knowledge is only literal knowledge. Knowledge of your Reality must be absorbed, and the only way this will happen, is through meditation. Meditation is essential. It is the base, the foundation.

What is meditation? It does not mean sitting cross-legged, with your eyes closed, nor does it mean reciting the Naam Mantra in a mechanical fashion. What is needed is your total involvement. Self-involvement will bring you closer and closer to Selfless Self.

You are to accept what the Master says, so that, slowly, silently and permanently, all the bodily effects that have obscured your Reality over a lifetime, will dissolve. Then, all your unhappiness, dispeace and irritation will simply melt away. Your troubling, illusory concepts will dissolve with meditation.

At present, you are posing yourself as a human form, when, basically, you are formless. In the beginning, you will need to put some effort into the meditation, until it happens spontaneously. The time will come when it will continue by itself, without your knowledge.

At the Ultimate Stage, you will forget about your whole illusory identity. And, in spite of holding the body, and attending to your work, and many other tasks, you will not be concerned about anything, even little dramas or big crises that come your way. And not only that, you will find that you experience exceptional happiness, and exceptional peace. You will no longer need to search for happiness from material sources, as you did previously.

Who am I? This is the most important question. Be serious, not casual! This human body offers a golden opportunity, to identify yourself in a real sense. But if your approach is a casual, half-hearted one, then, once more, you may see a similar type of “dream”. [dream refers to the concept of “rebirth”. There is no rebirth]

This is to be your last dream! Make it your last! We have become victims of our own concepts. These body-based concepts are to be erased, and permanently dissolved. The purpose of spirituality is to know yourself in a real sense. Spirituality invites the attention of the Listener within you. It indicates your Reality, that: “except for your Selfless Self there is no God, No Brahman, no Atman”.

Be strong! Be serious! Some visitors come here, and take the Naam Mantra. They listen to the Talks, but then... nothing! Because they are lacking faith and confidence, they are soon back on the road again, travelling, here and there, Guru-hopping. They are looking for more, looking for something else. There is nothing more. There is nothing else. “You Are Final Truth.”

There has to be a full stop! You have reached the destination. Everything is within you. I am repeatedly saying: “Except Your Selfless Self, There is no God, no Brahman”. “Why Keep Travelling, When You Are the Destination?”

“Everything is Within You. You Are The Central Point of this Universe.” Happiness and peace, are to be found within you alone, because you are the Source of happiness and peace.

5. Why is my peace disturbed?

Because directly or indirectly, you are posing as a somebody. You think that you are an individual, a separate person, a separate entity, an individual. The ego says, “Oh, she is disturbing me”, or, “he is verbally attacking me”. You are living as if you are a separate individual, and reacting to others, as if they are individuals too. “There is Peace. You Are Disturbing the Peace.”

You are Presence! You are not the body. That Presence is within the body. There is not “my Presence”, and “your Presence”. There is only One Presence. It is the same Presence that is everywhere. If you want to compare yourself to something, compare yourself to the sky. You are everywhere just like the sky. There is no difference between the speaker in this body, and the listener in that body over there. Accept Reality! It is your Reality. It takes courage to accept Reality because it demands a letting go, of everything that you have previously taken for real.

There is no past life, no future life, no hell, no heaven, because you are not a doer. Without a doer, there can be no deed. Some people say that because of their previous bad deeds, they have taken birth as a man or a woman, etc. This is nothing but imagination, concepts, illusion. There is nothing. There is no birth. There is no death. You are unborn. We are talking about the fate of the unborn child.

Take up the challenge, and accept Reality. Don’t be a coward, worrying, “Oh what is going to happen? Oh, what if he hurts me, or what if I lose my job?” You are not helpless. Be bold and fearless: “Yes! I can do it!”. Age is not a barrier to Self-Realization. It is not an excuse: “Oh, I am an old man.

What is going to happen to me?”, or, “I cannot change”. Spirit has no age. Is the sky one, or two hundred years old? Your Presence is ageless. Our age is only connected to the body.

To know yourself in a real sense requires total and complete involvement. Devote some time for yourself, so that you can meditate, for at least, one, two or three hours per day. All these saints devoted about ten hours a day to meditation. But nowadays, this is not possible. If you don’t have much time, at least manage one hour. In the beginning, practice is essential. Afterwards, it will not be necessary. When you first begin the practice, your mind will rebel against you, and not give you any peace. Just ignore these disturbances, and keep going.

The mind, the ego, and the intellect are there because of this body-form. Prior to beingness, they did not exist. Yet, we always give them so much importance, proudly stating: “My great mind, or my superior intellect”. But consider what is going to happen to the mind, the ego, and the intellect when the body expires? Everything will disappear. You are not the mind, the ego or the intellect. Everything came out of nothing, and everything will dissolve within nothing. You need spiritual courage to accept this knowledge, to surrender everything that you have known. “I can do it”, says my Master. “My Master says that I am Brahman, therefore, I am Brahman”.

To illustrate the strength of the ego and its identification with concepts, let’s say that someone called you a donkey [ass]. You would immediately feel like reacting aggressively. Correct? Why? Because you are insulted. The ego has taken a bruising. You have accepted the words and their meanings. Yet, when the Master says, “you are Brahman”, you will not accept that. Accept what the Master says. Nothing is impossible. Impossible is a word in the dictionary of fools! You are not a fool. Nothing is impossible!

You are not a doer. You cannot do any deed. But still, you continue to carry the burden of your human life. Change your view, change your perspective, and then, everything will be peaceful. There will be no tension! When you stop viewing yourself as a human being, there will be peace. Identify yourself: “Who Am I?” You are neither a man, nor a woman. You are Brahman. You are Ultimate Truth, which is not separate from you. Be realized, and make others realized. Come out of the darkness of ignorance!

6. Why are these bad thoughts coming?

Thoughts are flowing all the time. This is the nature of the body-form. The mind is a factory that manufactures thoughts. But because we are struggling with them, we get irritated. Don’t struggle with the thoughts. Accept the thoughts which are useful for your routine life. Otherwise, throw them out. It is very simple. Dissolve all these illusory concepts, and then your entire lifestyle will change.

This is plain knowledge, plain Truth. The language I am using here is very simple language, very basic language. Even if you think about it logically and intellectually, you can see Reality. You know, the Reality that is there. This body is not your identity at all. Some day or other, willingly or unwillingly, we will all have to leave our bodies. Try to identify yourself, and then you will feel secure, knowing that there will not be any more dreams like this one.

You are to discard all the concepts, including, “I am Brahman”. “Brahman” is also a concept because prior to beingness, you did not know, “I am Brahman”, or “I am Atman”. These particular words only appeared with the body-form, after the Spirit touched with the body. There was no language prior to beingness. We created language. It is illusion. We have created so many spiritual words such as Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. Prior to beingness, you did not know one single word. You did not know anything because you did not know yourself. It is a fact that, “You are Totally Formless”. As of today, you are formless. Listen to me! This form is not your identity at all.

7. Why do we have so many questions?

In spite of listening to the Masters and the teachers, and, in spite of reading many, many books, there is still no Conviction. And because we lack Conviction and confidence, we are left with many unanswered questions. Where were those questions prior to beingness? Where will those questions be, after you leave the body? Maya, Brahman, Paramatman, God, Master, all these spiritual terms are merely concepts, which came along with the body. This is not to say that they are bad concepts. But while you are using these concepts, I advise you to also identify the Invisible Listener, the Invisible Witness within you.

You can see different worlds, you can see everything in your dreams. When you are dreaming, and in deep sleep, you assume many forms: human beings, animals, the sun and moon, gods and goddesses, etc. You can manifest in various forms simultaneously. This means that the whole world is projected in a dream, along with you. You are watching the dream, witnessing the dream. When you wake up, you will usually say, “I had a very good dream”, or, “I had a very bad dream”. Who is videoing that dream?

Who, or what, appears in the dream world? It is your Selfless Self. The same thing happens in this life. You take the form of a human being, and through this form, you are able to see the entire world. Your Invisible Identity which is unknown to you, appears as your father, mother, sister, Master, God, etc, etc.

Your identification with the body-form, has created all this confusion which, in turn, has given rise to endless questions. All your questions are body-related. You are not the body. You were not the body. You are not going to remain the body. You are totally formless. I am telling you, again and again: “You Are Totally Formless”. But in order to have that Spontaneous Conviction, you need to follow a disciplined practice.

Continuous self-hammering is needed: “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”. Brahman is a name that has been ascribed to Ultimate Truth, the Final Truth That You Are. You are Brahman. You are Ultimate Truth. Brahman or Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. So, stop counting yourself as the body-form. Stop considering yourself as some kind of small, insignificant, powerless, illusory body-form. You are seriously underestimating yourself. You do not know your own greatness. The fact is that you are vast. You have tremendous power, strength and energy.

This knowledge is rare. It is priceless, but sadly, because it is offered free of charge, it is not really valued. If I were to charge something, then the response would be different: “Oh yes! This Master has given us great knowledge”. Such is the world we live in today!

I am presenting you with your Reality. I am placing the facts of your existence before you. I am not giving you any theories of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, or Master. These are nothing but words and names.

You are Ultimate Truth. You are Almighty God. It is a fact! Therefore, bow down to yourself! Bow to Selfless Self. The body is not your identity. Bow to That through which you know yourself. There is no difference between the Master and the disciple. Be with you! Uncover your strength!

We all have so many questions, thousands of questions. Why are these questions overcrowding your mind? Because the mind is rebellious. The crooked mind is rebelling against you, pinching and pricking you, stinging you all the time. The mind is a crazy mind. It is very crazy, and causes a lot of havoc and confusion, yet, it has no independent identity of its own. You are supplying power to the mind. The mind cannot function without your energy.

The mind, the ego and the intellect, are concepts that appeared upon your Presence. They have set up home in the body-form. Prior to body-based-knowledge, there was no mind, no ego, and no intellect. When the body expires, they will not be there either. Nothing will dissolve back into nothing. There is no need for you to make any special effort using the mind, in order to know yourself. Identify yourself! Just identify your Unidentified Identity. For the purpose of identification, and, to attain perfection, absorb the knowledge that the Master is conveying, and meditate. Meditate until you have Conviction. In what way is Brahman knowledge, Atman knowledge, helpful to us? How is it useful? It is useful because it reminds us of our forgotten identity.

As long as you consider yourself to be the body-form, you will continue to be swamped by concepts. As long as you are measuring yourself in the body-form, these concepts will keep on attacking you. Be as you were, prior to beingness. There was nothing there. When you leave the body, there will be nothing there. Prior to beingness, you did not know yourself. Everything that you are experiencing during this span of physical knowledge, body-based-knowledge, is illusion. You do not know who you are.

You have many questions because you consider yourself to be somebody, an individual, a separate entity. You should not have any questions at all. It is only because we mistakenly consider ourselves to be body-forms, that these concepts and questions arise. The questions keep flowing. Endless questions! When you know that you are not the body-form, the questions will finally dry up.

Everything is illusion, including you, and I. To establish the Reality that you are Ultimate Truth, a process of meditation, spiritual knowledge and Naam Mantra is recommended. Meditation, Naam Mantra, spirituality, spiritual knowledge, a Master, these are all needed to bring about Spontaneous Conviction.

The Invisible Listener, the Invisible Presence within you is Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. It has been referred to as Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, etc. The name is irrelevant because that which you are is nameless. Respect yourself! Your Presence is invaluable. You are not respecting your invaluable Presence. Instead, you are giving respect to the illusory concepts, holding onto them, and protecting them. In fact, you have become a victim of all your illusory concepts.

What is the remedy? It is simple: just have the courage to accept Reality. Reality is not separate from you. Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, or the Master, are not separate from you. But, in order for this knowledge to be absorbed within you, in order for you to have the Conviction that, “I am formless”, then, meditation is essential. The fact is that you are formless. The logical development of this, is that there is no birth or death. There is nothing to worry about. We are talking about the unborn child. You are unborn, formless, therefore, why worry about the fate of the unborn child? Spontaneous peacefulness will be yours after Conviction!

This is straight knowledge, direct knowledge. I am showing you the whole picture. Here, we are not playing any power games of hide and seek. The Master is not interested in gathering disciples. The Master is only interested in re-igniting the flame of your Inner Master. All you need, is to muster up the courage to accept your Reality, and to know sincerely and wholeheartedly, that: “I Am That!”

The human body offers you a golden opportunity, through which you can listen to your true story, and be reminded of your forgotten Identity. Listen carefully, engrave Reality within, and enjoy life! All your questions arise from the body-form. You are formless. There were no questions prior to beingness. There will be no questions after beingness. When you know Reality, the questions will evaporate.

8. What do we really want?

Everyone wants peacefulness. Every single being on this earth is looking for calm and tranquillity. We want to be at peace, and happy, free of the tension and crippling fear.

We all carry a fear of death. The concept of death frightens us because we consider ourselves to be the body-form. We are terrified of being extinguished, annihilated, and of losing everything, all that we believe ourselves to be. We cling to life, because we wish to hold onto everything that we think we are, have, and own.

The Spirit has accepted the body-form as its identity. That Spirit wants to continue life in the body because it knows itself as “I am”, through the body. It will do anything to survive, to perpetuate its bodily existence. When something goes physically wrong with the body, we will do all in our power to find a cure. We will search for medical specialists, who may be able to prolong our lives. Even if we are suffering from an incurable disease, the majority of us will choose, to survive for as long as possible. It is the nature of Spirit.

All our fears are rooted in the great fear of death. Death is a concept. There is no death. The body will expire, that is inevitable, but You will not expire. You are formless. You are immortal. When you identify yourself, there will be abundant peace and happiness. And, most importantly, the ghost of death that has haunted you throughout your life, will disappear, once, and for all. When you know that you are not the body, when you know that your identity is eternal, that you are immortal, you will no longer have any difficulty handling any problems that come your way.

What does this human body need? What do we want? Why are we visiting all these Masters and teachers? Why do we read all these books on philosophy, spirituality, religion? What exactly is it that we are looking for?

We are all looking for happiness and peace. We are looking for ways to overcome our difficulties. We are looking for answers. We do not know who we are. We are living our lives in a state of anxiety, depression, fear and dispeace. We are searching for meaning. We are asking “Why this? “Why that?” “Who am I?” We do not know. We keep searching and looking, but we are always looking in the wrong places. We are expecting to find the answers from outside of ourselves. We are expecting to find the answers from the illusory world.

You will not find the answer to your predicament, unless you turn within. “Look at You. Be With You, and Not With the World. All That You See is Illusion. That Through Which You See is Reality.”

Life in the body is intolerable because of its endless, disruptive demands and desires, that disturb the peace. “There is Peace. It is You Who Are Disturbing the Peace.” Concept after concept keep arising, telling you to do this, or do that, go here or there. And like a puppet, you blindly follow these dictates. Prior to beingness, we had no desires, no wants and no needs. Life in the body is insufferable, unbearable, because you are controlled by all the bodily demands that are in a constant state of flux. You know that you are not the body-form, but you are allowing the body-form to use up all your energy, and give you the runaround according to its whims.

If you are not the body, then, who are you? What are you? Find out! Ask yourself “Who am I?” Through Self-enquiry, one by one, you will eliminate all the illusory concepts, and know what you are not. You have made a huge mistake about your identity. You have forgotten your true identity, that you are Spirit or Presence, and not the body.

We have endless desires that we try to fulfil, to help us endure this illusory existence. We fulfil our desires to alleviate our pain and suffering. We seek out attractions and entertainment because we do not know who we are. We want sex, money and fame because it will give us momentary comfort and happiness. But we are unable to find any lasting happiness, permanent happiness, because we are sourcing our happiness from the illusory world.

At present, you do not know yourself in a real sense, therefore, all these desires are controlling you, overloading you. But, when you identify yourself perfectly, and realize: “Yes! I am nothing to do with this body-based knowledge. This body is only my external cover, and not my identity at all”, then you will find permanent peace and happiness.

“You Are Not the body. You Are the Holder of the Body.” This means that you are the Power, and the Source of Energy that sustains the body. Without Presence, your body is nothing but a dead body! The Holder of this body has no birth or death. Birth and death are mere concepts, that will dissolve with meditation. When everything has dissolved, when all the illusory layers covering your Presence have been removed, then you will live, an exceptionally peaceful, and happy life.

You will live life as before, ie, carrying out your responsibilities – but, with one major difference – you will live life knowing, that you are simply acting out different roles. You will no longer identify with the body-form, and, as a consequence, you will not be concerned with any problems that may come your way. You will be established in your Ultimate Truth. Permanent peace and happiness, without any stress or fear, will be yours! You will be living “in the world”, but, at the same time, knowing that you are, “not of the world”.

Meditate and absorb the knowledge that “I am not the body”. Meditation will reignite your Inner Master, who, in turn, will give you the guidance and instruction that you need. You will know how to act, and behave at all times, in a humble, and normal manner. Beware of hurting anyone’s feelings. If this happens, it is a sign that the ego is still in operation. Avoid causing anyone hurt and pain, in the name of spirituality. Beware of the subtle ego! Be calm and quiet! Reality will be absorbed within you, and then, you will know! You will no longer have any wants and needs because you will know yourself in a real sense. “What do You Want? Nothing! What do You Need? Nothing! Because Now You Know That Everything is Within You.”

9. What do you mean by “real happiness”?

Whatever happiness you have now is material happiness, external happiness, that provides you with material comforts. You find comfort from money, sex, publicity or fame. A variety of consoling, calming, soothing things, are there for the taking, out there, in the illusory world. They can offer you temporary happiness.

However, if you want to find real happiness, permanent happiness, you must identify yourself. You are Ultimate Reality. Reality is already within you, but you have accepted the body-form as your identity and your reality. A mistake has occurred. This mistake was not your fault. You were conditioned. Your Unidentified Identity is Ultimate Truth. You are Ultimate Truth.

Under these illusory circumstances that you find yourself in, try to know, “Who Am I?” This is the base, the foundation. You are the Unidentified Identifier which has been referred to by many different names: Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God. Reality is already within you, but, you are unaware of that. The body-form is not your identity at all.

You are depending on others to give you happiness. I have seen so many young boys leaving their family life, leaving behind their wives, their parents and children. They are going here and there, searching for someone who knows the secrets, someone who can tell them the truth, and give them happiness. They are suffering from the delusion that the truth lies outside of themselves, in the world, in the mind of someone who is superior to them. They are also deluded into thinking that someone can give them happiness. They feel that they are handicapped, less than whole, and therefore dependent on others. So, there is the mistaken conviction that, “if I approach this Master, I will find truth and happiness”. This is an illusory concept. There is no Master who can give you happiness. The Master does not grant any special favours.

The Master’s role, is one of inviting the attention of the Invisible Listener within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. The Master shows you that you are the Source of happiness.

Whatever is within this body, [Maharaj points to his body] is the same, as that within your body. But, you are identifying yourself in the body-form. This illusion has to dissolve. It is very simple. Why go here and there? You are amusing yourself, playing with spiritual words. This is a meaningless pastime: Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, maya, chakras”, this chakra, and that chakra – an utter waste of your time! Don’t fall victim to spiritual words, or become their slave.

It is an “Open Fact” that the body is not going to remain a constant, so you must identify yourself. Who is acting in this body? Who is experiencing in this body? The body cannot act without Presence. It is the combination of Presence and the body, that enables the functioning of the body.

Presence does not know that, “I am Presence”. The body does not know that, “I am a dead body”. Just like with an electric fan, if there is no electricity, the fan cannot work. But, with the combination of the fan and the power – the fan is able to function. Similarly, the combination of the body and Spirit, enables the body to function … and then, the talking starts [Maharaj chuckles] The body is like a magic box.

Try to identify yourself, “Who Am I”? It is pointless to just continue travelling here and there, like a spiritual tourist, and devouring books on the way. Meditation will make it easy for you to identify yourself. “You Are the Source of All Happiness, Real Happiness, Lasting Happiness.” Meditation means sitting down quietly, and then trying to identify what is there.

Self-enquire! “What is in this body? Who is experiencing the thoughts?” Thoughts are flowing, but who is experiencing thoughts? Who is watching the dreams? Who is the watcher that is watching the dreams, and watching this world? Find out! Think on it! No one is thinking any more. They are accepting everything blindly.

After meditating for some time, the thinker will eventually disappear. Nothing will remain. It will be like the way you were prior to beingness, That Reality will open up. When everything dissolves, nothing will remain. Nothing! No “I”, no “he”, no “she”, no “it”, no “Master”, no “disciple”, no “God”.

This Conviction must appear. You need not go anywhere to find real happiness. “Everything Starts From You. Everything Ends Within You. Everything Comes Out of Nothing. Everything Dissolves Within Nothing.” Why are you in search of finding nothing? “Know That There is Nothing to Know.” You will find happiness without any material cause through meditation.

You are unborn. The concepts of birth and death are only connected to the body. They are not connected to You. You are like a child who was never born, but who is always thinking, and worrying about his future!

“Your Invisible Presence is Just Like the Sky or Space.” It cannot identify Itself. We are trying to identify ourselves with the ego that says, “I am somebody”, and then, we are trying to identify our identity in the light of that ego. What is the ego? What is the mind? What is the intellect? These came along with the body. They are the subtle, functioning organs of the body-form. They are not Ultimate Truth. “Ultimate Truth is Lying Within You.” Real happiness is to be found only in you. It is nowhere else.

“Who Am I”? The conclusion is: “You are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God. The Master is not separate from you. That Masterly essence is within you. But you cannot truly know this without meditation. Meditation is essential. We are constantly being bombarded by concepts. They are pressurizing us. Meditation will bring us out of this vicious, illusory circle of concepts, which has entrapped us since childhood.

10. How did everything come about?

When the Spirit clicked with the body, you started to know: “I am”. And then, instantly, the world came into focus. This means that: “The Entire World is Projected Out of Your Invisible, Anonymous Presence”. If Presence were not in the body, who is going to be able to talk about the world? This means that you are the Principle behind these words. You cannot see the world without Presence. If there is no Presence within this body, the body is literally a dead body. A dead body cannot talk about the world, or Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, Master. Your Invisible Presence is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, Master, through which you are talking, through which you are able to see everything around you.

Try to “Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator Within You.” You are not doing that. What are we all trying to do? We are all trying to know what Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, is through various external sources. Who is trying to find Brahman? You cannot find what you already are. Brahman is not separate from you. Atman is not separate from you. God is not separate from you. “The Master is Not Separate From You.”

You have forgotten your formless Identity, therefore, you are roaming here and there, trying to discover the meaning of Brahman. You are Ultimate Truth. You, yourself are Ultimate Truth. This is the principle of spirituality.

When you are meditating, you forget about your body-identity. You see, the mind, the ego and the intellect came afterwards. They are subtle veils that appeared upon your Presence. If there is no Presence, where is the ego? Where is the intellect? Where is the mind? The mind, the ego, and the intellect appeared upon your Presence. They are illusory layers. You are supplying power to them. You have become a victim, a slave of that mind, ego and intellect. You are measuring yourself as “I am somebody”, and that is the illusion. Use discrimination, and try to find out: What is illusion, and what is Reality? “Everything you see is illusion. That through which you see, is Reality.” “I am Inviting the Attention of the Invisible Listener Within You”, which is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. That is your Reality. Stop ignoring it! Stay with the Seer, instead of the seen. Right knowledge will dissolve all the illusory notions you have about yourself, and will reveal your true Identity.

11. What is the meaning of life?

There is no meaning of life because you are basically unborn, and hence formless. What was your identity prior to the body-form? And what will it be when you leave the body? When the Spirit clicked with the body, the words came into existence. Words like “meaning”, “life”, “death”, etc.

Nothing has happened in this illusory world. As long as there is body-based existence, these body-based concepts such as “meaning of life” will continue to appear upon your Spontaneous Presence. The meaning of life for whom? Self-enquire! This question, like all the other questions, is body-based. You are unborn. You are not, were not, are not going to remain the body.

Your Presence existed prior to beingness, prior to the mind, the ego and the intellect, prior to everything. You are trying to apply reason and logic to your illusory life, because you have identified with the body-form. Your Reality has nothing to do with reason and logic. Find out who is living? Find out who is dying? Nobody!

12. So, my mistake was to identify with the body-form?

It was not your mistake. It was not your fault. You did not know any better. All our needs and requirements came along with the body-form. Prior to beingness, there were no desires and no expectations, for happiness or anything else. Who wants happiness? Who wants knowledge? Who wants anything? You are an illusion, therefore, knowledge for whom? You have mistaken your identity. In order to identify yourself correctly, we need guidance from an authentic, enlightened Master. The Master reminds you of your forgotten Identity.

A Master is only needed at the beginning. After Realization, the outer Master is no longer necessary. You will be guided by your Inner Master. The Master re-introduces you to your Ultimate Truth. Considering yourself as the body-form is what has caused all your problems and confusion, your unhappiness and dispeace.

You are not the body-form. “You Are the Destiny, the Terminal. The Final Destiny, the Final Terminal.” “There is Nothing Except Formless You. There is Nothing Except for Selfless Self.” Nothing Is There. That Conviction will appear spontaneously. Conviction is not intellectual Conviction, it is Spontaneous Conviction. This is the purpose of our life. This Conviction will banish all the disturbing and painful atmospheres surrounding you. The concepts such as pain, and peacefulness are just that, concepts. They have come with the body-form. There is nothing there.

The human body is an external cover, just like the clothes we are wearing. It has a time limit, and an age factor. There is no age factor for Ultimate Truth. Does the sky have any age? Can we say, “Now the Indian sky is twenty years old, thirty years old, or a hundred years old”? Of course not! The sky does not have any age factor. Similarly, you, the Projector of the sky, and of this world, have no limitations at all. We are unlimited. We have limitations only because of the body. You are not the body. Find this out for yourself, and accept it. This is a fact. One day or other, willingly or unwillingly, we will leave the body. The body will be burned, or buried. This is not our concern. Your first lesson is Conviction, the Spontaneous Conviction, that “I am not the body at all. I was not the body at all”. You must have this Conviction, while at the same time, not neglecting your daily, routine life.

13. Why is there pressure, to go searching here and there for Truth?

Because you are posing yourself as the body-form. It is a fact, even if you think about it intellectually, that the body is not your identity. When you leave the body, what is going to happen to it?

Your Presence is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. The Conviction will appear in you spontaneously, as a result of meditation and reciting the Naam Mantra. You have been devoting all your time to the illusory world, now devote some time for yourself! Dry, spiritual discussion is meaningless. Be practical, do your job, do your duties. I am repeating the same thing, over and over again: Don’t neglect your spirituality. Spirituality is not separate from you. Everything is within you. There is no need to go anywhere to search for Truth. “You are Ultimate Truth.”

14. How can we leave all our problems behind?

That is the question for us all. You meet a Master. Then the Master tells you what the cause of your problem is. He gives you a diagnosis: You are measuring yourself in the body-form. “Basically, You Are Formless. There Is No Form.” Why feel guilty? You haven’t done anything. “There is No Deed, There is No Doer.” There is no experience, and no experiencer. “Your Presence is Just Like the Space, or the Sky.” “The Entire World Appears Upon Your Presence.” “You Are Completely Unconcerned With This World.” “That Invisible Presence Within You, is the Ultimate Truth That You Are!” To effectively ignore, dissolve and overrule all these illusory concepts, serious, concentrated meditation is needed, in the beginning.

The Lineage Masters have given us some secret words, through which to hammer yourself. You are reminding yourself that: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am, I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. Why do we need these words? Because you have forgotten your Identity. As long as you are considering yourself as the body-form, you will not be able to identify yourself in a real sense. All your illusory problems will continue as before, along with your illusory suffering.

For us to gain the Reality, and know Ultimate Truth, we need to hammer ourselves. The principle of this hammering, is that the Invisible Presence within us is very sensitive. Whatever is impressed on Spirit, is instantly reflected. Considering this fact, the Master gives the Naam Mantra, the meaning of which is: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. Therefore, while you are continuously reciting the Mantra, and sitting for meditation, you are regaining your old memories, slowly, silently and permanently. And then, you will have strong Conviction: “I used to consider myself as the body-form, but now, I know it is not my identity at all”. “I Am Ultimate Truth, Which is Called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. It is Not Separate From Me.”

Previously, you were living like some sad, pathetic, little human being, holding the food-body. But the food-body has a time-limit. It belongs to the five elements. It is not your identity at all. When you undergo the process of meditation, some vibrations are created within you, that will effectively dissolve all your wrong concepts, your guilty concepts, your illusory concepts. You will emerge from the darkness, and live in the light.

When seekers start reciting the Mantra, some of them experience mood changes like depression, nervousness, irritation, etc. Contrary to what you may feel is going on, this is actually a good sign. It means that the Naam Mantra is working. It is having the desired effect. All the illusory concepts and impurities are being removed, one by one.

Keep at it! Continue with the Naam Mantra, and the meditation. And thereafter, you will have strong Conviction. Your painful life will dissolve, and in its place, there will be immense pleasure. You will feel it strongly: happiness, joy, elation, bliss. There will be no more pain because the illusory you is no longer operating.

There will still be good or bad moments in your life, little problems, or big problems, but you will emerge victorious, in spite of these difficulties. No matter what challenges come your way, your peacefulness will not be disturbed.

You will be happy, and you will stay happy. Nisargadatta Maharaj, Ranjit Maharaj, Siddharameshwar Maharaj, all suffered from ill-health, at some point in their lives. Even though their bodies were not co-operating, and in spite of their incurable diseases, they were always content, tension-free and happy.

Oftentimes, if we fall sick, suffering from flu, a fever, or something more serious, we will experience tension, accompanied by negative thoughts. But these great, saintly people stayed strong. They were untouched by anything. They remained firm, and solid, in the Stateless State because the Conviction that they were not the body was established. They viewed their illness in this way: “I am not the body at all. The body contracted this disease, not me!” “My Presence is Just Like the Space or the Sky.” The sky does not suffer from any kind of disease. They knew for certain that cancer, or tuberculosis, or any other disease, had nothing to do with their Ultimate Reality. Can the sky suffer from cancer or tuberculosis? It cannot! And, neither can you, because “You Are Subtler Than the Sky. Your Unidentified Invisible Identity is Subtler Than the Sky.”

You are posing as a man, or a woman. Think on it! Is it true? No one is thinking anymore. No one is discriminating. You are blindly accepting everything. Come out of all these self-imposed constraints! Prior to beingness, you were not a man or a woman. There was nothing there. You were totally Unknown, Invisible, Anonymous. And, when you leave the body, it will be the same. There will be nothing there. The logical deduction therefore, is that all your needs, requirements, and all your expectations, came along with the body. And they will inevitably dissolve, along with the body. This is easy to understand, but, it is a little difficult to maintain.

With strong faith in yourself, and strong faith in your Master, whoever he may be, that Spontaneous Conviction will happen. Have one Master only! Don’t change your Master. The Masters are like mothers. You don’t change your mother! Be loyal to yourself, and be loyal to your Master. Then, there will be enlightenment.

2 THE PRINCIPLE OF SPIRITUALITY

“You have accepted that which is not. Illusion means you have accepted that which is not. This body-form is not your identity. But you accepted “I am somebody”. The body is not going to remain constant. It undergoes change – from a child, to a young man, and then, to an old man. This is not your identity. Forget about it!”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

15. Why do I need spirituality?

You need spirituality so that you can know what Reality is. You need spirituality to realize that you are Ultimate Truth. Why is reading required? Why is spirituality required? Why is a Master required? Why is knowledge required? And for whom?

What is the use of spiritual knowledge? Prior to beingness or consciousness, spiritual knowledge did not exist. You did not know yourself. After leaving the body, you will not know yourself. The body is not your identity. The body was not your identity. And the body is not going to remain your identity. It is a fact. But we are not accepting this fact. When the Spirit clicked with the body, you accepted illusion, “I am somebody”, either a man, or a woman. This is not your identity. Who is holding the body? Who is talking from this body? Who is listening from this body? It is: “That Invisible Anonymous Unidentified That You Are.” Unless this Ultimate Truth is established permanenty within you, it will not be possible for you to know Reality. “Ultimate Reality Will Not Emerge Until All Your Body-Based Knowledge Has Dissolved.”

Prior to beingness, you did not know yourself. When the Spirit clicked with the body, knowingness began. You became aware of your existence: “I am”, and instantly, the world came into view, including your father, mother, relatives and friends.

Everyone is trying to condition, you with their own thoughts, their social culture, spiritual culture, etc. And as it is the nature of Spirit to easily absorb influences, it accepts all these illusory concepts: “You are a man, or a woman, a father or mother. These people are your relations. You are a Christian or a Hindu”, etc, and many other concepts, hundreds and thousands of concepts. We have created our lifestyle from illusory concepts. And, we have been living our life, trapped within the circle, of these illusory concepts.

We are downright ignorant. We do not know who we are. In this life, we have so many attachments to the body, the body-related relations, father, mother, sister, brother, husband, wife, son, daughter, Master, God. We have grown attached to everything. And, in the process, we have completely forgotten about Truth.

Where were all these attachments prior to beingness? There were none, of course. All our relations came along with this body. All our relations will dissolve, disappear, along with this body. We are sometimes, maybe too attached to our families. It is okay, as long as you know that the family is also an illusion, and that all you are doing, is playing a role.

At the last stage, you should be free from all desires. Just now, we have a lot of desires, a lot of needs, a lot of requirements because this illusory life, this body-based-knowledge often becomes unbearable. All beings including animals, have desires, but we are fortunate to be in a human form that is endowed with intellect. This gives us the ability to understand.

The mind means the flow of thoughts. There is a continuous flow of thoughts – good thoughts and bad thoughts. There are three types of thought flowing inside: “spiritual”, “commercial”, and “criminal”. Put simply, spiritual thought means that we are always thinking about the deities, the gods and the goddesses, saying prayers, searching for spiritual knowledge, Self-knowledge, etc. Commercial thought means consumerism, seeking enjoyment and so on. And criminal thought refers to hatred, struggle, conflicts, etc.

Spiritual thoughts will help you to establish your true identity, and deepen your Conviction. You will begin to master the thoughts, deciding which ones to accept, and which ones to reject. It is up to you. Everybody has so many questions, hundreds of questions that they wish to ask. These questions appear upon your Presence because you have forgotten your Identity. Basically, you are Ultimate Truth. You are God! Still, in spite of this literal, spiritual knowledge, you find yourself asking more and more questions.

16. What is the principle behind spirituality?

The principle of spirituality is: “Except Your Selfless Self There is No God, No Brahman, No Atman, No Master.” This means that all the Power, all the Energy is in you, and you alone. There is nothing except Selfless Self. “You Are the Central Point of the Universe.” This is the conclusion.

Who is holding the body? It is that Invisible Presence, or Unidentified Identity, called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. “The Master is Not Separate From You. God is Not Separate From You.” But, you are measuring yourself as a form, either as a male, or female form, when basically, “You Are Formless”. This misconception is the problem. Prior to beingness, there was no form. You are holding a human body that belongs to the five elements. The Holder, the Sustainer, of the body is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. “That” has nothing to do with this world.

Prior to meeting a Master, we considered ourselves to be body-forms, either as men or women. We were trying to extract happiness and peace, a fearless and tension-free life, from various different sources. However, with temporary and material sources, our happiness was always short-lived. We could only find fleeting happiness. There was little pleasure in life. And we were always encountering difficult and painful atmospheres. We were facing umpteen, different problems: family problems, financial problems, mental problems, physical problems. Then everything changed! Everything changes when you meet a Master, when you listen to spiritual knowledge, and practice meditation.

The principle behind spirituality is the removal of all the concepts, including, the “I am” concept. “I am Brahman” is also a concept. When all these concepts have dissolved, “There You Are Without Any Identity.” Listen to me! When all the concepts including Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, Master, disciple, etc, dissolve, There You Are. That Spontaneous Conviction is supposed to appear. After the Spontaneous Conviction, you will no longer feel attracted to going anywhere else to find Ultimate Truth, because you will know, that Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. You are Ultimate Truth.

17. Is spirituality useful?

That’s an important question! We are always quoting from others, talking about what Ramana Maharshi says, what Nisargadatta Maharaj says, what Vedanta says, and what all the other Masters say. Our human life is an unbalanced life. Prior to beingness, there was no awareness. When we leave the body, there will be no awareness. This is fact. And, in between, we are travelling through this miserable, human life.

Spirituality can make your life a pleasant, blissful experience. It can transform your life into an ecstatic one, that is filled with happiness and peace. Your life can be blissful, peaceful, and fearless, without any suffering.

Try to identify yourself. “Spirituality Invites the Attention of the Invisible Listener.” It teaches that whatever you have listened to, and whatever you have learned, is meaningless. It is second-hand knowledge. It is illusion. All these layers appeared upon your Presence. “Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence, or Unidentified Identity is Ultimate Truth”, (these are only words), where there is no experience, no experiencer, and no witness. In brief, it is the way you were prior to beingness.

How were you prior to beingness? You reply with a simple answer, “I don’t know”. After leaving the body, how will you be? “I don’t know”, you reply. However, behind that “I don’t know”, there is something that is Invisible and Formless, within you. But all the time, we are measuring ourselves in the body-form. Even with spiritual knowledge, we still view it from a body-based perspective. Spirituality is only useful, if it can help you to identify yourself. It is only useful, if it can help you to know yourself in a real sense.

Because of our long association with the body, we have strong faith, and a strong belief in this food-body. The food-body has a time-limit, but, the Holder of the food-body, has no limits whatsoever. We can understand this fact intellectually: “I Am Not the Body”. It is an Open Fact. The body has a lifespan of 60, 70, 80 years, or whatever it may be, and then, willingly or unwillingly, you must vacate the body.

We need to identify ourselves in a real sense. Presently, we are identifying ourselves in the body-form. That is illusion. Spirituality helps us to discriminate between illusion and Reality. “That Which You See is Illusion, but That Through Which You See is Reality.”

We frequently hold high expectations, thinking that: “If I go and see this Master, something will happen, like a miracle”. Nothing is going to happen, unless you visit your own Inner Master. You are to think about yourself very seriously because this is your time. You have a golden opportunity to identify yourself. What is the body? Just glimpses of “I”, glimpses of “I”. There is no birth or death, no destiny or past birth. There is nothing. Absorb this knowledge!

18. What is the secret of spirituality?

The secret is to remove the layers that are covering your Presence, so that you can know yourself in a real sense. The basic error is that you are counting yourself as the body-form, and that is to be discarded. It is a fact, that the body is not your identity at all. Dry spiritual discussion will not help you. You are Ultimate Truth. Spirituality shows you how to absorb this Truth, your Ultimate Truth.

All your body-based concepts must dissolve. And then, the Originality, your Originality, the Spontaneous Presence,

where there is no experience and no experiencer, will emerge. We need to use some words to try and convince the Invisible Listener. However, words are not sufficient to define, or expose the true meaning of spirituality. But, nonetheless, we are trying our level-best to convince you, so that you can leave behind all this illusion, and know the Reality.

What is Reality? Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence is Reality. It has no birth, and no death. Basically, you are unborn. You see, the moment that the Spirit clicked with the body, you started saying “I am”. And that “I am” was instantly coloured by many, many concepts when the world appeared, such as “I am a man”, or “I am a woman”, “I am somebody” – endless concepts.

The world is projected out of your Spontaneous Invisible Presence. It is like when you are dreaming, and the dream-world is projected. In this dream-world, you experience many different kinds of emotions, concepts and people. You can see the sea, the sun, the moon, the hills, and endless vistas. This world is projected out of your Spontaneous Invisible Presence, just like the dream-world is projected from you. This life is a long dream. Wake up from the dream!

When the illusory layers have all been removed, eureka! “There You Are: The Source of Happiness, the Source of Everything.”

19. What do we mean by spirituality?

Spirituality means identifying oneself in a real sense. Your consciousness is pure consciousness. But this consciousness is within the body-form, and therefore, it has created some confusion. This has resulted, in our imagining ourselves to be something else, something other, something different and separate, from pure consciousness.

You are that Invisible Unidentified Identity called Brahman, Atman, God, Master. This is the foundation of our teachings. Therefore, my Master says: “Except For Your Selfless Self, There is No God, No Brahman, No Atman, No Paramatman, No Master.” That Conviction will appear.

We have so many problems because of the body-form. No one is happy. The only way to escape from all these problems is with spirituality’s help. It is the only way, because Spirit is your Source, your foundation. What do we mean by spirituality? Spirituality is illusion, but through it, we can be free from tension and dispeace, and know who we truly are.

Your Identity is Unidentified Identity, Invisible Identity, Anonymous Identity. It cannot be defined by words. Words are only indicators. This is the base, the foundation of spirituality, for which you must have Conviction. Study the lineage books carefully. You have to read some books. But instead of analyzing the Masters’ words, try to identify, try to understand, what they are trying to convey. Nisargadatta Maharaj is there, and Siddharameshwar Maharaj, and many other saints such as Ramana Maharshi. The great saints have left us their high teachings, so that we can know who we truly are. Spirituality does not exist for us to accumulate spiritual knowledge, and stimulate the intellect. It exists so that we can identify ourselves. This is the meaning of spirituality.

20. What is that Secret Asset?

“You have a Secret Asset, an Invisible Asset, a Confidential Asset. That You Are!” Find out what it is! Sit quietly for a few moments, and see what happens: just glimpses of “I”, that’s all. Nothing else! This little glimpse of “I-ness” is caught up, and mingled with the body, which first of all causes us to accept the body as our identity, and secondly, drives us here and there, looking for happiness. What is happiness? What is peace? Why do we fear birth and death, and so many other things all the time? There is neither birth nor death. It is because we are measuring ourselves in the body-form that we feel we are going to die. All these concepts have been engraved in us. They have been wrapped around us, suffocating and strangling us since our childhood days.

Don’t read books that will distract you from Reality. There are thousands of books on spirituality. Everyone seems to have written something, according to his own imagination, and those concepts that have conditioned him. Don’t read books that are full of concepts, and descriptions about Ultimate Reality. These concepts will only serve to distract you from Ultimate Reality. Why? Because you are Reality! You do not need books to know yourself. “Look at you!” You know yourself better than anyone! You know that the body is not your identity at all.

You can hold the body, take care of it, and carry out your responsibilities. Don’t sit idly saying, “I am a spiritual man!” Attend to your work, and carry out your duties. You can do it! At the same time, try and concentrate, on that Invisible Concentrator within you, that is Ultimate Truth. This knowledge is very simple knowledge. You are Ultimate Truth. That is your secret asset which is, as yet, unknown to you.

21. What is Reality?

We are asking the seekers/devotees not to take on any concepts that may distract them from Reality. What is Reality? Everything that you see is illusion. That through which you see is Reality. The body is not your identity at all. “That Through Which You Are Identifying the World, that Invisible Presence, is Ultimate Truth.” In theory, you know that, “I am Brahman, Paramatman, God”. But, theory is never enough! Reading books is not enough. Books are important in the beginning because they give you a foundation, a base. Nevertheless, book-knowledge is insufficient, because it is intellectual knowledge, and dry knowledge. “This Knowledge Should Touch Your Heart, the Bottom of Your Heart, Yes!”

All your illusory concepts will be discarded, only when this knowledge touches you deeply. That way, Reality will be absorbed. We have so many desires. We are roaming, here and there, searching for comfort, happiness and peace. Yet, all these are body-based concepts.

What is Reality? I was not the body. I am not the body. I am not going to remain this body. The Invisible Presence within the body is called Brahman, Soham, I Am That. The Naam Mantra’s purpose is basically to indicate, and remind you, of your Identity at all times: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am.” Considering the sensitivity of the Spirit, this Mantra is very effective in removing all your body-based concepts. The meditation will construct firm and solid foundations. It will help establish Ultimate Truth in you. Meditation is an absolute must! You are not meditating enough, instead, you are giving your attention to second-hand knowledge. You are addicted to literal, spiritual knowledge, bookish knowledge.

Recognize your importance! You are not the body. You were not the body. You are not going to remain the body. You are Almighty God. But at present, you don’t believe that. You are still thinking that God is something different, something separate from you. You are everything. There is nothing, except formless you. But you have split yourself into two, i.e. the body-form, and Ultimate Truth. There is only Ultimate Truth, Ultimate Reality, Oneness. You can call it what you like, for it has no name. You Are That!

The illusion of individuality has created all your problems and confusion. Be simple, be normal, be humble. Don’t think so much! Digest whatever I have told you. Try to digest it.

Life is painful because we have placed so much faith and trust in this body-form. And then we find that the body-knowledge is intolerable, so we develop expectations, needs and requirements. Stop considering yourself as the body-form, and you will know Reality. Stop counting yourself as a body-form! Though you are holding the body, don’t be so concerned with it, or wrapped up in it all.

Slowly and silently, try to dissolve all these illusory concepts. Reciting the Mantra will stabilize you in Reality. Continuity is necessary. You can read books, but don’t accept everything in them. Be selective! Some books create more confusion than clarity. Read I Am That, read Selfless Self – and you will find everything completely clarified.

There are thousands of books. Everyone is encouraging their own variety of illusory concepts: “There is God, Brahman, Atman, and other concepts, to be found in the Shastras, in the Vedas”. The Shastras and Vedas are okay to an extent, but they are not Ultimate Truth. Why? Because your Unidentified Identity is Ultimate Truth. Your Unidentified Identity is Reality.

22. What is illusion, and what is Reality?

You must find this out. You can discriminate, and separate illusion, from Reality because you are a Master. You are your own Master, the architect of your own life. You are the decision-maker.

You don’t have any connection with this world, and you don’t have any connection with spiritual knowledge. All the requirements, all the needs, absolutely everything, is body-related. The world is an illusion. You are Reality – Formless You! Sift through all the illusion, and discard it. Learn to discriminate and discern.

Who wants peace? Who wants happiness? We need happiness, bliss, a peaceful and tension-free life, all because we are considering ourselves as body-forms. And basically, we are formless. There is no birth, no death, no destiny, no heaven no hell. There is nothing there. To emerge from all the illusion, drop each and every concept, and loosen your attachments to the body-form.

Don’t struggle with the mind. Don’t struggle with anyone else. Be tolerant! Tolerance is a sign of living the spiritual life. Forgive and forget! Have strong courage to accept Reality.

The mind is only a manufacturer of thoughts. The intellect makes a decision, and the ego implements it. It is okay, it is just the bodily functions, but you are separate from all that. You are totally different from that. You are the Master of the mind, ego and intellect. So start behaving like a Master, instead of a slave.

When your illusory knowledge has dissolved, whatever arises, will not cause you any problems, because by then, you will be invincible. You will be super-tolerant, super-courageous. The mind is separate from you. Your Reality is separate from the seen. Your Reality is invisible. You are a Master. Act like a Master!

23. Is duality an illusion?

Was there any duality, prior to this body-based-knowledge? And, will there be any duality, after leaving the body? We have accepted the illusory, bodily essence as “I am”. “You Are the Holder of the Body, Not the Body.” When you experience duality, it is because the subtle ego, the subtle mind, and the subtle intellect are present. There is, in fact, no duality at all. It is only because we have accepted the body-form as our identity, that we feel this sense of duality.

The Holder of the body has no duality. The Holder of the body, the Sustainer of the body is like the sky, and beyond the sky. But we have compartmentalized everything, named everything, and thus created this duality. We say, “This is my house, and that is the sky”. “This is the ashram, and above it is the ashram sky”. “This is the Bangalore sky, and that is the Mumbai sky”. The sky is everywhere. It does not divide itself into different countries, or places, or bodies, or buildings.

The names are different, that’s all. All these bodies have different names: male and female, but the Spontaneous Existence within these bodies is one and the same. Where there appears to be duality, this means that there is some remaining body-sense still around, “I am somebody”. Dissolve that body-sense! When you consider yourself as the body-form, there is a feeling of duality, but this is illusion. Absorbing Reality is of prime importance. The Holder of the body, is Reality. Absorb this knowledge!

24. What do you mean by identification?

Identification means being able to identify your true Identity, your Unidentified Identity. The seen is illusion. That through which you see, is Ultimate Truth. You are lacking Conviction, courage, and confidence, all of which are needed to accept the Reality. Even though we are reading spiritual books, we are not reaching the final conclusion, the Truth, which is: “I Am the Principle of This World”. Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God and Master are only words. They serve to indicate the Invisible Listener within you. Reality is not separate from you. What we call Brahman is not in the sky or space. Everything is Within You. We have created language and have ascribed names to everything, such as Ultimate Truth, the Invisible Listener, etc. You accept the names, the concepts, but not the Reality that you are.

We may read all the stories about “Krishna”, but we are not connecting with them. Instead, we take them literally. What is conveyed in these spiritual stories, the principle behind these stories, should impact you. They must move you, strike a blow to your heart, and touch you. When you read the Upanishads, get in touch with the essence. Identify yourself with what is behind the words, so that you recognize the Truth that is conveyed. What is described is your Essence, your Reality. And then, eureka: “Aha! Yes! I Am That”.

Identify yourself! Meditate, keep in touch with your Selfless Self, and then identification will be possible. It will happen. What is Realization? It is simple Conviction, Spontaneous Conviction, that says: “Posing myself as a man or woman, as the body-form is illusion. But, That through which I know myself, that Invisible Presence is my Identity. You are Ultimate Truth. That You Are!”

25. What is Conviction?

Conviction means “I am not the doer. There is no deed. I am nothing”. Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves back into nothing. This mistaken identity of “I am somebody”, which you are experiencing, will dissolve. The concept of the body-form must disappear because it is not Ultimate Truth. The Presence within the body, through which you are acting, is Spontaneous Presence. That you are, just like the sky or the space.

Visitors to the ashram, are always asking the question, “What happens to the body after death? What happens to the Spirit?” You know that death means leaving the body. But, as a matter of fact, there is no death, and there is no birth. Death and birth are concepts that are connected to the body-form only.

Supposing that in a dream, you witness yourself going through the process of dying. And then you witness your death. Just imagine this for a moment! Who is seeing the death of that body? Or, say, you see someone who has died in your dream, but when you wake up, that person is still living. What is true? Is that person alive, or dead? What is illusion? What is Reality? What is true, and what is false? Question yourself. Self-enquire, and you will find all the answers within you.

Your Spirit has exceptional power, and tremendous energy, which you have not yet tapped into. The Master is not separate from you. You are a Master. My Master, Nisargadatta Maharaj, says: “I am not making you disciples, I am making you Masters”. What is stopping the Conviction? It is your long association with the body-form. You are unable to accept Truth, because you are protecting all your concepts with all your might.

Whatever experiences you have in dreams, will disappear when you wake up. Your present life is just like a dream, a long dream. Convince yourself of this! You are your own Master. You are the architect of your life. Don’t encourage body-based questions. Stay with the Conviction. Convince yourself of your Reality because you are your own Master. You are in charge. The mind is always asking, “Why this, why that? Avoid all these questions. Find out what is true! The illusory world and all your experiences? That is all false!

In this illusory world, all the questions that we keep asking, are body-based questions. Nothing has happened. In a dream, you see and experience so many different things, but you don’t ask, “Why is this happening, or why is that happening?” It is a dream! It is false! It cannot be true. Similarly, your present life is not true. As long as there is Presence in the body, you will feel that it is true. After you leave the body, what will happen? There will be no questions, for sure. When we wake up from our dreams, everything disappears. Likewise, when this long dream of life disappears, nothing will remain. Does a dead body have any problems? When the body is buried or burned, what happens to the Spirit? You are the Holder of the body. The Holder is everywhere like the sky. Does the sky die or take birth? Just like the sky has no death and birth, in the same way, your Presence has no death and birth.

You are unborn. You are formless. That Conviction is bound to appear. It is not an impossible goal, but in the beginning, you must try to follow the Master’s instructions, and practice meditation regularly. You must make time for meditation, because without it, your foundations will be weak. This is very simple knowledge. It is free of charge. There is no need for any garlands, flowers or rituals. In India, there are all sorts of rituals: “Do this pranam, or that pranam”. Why? Prior to beingness, did you do any pranams? Did you recite any name, like “Ram Ram Ram”? When did you first hear about Ram?

All this is okay. I am not criticizing it. It is an aspect of faith. I am just asking you to Self-enquire! In a dream, gods and goddesses may appear, but as soon as you wake up, there is no sign of them. Where did they all go? You see many people in your dreams, but then, after waking up, they have all vanished. What happened to them? Did they go to hell or to heaven! [Maharaj chuckles] Nothing is there. There is nothing.

Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing. You must know that! Verify this for yourself. Your Invisible Presence is Reality. Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, The Master is not separate from you. How many times must I keep on shouting the same thing! And still, your crazy mind continues to create endless questions, “Why this? Why that? Why? Why? Why?”

Someone asked a question recently: “When I am meditating, I completely forget everything. But as soon as the meditation is over, my mind starts playing up, and I feel depressed”. I told him that what is going on are just mind-games. In this worldly life, everything is false. Your happiness is false, and your depression is also false. Depression, happiness and blissfulness, all these appear on your Presence. Your Presence is subtle. Does the sky suffer from depression? “Oh, this Indian sky is depressed”, or “the sky in Nashik is depressed!”

You will receive all the answers from within. Ask your Inner Master questions. You will be surprised at first, when the answers start to flow. Make your Master talk! Have a dialogue with your Master. In the beginning, you may not get the answers, but after intensive hammering, you will. And then you will silently exclaim, “Oh I am That!” You don’t have to go anywhere to find answers. With meditation, all your questions will be solved.

After hammering yourself with the Mantra: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”, or “Soham”, the Whole Truth will open up for you. You will be astonished by your capacity to answer very difficult questions.

Don’t change Masters. People are changing their Masters regularly: this Master, that Master, that other Master. It is meaningless. You are time-wasting because you are not giving any importance to your own Master, the Master within you. The Master is not separate from you. Receive answers from your Master, that is within the human form. The Master of the human form is the Holder, the Sustainer of the body. “That” does not have any specific identity. You cannot imagine, or guess, what it is like. Try to convince yourself, and then the Conviction will arise spontaneously.

26. How will Spontaneous Conviction appear?

The Spontaneous Conviction will appear after concentrated meditation. Meditation is the foundation, the base. The mind will not accept the meditation practice so easily. It will rebel in different ways, trying to put you off the practice. There will be thought-disturbances, making it difficult for you to sit for any length of time. Whatever happens during your practice, persevere with the meditation, and ignore the thoughts and feelings that arise.

Distractions will become fewer and fewer, if you don’t give them attention. If you pay any attention to these temporary vibrations, it is like adding fuel to the fire. View them as passing clouds, and just let them go.

Strictly follow your Master’s instructions in the beginning. The Master is an enabler. He is like a mirror in which you can recognize yourself, and know Reality. Have strong faith in the Master! You are already a Master, but you are not aware, therefore, an outer Master is needed to guide you, until you have Conviction. After Conviction, you will realize your Masterly Essence. You will be your own Master, and live like a Master.

This physical body is not the Master. The Spirit is talking through this body. The Spirit is listening through this body, but there is no difference between the speaker and the listener. If you have strong devotion and an unwavering faith in the Master, the Conviction will come.

At the moment, you are under the false impression, that you are separate from the Master. This feeling of duality comes from the influence of the body-form. Your whole perspective will change with meditation. When you realize what you are not, all these illusory divisions and separations, and imaginary dualities will dissolve.

After Spontaneous Conviction, there will not be any feeling of division between the Master and the disciple. When you see yourself as formless, and the Master as formless, any sense of separation, that was there previously, will dissolve. There is only Oneness!

All is one! There is only sky! For example, the sky within this ashram, the sky within that house, and the sky within that bathroom, is one sky only. All one and the same. We have erected the walls, and created divisions by naming everything, for our orderly existence in the body-form. But, they are all one and the same. When the walls collapse, ie, when there is the realization of oneness, what is left? Formlessness and omnipresence. Sky is sky!

The Spirit within this body, that body, or in everybody, is one and the same. It is everywhere. That Conviction will appear spontaneously, after reciting the Mantra. I keep reminding you of the wonderful opportunity that you have, to wake up from this dream. But you have become so comfortable and complacent in your illusory dreamworld, that you cannot even see, or value this opportunity.

It is a tragedy that you view the body as an end in itself, as if it is some kind of hedonistic machine. This kind of base existence makes you no different to any other animal. Use your intellect that you have been gifted with, to find out who you are! Recognize that the body is of great value, because it is the medium through which you can identify yourself. Don’t neglect this opportunity! If you do, your illusory concepts will, once more, create another dream. So, use what you have at your disposal, and give of yourself completely, devote yourself to the task of finding out who you are. Take this opportunity with all seriousness. Remove the concepts, before they are set in stone. When old age approaches, it will be much more difficult, even impossible, to shift them.

I am not asking you to neglect your family life, and sit for hours in meditation, no, not at all. Attend to your work. Eat whatever you wish. There are no food restrictions. If your body needs a particular type of food, then have it. The body is a food-body, therefore, keep it healthy. If you like vegetarian food, then eat vegetarian food. If you like meat or fish, then eat meat or fish. There are no dietary restrictions. You are not an ascetic, therefore, there is no need for any self-denial, or fasting, or renunciation. Everything in moderation is good for the body, while anything in excess, is poison. So, don’t worry about your diet! You have nothing to do with the food-body, but you do have a duty to keep it healthy.

Follow the teachings, that is most important. You are to grasp this opportunity with both hands, and take it very, very seriously. You will not be able to remove the concepts when you are older. At present, they are tender, however, if they are established, it will be much harder to shift them. Now is the time. Now is your time! Devote time for yourself. Move closer and closer to Selfless Self, then, the Spontaneous Conviction will appear.

After Conviction, you will be a Master in your own right. I guarantee it! With strong faith in yourself, and strong faith in the Master, Spontaneous Conviction is inevitable. That illusory sense of separation will disappear.

27. What is this body?

The appearance of the body is a play of consciousness. If there is no consciousness, there is no knowledge. If there is no Presence, there is no experience, experiencer or witness. Convince yourself of this fact. Have some Conviction! If you think about it intellectually, and forget about spirituality for a moment, you will accept the fact that you are basically formless. Intellectually, you know that the body does not have an eternal existence. Who is acting from this form? Who is performing all the activities? The body-form cannot do anything by itself. It is your Invisible Presence that enables all of the body-form’s functions. It is the pure consciousness. Prior to consciousness, there was Presence, which is Invisible Presence, Unidentified Presence, Anonymous Presence, that cannot be defined. It cannot be guessed. It cannot be explained in words.

We need language and words, to communicate thoughts and knowledge. Beyond that, words have no importance. Language has been created by us. There was no language prior to beingness or consciousness. Therefore, I am requesting all devotees to refrain from analyzing the words of the Masters.

I often hear seekers saying, “I don’t understand! This Master says this, and that Master says something different, which sounds completely contradictory to me. Which statement is correct?” Don’t analyze, or compare the different statements made by the Masters. This is a complete waste of your time, and will only cause confusion. You are not analysts! You are not on a course of comparative philosophy, or comparative spirituality. The words are not important. It is the power behind the words that can dispel the ignorance. Focus instead on what the Master is trying to convey. What did Ramana Maharshi, Nisargadatta Maharaj and many other Masters and saints convey?

You are trying to use the mind and intellect to grasp Reality. The mind cannot grasp that which is prior to it. Don’t overuse the intellect. Accept what the Master is placing before you. Let the Invisible Listener listen, and be reminded of its Identity. The Master is showing you your Ultimate Reality, your Ultimate Truth. He is not delivering a lecture for your intellectual stimulation. He is not presenting you with theoretical knowledge, but with pragmatic knowledge, your innate knowledge, Reality.

The Master conveys Truth, your Truth, Universal Truth, Universal Reality. Imbibe it! Don’t dissect it. Disable the intellect, and absorb the knowledge.

You are not a disciple. You are not a devotee. You are a Master. You are a Deity.

28. How is this world illusory?

When you leave the body, the illusory world will disappear. Nothing is there. There is nothing prior to the body-form, and nothing after the body-form expires. There are no Masters or devotees, deities or experiences. The world is a projection of your Spontaneous Presence. Prior to beingness, prior to a hundred years, how were you? You did not know yourself.

Through the consciousness, when it took the form of the human body, you forgot about your true Identity, your Source. The body-form deluded you into thinking, and accepting, that “I am somebody”. Okay, while you are inhabiting this body, you can use it, but at the same time, there should be Spontaneous Conviction, that you are not that. You know that you have nothing to do with the body because it is not your identity. Basically, you are totally formless.

There is only pure consciousness, without an experiencer, or any experiences. There is just Presence within the body.

We have various practices to lead us to Conviction. The Naam Mantra, meditation, reading books, singing bhajans and listening to the Master, are all useful tools or aids, to bring about Spontaneous Conviction, because you have forgotten your Basic Identity. You are Ultimate Truth, Final Truth, so stop counting yourself as the body-form. If you stay attached to the body-form, and ignore Reality, then, again, there will be the possibility of another dream, like this one. The appearance of the body-form has created all this illusion. It has obscured your true Identity. When the body expires, the world expires.

Just listen to me. I am using words to try and convince the Invisible Listener within you. I am placing before you, your Ultimate Truth. I am talking to the Invisible Listener, not to the body because I know that you are basically formless. There is no difference between the Speaker in this body, and the Listener in that body. The Master and the disciple are only external appearances. But prior to that, there was no Master, no disciple, no deity, and no devotee.

It is all one and the same. The sky is one. When you say, “This is China, and that is Pakistan. This is Russia, and that is America”, you have broken up the sky into parts, and called them by different names. The sky is one. Likewise, we have called the billions of bodies on this planet, by different names: “He is John! That is Jim”, or, “Sandra is over there”. These names are tags, labels for the body-forms, which, as you know, are all illusion!

29. If the Identifier is invisible, how do you identify the Identifier?

We are talking about the unborn child! Nothing has happened. Nothing is happening. Nothing is going to happen. We are using language to convey your Identity. Don’t let the words trap you. Don’t analyze the words. There is no “identifier”, no “invisible” and no “unborn child”. Everything is within you, without words, without language. Silence, too, is only an indicator. There is no silence.

Everything starts from you, and everything ends within you. There is no road. “Where All Roads End, There You Are.” So stop measuring yourself as the body-form. Hammer yourself with: “I Am Not the Body. I am Ultimate Truth. That Conviction Leads to Ultimate Truth”. It is a fact, but you are not accepting the facts. You are trying to extract spiritual knowledge through your body-based-knowledge. It cannot be done.

There are no spiritual roads. We have created all the roads, all the paths, all the ways, traditions and religions, that are there. There was no mind, no ego, no intellect prior to beingness. There was absolutely zero, prior to beingness.

Were there any roads prior to beingness? Did you know of any “Brahman” prior to beingness? And after leaving the body, where will Brahman be then? It is an open fact that there is nothing, even if you think about it intellectually. Needless to say, “Identification” is also another illusion.

30. If the Seer disappears from the body, what happens to the world?

What is the fate of all your concepts? What is the fate of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, disciple? Everything begins with you, and everything ends within you. Everything starts from you, and ends with you. This [pointing to the body] is a magic box, a miraculous box. All the miracles happen here. No one has the gift to perform miracles. There are no miracle workers. You are the miracle. All miracles take place within you. You are a magician! Don’t underestimate yourself, by taking yourself to be the body-form. You are formless. You are a formless magician.

Again, I am repeating the same thing again: You were formless prior to beingness. You are formless just now. And when you leave the body, you will be formless again. Birth and death are only concepts. No one has any experience of birth, and no one has any experience of death. To have this Conviction, you need to establish a strong foundation. The practice of meditation is essential. Give as much time as possible to it, especially in the beginning.

Previously, the Lineage Masters used to meditate for many, many hours. Now, I am only asking you to meditate for two hours, which you can divide into half-hour slots, if you prefer. You are to spend two hours meditating, until there is Spontaneous Conviction.

Always think about Reality! This is meditation. Remembrance of your Identity is meditation. Contemplate your Reality! Stay with your Reality, at all times. This is true meditation. Keep the practice alive. Question yourself! Have an inner dialogue. Your Master is hidden within you. Talk with Him, demand answers, and then, the answers you have been searching for, will start to flow. Establish this knowledge deep within you. Don’t just sit like a statue, meditating mechanically. Always try to question yourself. Get to know your Inner Master.

Forget about the world. You are the Source. After Conviction, signs of Realization will become evident, like forgiveness and forgetfulness, also tolerance, and a passion to know the Reality. You will not be attached to the world, and you will have complete devotion and trust. Even when unpleasant incidents arise, they will not disturb your peacefulness.

In the past, if someone was aggressive towards you, maybe, you would not be able to tolerate his behaviour. But, after Realization, even if something goes wrong, or does not go according to plan, you will remain at peace, calm and unconcerned. It will be similar to having a bad dream, but, then, soon after, when you realize it was a dream, it no longer bothers you. You can even laugh: “Oh, what was that?”

This life of ours is a long dream. Be firm! “Yes! I am That, I am Ultimate Truth, I am Final Truth. I am All in One. I am Brahman, Master, disciple, devotee. I am the Deity”. This is not imagination, it is a fact. It means that you are Almighty. You are omnipresent, everywhere, just like the space, or the sky. Stay with the profoundness of your knowledge: “That, I am! I am beyond the sky”. Your Identity is beyond the sky. The sky has some limits, but you are limitless.

When I was with Nisargadatta Maharaj, he used to say, “Listen to me!” At that time, we were like babies. We were not able to identify, and know the Reality, because we were immature. Maharaj used to say, “Listen to me! Listen to me!” He was addressing that Reality, the Invisible Listener within us – not the body, or the intellect. Maharaj was addressing the Invisible Listener within us. In this way, Reality was engraved.

In the same way, now, when you are listening, you may not understand what I am trying to convey to you, but, after some time, the penny will drop: “Oh! Master says it is my Truth! It is my Identity, my story, and not the story about any form”. Though you may not be able to understand this knowledge today, it is not going to go to waste. Somewhere within you, this knowledge is being implanted, engraved. The Listener is silently listening. The spiritual plant has been planted. It will grow, as long as you tend to it. You just have to water and fertilize it with the Naam Mantra and your devotion. You can sing the bhajans, or just listen to them. The vibrations, and the lyrics are extremely elevating, and indicate your Identity.

31. You say, that nothing has happened, and nothing is going to happen?

This whole world is an illusory world. Everything we know is illusion. When the Spirit touched with the body, the world was projected. When the Spirit leaves the body, the world will disappear. Therefore, all the knowledge that we have is illusion, including spiritual knowledge. The Naam Mantra is also an illusion, but it has great value, and will help us to remove illusion.

The Spirit is very sensitive. When the Spirit touched with the body, confusion started. There appeared to be so much happening with parents, society, and the world. You started believing in “I am somebody”. Then you adopted all the concepts. These were engraved in you over a lifetime. You posed as a “somebody”, and tried to live within the circle of illusory concepts. Then life became intolerable and unmanageable. You lived your life within the illusory circle, the circle of illusory concepts. But nothing was really happening because everything is illusion! Nothing has happened. Nothing is happening. Nothing will happen. Along the way, you heard about God, and how He takes care of all human beings. But that identification is not a true identification because the body is not your identity at all.

The Holder of the body is Ultimate Truth. That you are! But you are neglecting yourself, by considering yourself as the body-form. This body is a dead body. The body does not have any identity. You were a small child who became a young man, and then an old man. The body goes through these stages, but you do not go through any stages or changes. You are changeless. The subtle functioning organs of the mind, the ego, and the intellect, are also further layers on your Presence. Meditation and reciting the Naam Mantra will help you to come out of this whole vicious circle in which you find yourself.

32. What is Brahma Dnyan?

This means, identifying yourself in a real sense. We have identified ourselves as the body-form which is illusion. Knowledge of Ultimate Truth is essential, so that you can return to your original place. You just need to identify yourself in a real sense. Listen to this very simple thing: if you do not wake up in the morning, then there is no one to talk about the world, or about Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God and Master. There is no-one who can talk about anything. In fact, there is no one who can talk! This means that the entire world is projected out of your Invisible Presence. Without your Invisible Presence, there is no life, no action, no movement, nothing, nothing.

In the mornings, we chant “Chidananda Rupa Shivoham Shivoham”. It is a reminder, that everything is illusion: there is no Master, no mother or father, no brother, no sister, no friend, etc. There is nothing. That Conviction should appear within you spontaneously. Then, there will not be any kind of temptation to go searching for Truth, anywhere in the world. The knowledge that everything is illusion, will turn into Conviction, Spontaneous Conviction.

33. Why are there disciples and Masters?

Because you are unaware. You feel that there is something missing. You do not know that you are Ultimate Reality. You are missing. That something that is missing is yourself. So, the Master says, “There is Nothing Except Your Selfless Self.” There is no difference between the Presence in this body, and the Presence in that body. But you are not accepting the facts because of a lack of confidence.

In spite of your knowing the Reality, you are still posing as something other, “I am somebody”. Be humble, be simple, be normal. Do your duties, do your job. Spirituality is not about rules and regulations, or restricting any activities. It is about realizing that you are already free. Be free!

The disciple is unaware. He does not know, that he is, what he has been searching for. The Master convinces him of his Reality, gives him encouragement, and helps him to remove the illusory obstacles. The Master shows you God in you.

Be normal! Be a part of society. Do normal things. Don’t say, “Oh, I am a spiritual man, how can I eat?” Of course you can eat, because the body is a food-body, and needs food. What is most important is your willpower, and courage to accept Reality. The Master hammers Reality into you: “Except for that Invisible Listener Within You, There is No Brahman”. “Try to Identify the Invisible Identifier Within You.” These are words, but through words, I am trying to hammer the Invisible Listener with the knowledge of Reality: except your Selfless Self, there is nothing. Your Spontaneous Presence is Ultimate Truth, Final Truth.

Be Strong! I am not talking about egoistic strength. The body is an external cover. “I am Brahman”, or, “I am a Master, and you are a disciple”, are only assumed identities. For teaching purposes, I pose as a Master. There is, in fact, no Master, and no disciple.

“I am the Master, and you are the disciple” – No! It is not like that. “The Invisible Listener Within You, and the Invisible Speaker Within This Body, Are One and the Same.” There is no difference. The only thing is that you have forgotten your Identity. I am trying to invite the attention of the Invisible Listener, to remind you that you are Brahman. It is the Ultimate Truth. You are Ultimate Truth. Be firm, and find the courage to accept your Reality. The Master is there to guide the disciple. The Master shines a light, so that the disciple can find his way Home. Without a Master, we cannot identify ourselves, and know Reality. The Master knows all the details that will lead to your Spontaneous Conviction. He was once a disciple himself. Now he has flowered into Masterhood. The same thing can happen to you!

34. Why do we bow to the Master?

Because of my Master, I am now here, teaching. If I had not come into contact with my Master, I would not be teaching. The Master shows you God within you. The Master makes Masters of His disciples. If it were not for the Master, then we would still be in the dark, in ignorance, worshipping some external God, or other. I would still be visiting different temples, blindly worshipping this God, that God, or some other imaginary God.

God is not separate from you. To identify God, to see God, your Presence is needed. It is because of your Presence, that you are able to identify God. You are the father, and mother of God. It is a fact. The Master shows you your Identity: your Identity is prior to God. We bow to the Master because he is the impersonal, unmanifest Absolute, in manifest form. The Realized Master is free from the confines of the body-form.

The Master is greater than God. He is God’s God. We bow down to the Master because it is only because of him, it is only through Him, that we now know who we are. We are indebted to the Master, and because of this, spontaneous gratitude arises. Bowing to the Master keeps the ego in check, so that we stay humble. Through our reverence to him, we draw closer to our Inner Master.

35. Who, or what, is holding this food-body?

That Invisible Presence is holding the body. Where was that Presence prior to beingness? What will happen to that Presence? Of that, no one knows. We have so many concepts: last birth, future birth, destiny, and so on, with which we live our lives. All these body-based concepts, are supposed to dissolve completely. For this to happen, you need knowledge and meditation.

Our Presence is beyond our imagination. You can’t imagine how you were prior to beingness, or how you are going to be, after leaving the body. Even if you try your utmost to imagine, or guess, what this Presence is, it will not be that. All you will come up with are concepts. Dissolve all your body-based concepts. You do not have any specific identity. Your Identity is beyond the body, beyond, and beyond everything.

The body-form is not your identity. Your name, mind, intellect, and ego are not your identity. “There was Nothing There, And There is Nothing There.” All these body-based concepts came along with the body, and will dissolve along with the body. Countless concepts were thrown at us since our childhood days. They have left their lasting impressions.

You need a Master to dissolve them. You also need spiritual knowledge. Then all the add-ons, ie, all the body-based knowledge, that is not Ultimate Truth will be removed. And then, you will be totally out of concepts, and out of the circle of body-based knowledge, for good. When this happens, Ultimate Truth will emerge. “How You Were Prior to Beingness, and How You Are Going to Be After Leaving the Body, That Will Appear Spontaneously.” A Master is needed until there is Conviction.

Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves back into nothing. Body-based knowledge is unhelpful. Whatever knowledge you have, will die along with the body.

“Reality is Supposed to Be Absorbed Within the Spiritual Body of the Invisible Listener Within You!” When it is absorbed, you will have no concerns at all, even though you continue to live in this illusory world. You will live in a more detached way, without the strong connection to the world, that you used to have. You will attend to your work, and to all your duties, as you did before, but, and here is the big difference, even though you are attending to your duties, there will not be any concept around, of “I am doing this”. That Conviction will appear. All your concepts will dissolve, including rebirth, future birth, and past birth.

“Ultimate Reality, Ultimate Truth Is Not Separate From You.” For you to absorb this knowledge, satsangs, numerous talks, dialogues, conferences, etc, are all essential, until you reach Conviction. After Conviction, all these discussions will be rendered meaningless. If you glance within, you will see that the body is made up of five elements. There is also the mind, the ego and the intellect, as well as the experience of the Invisible “I” that mistakenly considers itself to be somebody.

We are holding the body, measuring ourselves in the body-form. That is not Reality. The Invisible Presence within the body is shapeless, and does not have any specific identity. It is called Unidentified Identity, or Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. That You Are. But in spite of this knowledge, you are not able to accept your Reality. And so, again you go wandering here, and there, looking to find Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master outside of yourself. Visiting all these different Masters is meaningless. Visit your own Master.

All the saints, including Jnaneshwar, say the same thing: “You are the centre of the world. If there is no Presence, who will talk about the world?” This means that the entire world is projected out of your Presence. Presence is not limited to this body. Presence is in every being. Lord Krishna says in the Gita: “My Presence is Everywhere”. That Conviction will appear.

So, who, or what, is the Holder of the body? It does not have a name. That, you are. To know yourself requires effort, and this is why we insist on the meditation practice.

Why is it so important? Because through it, there is ongoing hammering. You are hammering that consciousness with, “You are formless”, “You are Ultimate Truth”, “You are Brahman”, “You are Atman”, “You are Paramatman”. The Soham sadhana is perfect for erasing all the illusion, and establishing Ultimate Truth.

In our lineage, the recitation of the Mantra is given prime importance. The Naam Mantra has been tried and tested. The Mantra is most important, it acts perfectly. Take the Mantra seriously, for it has great power, and the highest value. Don’t disclose it to anyone else. Use it all the time, because this is your chance to know yourself. Put some effort into the practice at first, and soon, everything will happen spontaneously.

And, whatever happens around you, just ignore it because it has nothing to do with the Holder of the body, that you are! At times there may be some peaceful atmospheres, and at other times, some painful ones. It is of no consequence. It is just like when you wake up from a dream, you immediately know that it was a dream, you will know that you have not done anything because you are not the doer.

Your consciousness has taken birth, and projected a dream world. You are acting in that dream! When you know that it is a dream, you also know that you are not doing anything. Similarly, in this illusory world, when you know that it is an illusory world, all the actions are to be seen as illusory actions. Therefore, don’t give any importance to what you are doing because you know with deep conviction, that you are not the doer. There is neither a doer nor any deeds.

Again, I am repeating the same thing: do not try to define or analyze the Master’s words. What they wish to convey is the most important thing. Your questions are supposed to be practical questions, not theoretical questions. Stop this analysis! Withhold undue comments. This knowledge must be tasted, not analyzed. You have to taste the knowledge. Analysis, arguments, and counterarguments, are all counter-productive. You are to taste the knowledge. Try and ask practical questions.

When Presence touched with the body, the consciousness took possession of your body. You started living as the body, instead of, as the Holder of the body. You accepted illusion instead of Reality. Meditation will reverse the process, and correct the mistake.

36. Who is acting within the body?

I am pointing out that Invisible Presence within you that is Ultimate Truth. Your Ultimate Truth, your Reality is not somewhere out there in the world. The world is full of glittering attractions, that are there to pacify the body-form. Worldly entertainment is just like painkillers. Their effects will wear off quickly. Try to identify yourself, and then you will not only be pain-free, you will find permanent happiness.

The Invisible Presence acting within the body is Ultimate Truth, Brahman. It is not separate from you. You are the Source, the only Source. So, don’t feel tempted to go elsewhere. It makes no sense at all to travel around India, or anywhere else, in search of Masters. Why go here and there? Today, someone is coming from Rishikesh. He has been travelling in the Himalayas. There is no need for you to go anywhere because your Reality is within you, and within you alone. Why put the body under duress? There is no need to torture your body. This knowledge is very plain knowledge, plain Reality, ClearReality with no frills.

Who is acting from within the body? It is called the Invisible Concentrator. Who is listening? Who is watching? By themselves, the eyes are not watching. Who is listening? Who is watching? Who is experiencing? That Invisible Essence or Invisible Concentrator is called Ultimate Truth. Who is raising all these questions? That Invisible Questioner within you is Ultimate Truth. In the beginning, we are advising you to concentrate on the Concentrator. But at the Ultimate Stage, you need not do this. You need not do anything.

You are unborn. Try to understand how you were prior to beingness. You say, “I don’t know”. And, after leaving the body? You reply, “I don’t know”. That “I don’t know” response means that your Presence is there. Presence is needed for you to be able to say, “I don’t know”. “That Presence is Invisible, Anonymous, Unidentified Identity.”

37. Do we need God?

There is no need for any gods, goddesses or God. Saint Tukaram said, “All gods and goddesses are imaginary gods and goddesses”. They have taken birth, along with this body. “This Body is Not Your Identity at All.” The business of identifying gods and goddesses came with the body. As a matter of fact, we created these deities. You are not the body, or anything related to it. You are Ultimate Truth. You are Almighty God. Identify God within you. There is no other God but you.

38. Who wants Realization?

The illusory “I” wants Realization. But, you are already realized. Layers of illusion have covered over your Presence which has created a blockage, a barrier, that has stopped you from knowing yourself in a real sense.

Realization means Conviction. “Bow to That Through Which You Know Yourself.” The consciousness “I” is invisible, formless. You have mistaken your identity, and accepted the body-form as your Reality. As a consequence, there is an egoistic “I” that is influencing, and controlling you. Prior to that “I”, there was only pure Presence.

When you leave the body, where will that “I” be? For you to even say, “I”, Presence is needed. I am talking about that invisible energy within you, through which you can utter, “I”. It has been called by many different names – That you Are! But, the tragedy is that you are not able to accept it because of your long, and over-fond association with the body.

You are nobody. You are everybody. To know this, to absorb this knowledge, meditation is needed. “Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator Within You.” Don’t take these words literally. This is an indicator that says: “When you concentrate on the Concentrator, then the Concentrator will disappear”. Who wants Realization? The seeker? There is no seeker. Let the fire within you burn away all the illusory layers, and then, you will know, that there is Realization!

39. Who is the Master addressing?

The Invisible Listener within you. The Master reminds the Invisible Listener of his forgotten Identity. He hammers him with his Reality, his Truth. Who is the Invisible Listener within the body? Who is experiencing all these concepts and thoughts? After knowing the Reality, after having Conviction of this Reality, you will be in the Thoughtless State, with absolutely no thoughts. Even that primary “I”-thought will be rooted out. There is no “I” there at all. “I” does not have any shape or form. These are only words: “I”, “he” “she”, “you” – the medium of language to enable discussion, dialogue and conversation.

The Master is addressing your Inner Master. He is reigniting the fire, that has been covered, with the ash of illusory concepts.

40. “I” am doing this or that. Where is that “I”?

“I am” is doing this thing. “I am” is doing that thing. “I am” is seeing this and that. Where is that “I”? “I” disappears along with the body. Try to identify that “I”. If there is no consciousness to say, “I”, if there is no Presence, then, there is no-one who can say, “I”.

When “I” was projected, the world was projected. It is all a dream! Stop measuring yourself in the body-form. Be as you were prior to the body-form. You were formless. You did not know anything. There was nothing to do. When you leave the body, you will not be busy with any of your activities. Everything comes out of nothing, and dissolves back into nothing. When that Presence disappears from the body, will your dead body be able to act? Can a dead body tell you anything? There is nothing there.

I am labouring the point, so that you make a determined effort to correct the misunderstanding that you are a somebody. You are nobody, and you are everybody, because all forms are projected from your Spontaneous Presence.

41. Who says, “I am Brahman”?

These are also concepts. “I am Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God”. They are good concepts, connected with the Superior Ultimate Truth, with the Superior Power Within You. Various names have been ascribed to your real Identity, however, your Identity is beyond any name. For teaching purposes, I describe it as “Unidentified Invisible Anonymous Identity”. That is All! Beyond that, there is nothing.

Strange as it may seem, we need to do a lot of different things, in order to know that there is “nothing”. Knowledge itself, Brahman knowledge, or Atman knowledge, has its own limitations because we are posing ourselves as body-forms. “Basically You Are Formless. There is No Form at All.” The knowledge that you are Brahman is Brahman knowledge. It is limited, because when you say, “I am Brahman”, you are assuming a position, and therefore, taking on ego, when, in Reality, you are formless. Therefore, all our discussion is simply air-talk. We are like air, talking about air. It is not such a bad thing, as these dialogues help you to grow in Conviction.

We are always talking about different aspects of spirituality. We are talking about Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God and Master. The same message is conveyed again and again.

In fact, there is only one message which states without a doubt, that, “You Are the Supernatural Power. You Are Ultimate Truth. You are Final Truth. You Are God”. But, we don’t speak these words out loud. If we utter these words, we will find ourselves back in the ego!

When we say that, “You Are Beyond the Sky”, we are only using the sky, as an example of your formlessness and omnipresence. Therefore, don’t attach yourself to it. How you love your concepts! To be clear, there is no comparison between your existence and the sky. I am simply reiterating what my Master, Nisargadatta Maharaj, said: “If you wish to compare yourself to something, you can compare yourself to the sky. “You Are Beyond the Sky. You are Subtler Than the Sky.”

42. I don’t know why I focus on the darkness, and not the light?

You are so used to having problems, that it has now become your default setting. You are so used to pain and suffering, that it has even become a comfort zone for some of you. You have been going through life half asleep, and taking the dream for real. The seen is illusion, but the Seer is not. You, however, have been allowing yourself, to be dragged into the ups and downs of the material world. You have been living in a state of constant anxiety, always waiting for the next drama or crisis to appear. Come out of the circle of ignorance! Come out of the darkness! You are not what you have taken yourself to be for so long, a body-form that has been crippled, or paralysed, by the burdens of this world. Come out of the darkness! There is no “you”, and there is no “world”. It is a long dream. It is a long dream. Now it is time to wake up, and step into the light!

When you go deep, and deep, within Selfless Self you will find exceptional happiness there, that is like a kind of spiritual intoxication. This spiritual intoxication is flowing within you. When you taste it, your desires, for sex, fame or money will begin to fall away. You will feel complete, whole and fulfilled.

When you know Reality, Spontaneous Happiness will appear. It is the exquisite fragrance of Selfless Self. Enjoy it! Nothing can stop you from being intoxicated, apart from, a lack of confidence. Accept your Reality, and bathe in the light that you are. With full confidence, say, “Yes! Why not? My Master says I am Ultimate Truth, and therefore, I am Ultimate Truth”. It is simple, without any quibbling. All that is needed is simple acceptance, and trust in yourself, and in the Master. Have some guts! Let the calamities come! Let things happen. Bring it on! You are now out of the darkness of ignorance.

43. How can I identify myself?

This is a big question! And because we have been living constantly with body-based knowledge, we have become confused. Our minds are rebelling against us. All this illusory knowledge has to dissolve.

How will this body-based confusion dissolve? By no longer identifying with the body-form. Now you know better! Don’t give your attention to the illusory thoughts and concepts. It is like giving attention to the barking dogs. If you give attention to each, and every bark, you will become seriously disturbed. Self-enquire, and accept what the Master is trying to convey. Many devotees and saints were illiterate, and yet, they accepted what their Master said. They had no doubts. Put aside, the mind, ego, and intellect, and accept your Truth. Then, you will be able to identify yourself.

You are accepting this knowledge literally. You are accepting it intellectually, and egoistically. But ultimately, you are not accepting the knowledge, like this: “Yes! my Master says I am Brahman, and, therefore, I am Brahman!” After some time, your ego rises again, and questions the validity of what the Master says: “How can I be Brahman? Brahman is something other. God is something separate from me. God is a higher power administering this whole world.” And by the time you have dissected the teachings, the true essence that the Master is conveying, has been thrown out of the window.

You have developed so many concepts, including spiritual concepts, that you are very attached to, and are sadly, unwilling to surrender. Dissolve all your dearly-held concepts. Your Presence is Ultimate Truth.

44. What do you mean by refreshing our memory?

Do you have any questions? Any doubts regarding spirituality? If so, just ask. You have forgotten who you are, so we need to refresh your original memory of Reality. Spirituality is nothing special. Forget everything, including yourself. You have a storehouse of memories. You have collected so many memories since you were a child.

Forget all the memories! Dissolve them, because they are illusory, body-based memories of an illusory body-form! You are like a big computer that is full of data, with lots of wrong files, and viruses inside. To remove all these wrong files and viruses, first you have to clean up your computer. When all these files have been erased, the base memory, the substratum will self-reveal: “Except Your Selfless Self, There is No God”. When all the corrupted files have been removed, all that will remain is your original memory.

Forget about spirituality, and think intellectually! What is there? Question yourself, “how was I prior to beingness?” It is a simple question. Your answer is “I don’t know”. Okay, then second question: “how will I be after leaving this body?” The answer is: “I don’t know”. Prior to beingness: “I don’t know”, after leaving the body: “I don’t know”. You don’t know anything except “I don’t know” You cannot know anything, except “I don’t know”.

45. What is the mind, ego and intellect?

These three always work hand-in-hand, like a trio of bandits. The mind produces thoughts. The intellect makes a decision to implement the thoughts, and the ego puts them into action. The mind, ego and intellect have reduced your status to that of the body-form. They have created so much fear, anxiety, and confusion that you have been controlled like a slave. In brief, you are Almighty God. You are Almighty Brahman. You are Almighty Everything. Don’t count yourself as the body-form. It is such an insult. You are insulting yourself.

You are holding the body which is an external cover. After Conviction, you will not be concerned, or connected to the body. And, when you leave the body, there won’t be any feelings of distress, like, “Oh, I am dying! Oh, do something to safeguard my body!” etc. That thought will dissolve spontaneously. You will let it go! You know that you are not the body, and that it is not your property. This should be your Conviction on your deathbed: “My body belongs to the five elements. Take it away! I do not care for it. I am not bothered”. That Conviction will appear spontaneously, with the result that you will be free of all tension, and totally fearless.

After Conviction, you will not be concerned with the body, the world, and your feelings. Feelings may appear, they will come and go, but you will not be touched by them. Thoughts will come and go. Accept the useful ones, and ignore the rest. The art of living will appear within you spontaneously.

You will no longer be controlled by the mind, ego, intellect. You will be in charge. Behave well! Knowing how to act under certain circumstances, will become clear to you. Nothing is impossible! There is no difference between the Master, and the disciple. There is no difference between the deity and the devotee. These are the concepts. These concepts appear with the human form. The human form itself is illusion. You are beyond that. This illusory world, and what we are posing as, is all illusion. To absorb this knowledge, I will repeat myself again, and stress that meditation is essential.

All our concepts came with the body-form. And now, we have become afraid of them. We have accepted these concepts as “my thoughts” and subsequently, owned them. Therefore, we sometimes feel guilty, or we get irritated. If anything happens against our mind, we feel tense and depressed, “Oh that man is not a good man...”. There is jealousy and envy. Nisargadatta Maharaj often outlined the basics of behaviour: that you should not be jealous of anyone. There should not be any hatred, and you should not hurt anyone’s feelings. Don’t manipulate anyone, by forcing them to act according to your wishes.

The world itself is an illusory world. It is a dream! Prior to a hundred years, you were not there. After a hundred years, you will not be there. “Nothing Came Out of Nothing, Nothing Dissolves Within Nothing.” You know that there is nothing, but in spite of that knowledge, you are still struggling to find something. Bring that struggle to an end. Stop it right now!

You can do it! Reduce the force of the mind, ego, intellect. Capture these bandits! Master them! Don’t let them play havoc with your life. Don’t be their slave any longer. As I have said before, don’t follow the mind, let the mind follow you.

46. What is illusion?

Illusion is everything that we have ever seen, known, and experienced. The seen is illusion, the Seer, or That, through which you see, is Reality. That Godly Essence is in you. That Masterly Essence is in you. But, you are counting yourself as, “I am somebody. I am going to die”. You are ignoring your Reality. Instead, you see yourself as a weak and limited, frightened, separate entity. This is all illusion. You have reduced your identity to the human-form, and are roaming within the vicious circle of illusory concepts.

There are billions of bodies, but the principle is only One. You are omnipresent! There are many countries and houses, but the sky is One. That “somebody” has to dissolve. You are everybody, and you are everywhere. You are in every being. That Conviction will appear spontaneously with the guidance of the Master, and the help of meditation. There is no somebody. There never was. You are everywhere like the sky or space. All that you take yourself to be, is illusion. Your identity has been formed out of the sum of illusory layers, that were superimposed on your Presence. You have constructed your identity, using the building blocks of illusory concepts. Everything is illusion. But remember also that “illusion” is a concept. There is no illusion. We are just using this concept to discern your Reality.

47. What is sin?

Sin is also a concept that we have created. Was there any sin at your first birth? Just try to identify where sin came from. You have accepted all these concepts. You did not know any better. You were conditioned. But now that you know, you have to come out of the illusory circle. Rid yourself of all this illusion, and be free! Concentrate on the principle of the teaching: You were not the body. You are not the body. You are not going to remain the body. You are Ultimate Truth. This is the teaching in a nutshell. To truly live by this principle, we have meditation, bhajans and satsangs. They will all help you to regain, and embed, your Ultimate Truth: “Though I Am Holding This Body, I Have Nothing to do With the Body”.

I am repeating the same thing, over and over again. You already have the theoretical knowledge. You now need practical knowledge, which will only come with meditation. There is no Source, but you. There is only One Source! If you

visit many places, and many Masters, you may obtain some temporary relief, but nothing practical, or lasting. There is no alternative to meditation. Meditation will give you a hundred percent relief from all your concepts, including those powerful and loaded concepts, of sin and guilt. These concepts, in particular, have caused untold grief for so many innocent people, who have just accepted, what they were told by religious authorities. And then they carried their burdens of sin and guilt with them for decades. This concept of guilt, is like a cancer that spreads and destroys, all that is around it like wildfire. Forget about sin and guilt! Throw them out, and dump them with the rest of the garbage. They are nothing but concepts that have been used to control the masses.

Sometimes, visitors will say that their Masters have cursed them! This illusion has caused them to become fearful and anxious. The fact is that nobody can curse anyone. These are imaginary concepts. The mind creates untold problems. The Masters are very kind. They are just like the space, sky, or the wide ocean. In order to curse someone, there has to be an individual. There are no individuals. Can the Indian sky curse the Chinese sky? Don’t become a victim of your ideas and imagination, or those of anyone else.

Sri Bhausaheb Maharaj insisted on meditation practice. Through many years of experience, he knew that the flower of Self-knowledge would not open without meditation. You may have gathered so much theoretical knowledge, but you still do not have any practical knowledge. You must dig deep, and then, the knowledge will open up within you. In the beginning, you need to concentrate, and meditate, otherwise, the mind, ego, and intellect, and the body-based knowledge will creep up on you unaware. You will be distracted from Reality.

You are not a sinner. You have nothing to feel guilty about. You have not done anything. How can you? There is no doer. Forget about the food-body. Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator within you. Devote your maximum time available for meditation. If you are not able to sit for any concentrated period of time, you can recite the Mantra all the time, while

doing other tasks. Remember my words also! You are listening just now. When you go home, picture yourself sitting in front of me, listening, like you are now. Remember my words!

That Masterly Essence is already inbuilt in you. There is no difference between the speaker and the listener. Nobody is telling you this truth, because many teachers wish to exert power over vulnerable seekers. The Master is already within you, but you are missing Yourself. Therefore, I am hammering you all the time, with the same words. Nisargadatta Maharaj said: “Except for your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman”. Accept the Reality, and watch the show. Enjoy the movie! See the funny side of it all. There is no need to feel bad, or to consider yourself a sinner. Be free from all bondage.

Be spiritually strong. You are physically strong, but be spiritually strong. Nothing is impossible. Don’t become a victim of your mind. The mind is not so important. The mind is the flow of thoughts. It is always manufacturing more and more illusion, and giving you new problems with which to contend.

You have tremendous strength, unbelievable strength, but, you are not using that spiritual strength. Okay, that is enough! I am repeating the same thing, again and again, and again. Now, meditate on this talk. Absorb it! And then, put the knowledge into practice.

48. What exactly do we need to know?

The basic thing that we need to know, is that the body we hold, is not our identity at all. Because prior to beingness, prior to consciousness, our Existence was there but it was an unknown Existence, without an experiencer, or any experiences. Then the question arises: How was I prior to beingness, prior to consciousness? Prior to beingness or consciousness, your Presence was there. It was like the space or the sky. There was no awareness. Your Presence is everywhere. Everything is within you. You are Ultimate Truth. There is no power except you, Formless You. The Truth is that except for Selfless Self, there is no God.

49. What is spiritual awareness?

Spiritual awareness will come from spirituality. “I was not the body prior to beingness. I did not have any form”. When Presence touched with the body, consciousness came instantly. And then, the mind and the intellect took birth. This is the process. Amidst all of this, there is your Presence which is completely separate from everything else. It is Pure Presence, pure consciousness, which remains untouched by the body-form. There is nothing there.

Spirituality means that you ought to identify yourself in the midst of all the illusion. “Where do I stand? I am not the body. I was not the body”. The mind, ego and intellect are also illusory, subtle organs. Through a process of “neti neti”, and eliminating and discarding the illusions, one by one, we will arrive at Reality. When all the illusory layers have been dissolved, when everything has been removed, what is left is Reality. There you are – the “Naked Truth”.

So why do we need spirituality? Why visit the Masters? There is no difference between the Master and the disciple. That Presence, that pure consciousness, that is within the Master, and within the disciple, is exactly the same. There is no difference, and there is no separation.

Using language, we are trying to convince ourselves, “I am separate from this illusory world!” Why? Because there is the pressure of death, and the fear of death, which keeps gnawing, and eating away, at our peace and happiness. There is always stress and tension. To emerge from all of this, you need to identify yourself: “I am not the body-identity. I am not the body. I was not the body. I am not going to remain the body”. It is a fact that all these practices will result in your Spontaneous Happiness.

Prior to consciousness, how were you? At that time you had exceptional peacefulness, where there was no experiencer, and no experiences. Now, because of this body-form, we have a lot of experiences. There is so much to see around you, that you feel, “I am having this experience, that thrilling experience, this amazing spiritual experience”, etc. Something appears to be happening. It is a happening, and a non-happening, appearing upon your consciousness. If there is no consciousness, there is no happening, no non-happening, no knowledge. Knowledge and no-knowledge are in that consciousness. If the Spirit had not touched with the body, these concepts would not be there. When all your body-based concepts disappear, there will be spontaneous happiness and peace. Guaranteed!

50. After reading all these spiritual books, where do you stand?

There must be a conclusion. What conclusion have you reached, after reading so many books? You have read endless books, but have you read the Reader, the Invisible Reader that is within you? You are not to be found in books because everything is within you.

The principle of spirituality states that God is not separate from you. God does not have an independent identity. If your Presence were not there, who can identify God? To say God, your Presence is needed. This means that you are the father of God, and the mother of God. You may be surprised at what you are hearing just now, but these are the facts! If there is no Seer, if there is no Presence in the body, who is going to identify God? God is the supernatural power that is already within you, but you are counting yourself as the body-form, and that is an illusion.

What is the message given by the various Masters through their spiritual statements? And where do you stand, with regard to their message? It is most important that you know. Question yourself, and find the answers from within. Through meditation, you will prompt Selfless Self to dialogue with you, and answer all your questions. In the beginning, the practice must be a deliberate act. Keep it up until there is Spontaneous Conviction. Then, everything will be easy, and unfold naturally, and spontaneously.

“Where do you stand in the light of all your knowledge? This is the question. Who am I? After finding out, “Who Am I?”, that “I am” will also disappear. This is the purpose of spirituality. Jnaneshwar says, “I am going down, prior to, prior to, where nothing was, through which speech, language, and words are appearing”.

Four stages are involved in the process of speaking: Para, Pashyanti, Madhyama and Vaikhari. Para means the thoughts, the subtle thoughts. Pashyanti means the experience of the thoughts. Madhyama means coming from the mouth, instantly. First of all, the thoughts are appearing without your knowledge. Then, at the second stage, you experience the thoughts. Then it moves to the neck, and then it comes out. This is the spiritual process. There is no need to give it much attention! This means that: “That” through which you are talking, through which you are listening, that Invisible Presence is called Brahman.

When you are trying to identify Brahman, the Identifier will eventually disappear. There will not be anything remaining. That You Are! “Where Everything Ends, There You Are.” That Conviction will appear with meditation. Meditation means full involvement. Complete devotion is required. There must be commitment. You must be driven, burning to know, “Who am I?”

You can find out where you stand through meditation. You cannot know yourself through books. Force your Selfless Self to talk! You have knowledge, but if you just keep reading and reading, you will never reach a conclusion.

When you return home, carry on with the practice, with complete devotion: “Yes, my Master says I am Brahman, therefore I am Brahman” – end of story! Game over! The Conviction will come. There are no rules to follow, no expenses, no restrictions, or exercises. Just try to identify yourself, and then you will stay firm in the Perfection of your Identity. That is the purpose of spirituality. Identify yourself, convince yourself, and know where you stand!

To carry on talking for hours, will make it all meaningless. The principle is very simple. The entire world is projected out of your Invisible Presence. That You Are! The body is not your identity at all. “Be With You” all the time. Recite the Mantra given to you by your Master. Meditation will lead you to your Inner Master. It will bring you to your Inner Listener.

51. I do have knowledge, but, it is not practical knowledge

Everyone knows that the body is not going to remain. But, as long as you are attached to the body, the mind, the ego and the intellect, this knowledge will not be absorbed. You are under pressure from the mind, the ego, and the intellect. You are supplying energy to these. Your energy is most important. Your Presence is most important. You do not know your value. You are still considering yourself as a male or female. Your attachment to the body is a hindrance.

Listen carefully: the human body presents you with a golden opportunity to identify yourself. Though it is not your identity, the human form is the medium through which you can identify yourself. Use it for its real purpose!

52. What do you mean by “I don’t know”?

How were you prior to beingness? You cannot guess, or imagine, how you were prior to beingness. Everything is illusion, including you, and I. Everything we see, think, know, and understand is illusory. Our essence is beyond everything that we can possibly know. It is beyond the mind. We cannot know the unlimited, from our limited body-form stance.

All that we can know, is “I don’t know”. In that negative answer, lies a positive meaning. This apparently negative answer comes from a positive. There is something there, something that knows, in order to say, “I don’t know” “I don’t know” means: “I am Not in any Form. My Presence is there, but it is Invisible Presence, Unknown Presence, Anonymous Presence, Unidentified Presence, which is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master”.

When Presence clicked with the body, the world became visible. Prior to that, was there any body there? You say, “I don’t know”. And, after leaving the body, will there be any world there? You say, “I don’t know”. It is only because of the Spirit clicking with the body, that you are able to see the world.

Let me give you a simple example. If you strike a matchbox with a matchstick, you will see a flame. The combination of the matchbox, and the matchstick, produces friction which brings about fire. But that fire is already there. It exists everywhere, but, it is unknown, and invisible. This means that the unmanifest fire, at a particular moment manifests, due to the combination, i.e. the match striking the matchbox. The same thing happens when the world manifests. The combination of the Spirit and the body – the “click” of Spirit with the body, brings about the appearance of the world. Your Presence was already there. It was everywhere. But that Presence was unknown to itself.

When the Spirit clicked with the body, you became aware of your existence, and started saying, “I”. Prior to that “I”, that Invisible “I” existed. Your Presence is totally Anonymous, Unidentified, Invisible Presence. This means that your Presence is everywhere, just like the fire that is everywhere, in the example I have just given. Convince yourself in this way.

Teaching others is very easy, but teaching the teacher is very difficult. Hammer your inner teacher: “I am Brahman. Brahman I am. I am Ultimate Truth!” Hammer, and keep hammering, and then you will see the results. Accept your Reality! “Yes! I Am That!” Then all of your concepts will melt, including, “I am Brahman”, “Presence”, “Spirit”, etc. Language has served its purpose.

This is a fascinating process that will eventually lead to, “Yes! I Am That!” Don’t worry! It will happen with meditation. I guarantee it! An interesting example of this process is documented in the Dasbodh:

There is a large stone statue that is awaiting the skill of the Master Sculptor. There are many parts in this stone statue that need to be removed. They are not wanted. They do not belong there. Complete faith is needed in the sculptor, in that person that is chiselling and hammering, and removing all the parts that have blemished this statue. The original statue has been damaged by add-ons. The statue has always been there inside the stone! But, some skilful hammering is needed to remove the unwanted parts. Once these additions have been removed, the statue will be restored to its original glory. When the statue is humbly returned to its pristine state, nothing can ever stick to it again, or be added to it, or obscure it again.

Here, the Master is the sculptor who removes all the add-ons, that have covered over your Presence. He hammers and chisels, penetrating the numerous, unwanted, illusory layers. At the same time, you are also remoulding yourself with the Naam Mantra, clearing away everything that is not part of your Ultimate Reality.

Thoughts, concepts, habits, ingrained illusions that you have been living with all your life, may rear their head once more. That is to be expected. However, to prevent this from happening, you are to take some precautions. My Master, Nisargadatta Maharaj, says: “I am Not Making you a Disciple, I am Making you a Master”. You are to maintain that Reality with meditation. As I told you, meditation is also an illusion, but, in order to remove one illusion, you need some help from another illusion. To remove a thorn from your foot, you need to use another thorn. After removing the first thorn, then throw it out, along with the second thorn!

If, and when, concepts reappear, dissolve them quickly! It is very simple. This is rare knowledge, the rarest of knowledge. “It is Your Story, the Listener’s Story.” We are not talking about Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. But, you must have some courage to accept this: “I Can Do It! Nothing is Impossible.” Trust and faith, is most important. Trust and faith is lacking because we have a dual mind that pulls us in different directions.

Stay with “I don’t know”. This means, “I am formless”. It means that “I know that I have always been, and, I will always be.

53. Does spirituality mean dissolving all our concepts?

Yes! You have forgotten your Identity, and that is why you need spirituality. Prior to this body-based-knowledge, there was no spirituality, and no knowledge. There were no concepts of gods and goddesses, and no concepts of disciples and devotees. All these concepts of gods, goddesses, Masters, disciples, and spiritual knowledge, came along with the body. We need to dissolve each and every concept!

You could say, that the Spirit touching with the body, was accidental. When this occurred, you started saying “I”. Because you started experiencing this “I”, and feeling it, a whole new history came into being. This illusory history is filled with illusory concepts such as “I”, man, woman, birth, death, last birth, future birth etc. etc.

To come out from all this illusion, we need spirituality. And, once it has done its job, once it has served its purpose, it can be thrown out. Spirituality, like everything else, is an illusion. After Conviction, nothing is required.

Your Invisible Reality is speaking, listening, watching, acting. That Invisible Reality is currently not known to you. You need a Master, and spiritual knowledge, to make it known.

Let us scrutinize the body! The body belongs to the five elements. After death, it dissolves back into the elements. The entire body, including the mind, the ego and the intellect (the subtle body), is a creation of these five elements. “Nothing Remains Except Your Selfless Self. Selfless Self is Not Visible. It is Invisible.” It cannot be recognized or identified. That is why I always say that it is Unidentified, where there is neither an experiencer, nor experience.

What is Reality? You will find out! You will receive answers from within. Remember that, “The Master is Not Separate From You. Ultimate Truth is Not Separate From You”. As long as you are measuring yourself in the body-form, you will not be able to identify yourself – That You Are Ultimate Truth.

There is no search. “Where All Search Ends, There You Are.” You do not need to search for Truth because “You Are Truth.” Why go elsewhere to find That which is only in you? “Everything is Within You”, but you are not aware, and that is why you are roaming, and wandering, here and there. This wandering should be brought to a halt!

Show everyone respect. Take care of your body, and take care of your family members. At the same time, however, there should be the Conviction within you, that, “I Am Nothing to do with all this Body-Based-Knowledge. I Am Nothing to do with Body-Based Relations”. Shankaracharya says, “All these relations are fictitious, artificial, imaginary relations. My father, my sister, my wife, my son, my Master, my God. They are all a fiction”.

All these relations have absolutely no grounding in Reality because prior to beingness, there were no relations: no

father, mother, sister, brother, wife, Master, God, etc. There was absolutely nothing. When you leave the body, where will all your relatives and relations be? There is no “you”, and there is no you, that has any relations. That is Ultimate Truth.

When all these imaginary concepts of relations and relationships have dissolved, along with all your desires, what is left is nothingness. And, “Within that Nothing, There is Something That is Unknown”. “The Unknown Came Into Existence in The Known.” When the unknown became known, you announced your existence, as “I am”.

Spirituality has nothing to do with holiness or piety. Spirituality has one purpose, and one purpose alone, which is to erase illusion, and establish your original Identity, that you are Ultimate Truth. Talking incessantly is meaningless. Identify yourself! Identify yourself through meditation. Through it, a complete cleansing process will take place. So, please try to identify yourself. Meditation is a powerful tool, and it will effectively dissolve all your concepts, “Slowly, Silently, Permanently”. And then, Reality will open up within you.

You will begin to see with your spiritual eyes, and not with these eyes. You will be wearing God’s spectacles! And, you will come to know, that what you thought to be true, is, in fact, untrue. That Conviction will appear, and that is sufficient. You can read books, you can listen to anyone if you wish, but be careful not to become their victims. Nine times out of ten, these so-called teachers, are imposing their own illusory concepts on you, and thus creating more layers on your Presence.

Don’t accept any more concepts such as past birth, future birth, past sin, future sin, gods and goddesses, kundalini and so on. You are to come out of all these concepts because everything is a concept, and concepts appeared along with the body. Prior to the body? No concepts! That reality is supposed to be absorbed, engraved within you. That is enough.

Discard all body-based concepts. There are many different religions. All of them cause great confusion. It is said in the Bhagavad Gita “Discard all religions”. All religions are fictitious, imaginary religions. Religion is not bad. Religion exists to offer society a peaceful atmosphere because human beings are always in conflict, fighting and struggling with each other. Therefore, we have religion to establish some peace and happiness.

However, behind every religion, there is dispeace, conflict and struggle. Those who belong to one religion, declare it to be better than the rest, or the best: “My religion is greater than yours! This sentiment should not be there. All religions have their imperfections. Though they are good in principle, the way they have been implemented is very, very bad indeed. There is a great deal of hypocrisy. Behind the curtain of religion, there are power struggles, with everyone fighting each other. This should not happen!

Here, we are trying our best to incorporate and deliver all the necessary spiritual knowledge to seekers, through these discourses, as well as through the books such as Selfless Self, I Am That, Master of Self-Realization, and this book, Ultimate Truth. They are very good books, because they are pragmatic. They are trying to convince the “Invisible Listener Within You That Except Your Selfless Self There is Nothing”. “You Are Ultimate Truth.”

After Conviction, you can live anywhere in the world, you can be doing anything, eating anything without any problem because you will know, that you are not the body, and you are not the doer. Life becomes very, very simple indeed.

You have all the knowledge. Just convince yourself that nothing is true. Convince yourself, and you will have practical knowledge. Just now, you have theoretical knowledge – make it practical! Apply the knowledge! You have all the information! I have told you everything. Nothing has been kept from you. I am not hiding anything from you. Nisargadatta Maharaj, Ranjit Maharaj, Siddharameshwar Maharaj, and myself, have not kept one grain of knowledge from you.

Everything is open. I have placed all the cards on the table. Now you know everything. It is now over to you to implement, enjoy and absorb this knowledge. Go ahead! Do not delay!

The visible world will vanish along with you. Firstly, you are a small baby, then, you become a young man, then, an old man, and then, some day or other, willingly or unwillingly, you will leave the body. It is not your identity. When you know Reality, there should not be any fear around at all. If spirituality has done its job, you will be completely free from fear. You will be totally fearless, when your time comes to leave the body: “I am not dying. Death and birth do not apply to me because death and birth are body-related, and not connected at all to my Presence”. The Spirit/Presence within the body does not die. This will be your Conviction.

If an earthquake occurs, some buildings will start collapsing. And the sky? What happens to the sky? Nothing! The sky cannot collapse. An earthquake has no effect on the sky. Similarly, if anything goes seriously wrong with the body, it may die. But, You cannot die because there is no death for the Spirit. “You Are Immortal.” Through meditation, you will discard all the concepts: the concepts of God, Brahman, Atman, etc, everything. Conviction will arise spontaneously. This is plain talk, direct talk, with no in-betweens.

54. What do you mean by knowledge?

You have theoretical knowledge. You are playing with all these spiritual words. You are to be serious about spirituality, not casual. It is not entertainment. You are trying to know yourself, your perfection. Be perfect! There are so many spiritual words in use, but in Reality, there is nothing there. You are talking about the child that was not born – the “Unborn Child”.

Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing. Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, Maya, these are only words. “There is Nothing to Know, That You Are to Know.” You must know that there is nothing to know! There is nothing that needs to be known! Whatever knowledge you may have, came after the Spirit clicked with this body. And, as you know full well, your body-based knowledge is illusion.

If you have the inclination, you may write books, but only after Spontaneous Conviction. Writing books on spirituality, as a theoretical exercise, or for spiritual pleasure, is meaningless. It is nothing but mental chatter, egoistic chatter, intellectual chatter for those who only wish a spiritual massage.

You are to impress Reality within you because you are the cause of this world. If there were no Presence within the body, how can anyone write books? “Your Presence is Everywhere.” I am not discouraging you from writing books, but your spiritual life should be a practical life. First, have Spontaneous Conviction: Perfection, Perfect Identification, then, you may write books.

Writing books is very easy to do, when you have read hundreds of books. You can write any book you wish, but don’t write books filled with concepts. The spiritual market is already flooded with these. They do not help, but, instead, hinder the seeker, because they add confusion, and further illusory layers of concepts. The only books worth writing, are those that have the power to demolish all your beloved concepts!

Grow in spiritual maturity! “The Advanced Stage is a Thoughtless Stage.” There will be no thoughts, because everything that is illusion has dissolved. “Where Everything Ends There You Are.” Practical knowledge, therefore, means that “Your State is Stateless and Thoughtless.” Practical knowledge means that there is stability. You are solid as a rock, unwavering, so that, whatever comes your way, will not unnerve you. Nothing can touch you. Practical knowledge means that you live like the sky. You know that you are not the body, the mind, the ego, or the intellect. You don’t argue with others because you know, that there are no others.

This is the last destiny, the Terminal. There should not be any instability. The mind is a crazy mind! Don’t let it divert you from Reality. Be a Master of the mind, and take control of it. Be firm! Don’t let it continue with its mischievous ways. Be stable! After knowing the Reality, be stable, knowing that you have reached the destination. Be secure in the knowledge that you finally know the secret. “You Know That There is Nothing to Know!” “Nothing is There! Nothing Has Happened, and Nothing is Going to Happen.” There is no deed, and there is no doer. “Your Presence is Just Like the Sky, or Space.”

The sky does not know that it is sky. The sky does not have any spirituality. Bring all your spiritual travelling to an end. Travelling is not needed. Who is travelling? Where was the ego, intellect and mind, prior to beingness? And, where will they be when you leave the body? This trio came with the body, and will leave with the body. Forget about all these illusory layers on your Presence. Stay with Reality! To say “I”, is illusion. To say “you”, is illusion. To say “Brahman”, is also illusion, because this is an illusory world. And, in an illusory world everything is illusion, including yourself and myself.

55. What is spiritual knowledge?

Spiritual knowledge offers information. It is information about the searcher, the identification of the searcher, Listener or Reader. It is nothing more than that. Was there any spiritual knowledge prior to beingness? And, will there be any spiritual knowledge after you leave the body? No! Because spiritual knowledge is illusion.

Will that so-called, spiritual knowledge help you at the time of leaving the body? No! It is a fact. Spiritual knowledge just means identifying yourself. These are just the words. You have a wavering mind which causes confusion. Meditation is the cure because it cleans everything, clears out everything. I call it the Antivirus Software. Meditation is the antivirus software which will dissolve all your viruses, bugs and worms that have infiltrated your “big computer”!

After you insert this Anti-Virus Software, your entire make-up will be changed completely. It will be thoroughly cleaned, and completely washed out. All your desires and concepts will be rinsed out, emptied out. And then, Spontaneous Happiness will arise. Peacefulness will be there, without any material cause. Meditation is needed to identify yourself in a real sense. Correct? Start today!

To live comfortably with the body-form, you must exercise forgiveness and forgetfulness. Suppose a dog starts barking, do you give it any attention? Or, if a drunk person starts abusing you, do you give him any attention? No! Don’t give attention to the continuous flow of thoughts. Register the useful thoughts, and throw out the rest! Be ruthless! Don’t entertain every bark that comes to your attention. You are in charge because you are a Master, and so, it is your call. Start making the decisions and stop following the mind.

56. Who wants spiritual knowledge?

You are Knowledge! The Listener is Knowledge, the Reader is Knowledge. Don’t count yourself as the body-form. Who wants the knowledge of Brahman? Is Brahman there? Is Atman there? Is Paramatman there? Nobody knows about all of that. These are only specific names that have been assigned as pointers to your Ultimate Truth. They are indicators. Prior to beingness, did you have any knowledge that you were Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, or Master? No! You did not know anything.

Beingness started growing along with the consciousness. The stages are: Beingness, Consciousness, and then Awareness. Beingness is totally pure. There is nothing there. Then Beingness is converted in the consciousness, resulting in, “I am somebody”, and that is consciousness. And then, instantly, it takes form, manifesting as “I am somebody. I am the human body”. After this human body-consciousness, awareness follows. There is the conviction, “I am somebody”. This is just the theory, so, don’t give it too much importance.

However, one thing is for sure: the human body is not a permanent body. It has its own limits, and therefore, cannot be your identity because you are unlimited! There is no kind of body-form whatsoever, that is anyone’s identity because you are basically formless. What you see in this world is the Seer’s reflection. The entire world is projected out of your Invisible Presence. If there is no Presence in the body, who will talk about the world? Who will talk about spiritual knowledge?

Spiritual knowledge has one purpose only, and that is to help you identify yourself. Through meditation, through reciting the Mantra, you are hammering yourself, because you have forgotten your Identity. You are hammering yourself with, “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. And this continuous hammering, will open the door to Reality within you. And then, you will forget all about your bodily identity. That is the purpose behind meditation. All these concepts of depression, nervousness, loneliness, sadness, anxiety, etc, all these disturbing clouds, that have been intermittently obscuring the light from the sun, will automatically disappear for good. You are that sun that is always shining!

And not only will you be free from all these disturbances, you will have exceptional Spontaneous Conviction, Spontaneous Spiritual Intoxication. And you will remain in that field of Reality. Though some unpleasant atmospheres may be around, you will still be spiritually intoxicated. You will be oblivious to everything, just like a drunkard who is immersed in himself. If anything happens around him, he is unaffected, because he is self-engrossed in his own world.

Similarly, when you have this nectar of spiritual knowledge, you will be self-absorbed in Reality. If something undesirable happens, you will not give it your attention. This is a sign of Realization.

Listening to direct, spiritual knowledge is effective because you have collected a lot of information from various material sources. Everything has to be removed because it is not part of you. It does not belong to your Essence. These “add-ons” have corrupted your “big computer”. There is a need to de-program all your data. It is like when a computer has a lot of wrong files, corrupt files, you have to remove them with an anti-virus software. Meditation is the anti-virus software, through which you will remove all the illusory concepts.

Any more questions? There won’t be any questions because all questions are rooted in, and through, the human body. The human body contains the mind, the ego, and the intellect, the subtle, functioning organs. They come with the body, and they will leave with the body.

Now you know that the human body is not your identity at all, because you are basically formless. There is no form there! Accept and absorb these teachings!

Prior to beingness, you did not know yourself. After leaving the body, you will not know yourself. Prior to beingness, there was no knowledge. You did not know anything. When Presence came along with the human body, you were able to see the consciousness, “I am somebody. I am a human body”. This has to dissolve. It is very simple!

57. Why are there still some questions?

All questions are related to the body-form. Basically, they are rooted through the mind. And as you know, the mind, ego and intellect are themselves illusion. They are functioning organs. Your entire body functions through the mind, ego and intellect. Who is supplying power to them? You are! You are supplying the electricity, you are supplying the power. The mind, ego and intellect exist in this form only because of your Presence.

How were you prior to beingness? Unknown. After leaving the body? Unknown. This means that the unknown dissolves in the unknown. What you feel as the “known” is due to this body alone.

Basically, you do not know yourself. After leaving the body, you will not know yourself. Therefore, the unknown came into existence in the body-form, and after leaving the body, the unknown will dissolve back into the unknown. In between, you are posing yourself as: “I am somebody”. You are not somebody, you are everybody. You are everywhere, just like the space or the sky. So be with you, it is not impossible. Don’t waste your time, travelling here and there.

58. Why do these concepts appear?

The body is not your identity at all. Unless you accept the Reality that “the body is not your identity”, the experience of a body-form will continue to appear upon your Presence. These concepts create so much confusion, and then, the mind raises all sorts of questions. So many questions keep arising, and they are all body-based questions! I receive so many questions from seekers, and they are always body-based concepts. Melt, dissolve, demolish all your body-based concepts. This is the primary task at hand.

Your problems are all body-related, arising from this human life that is only a dream: depression, worry, sadness, loneliness, feeling unloved, fearfulness, stress, dispeace, unhappiness, misery, etc, etc. We have become fearful of everything. We behave like sheep, instead of lions! We have a lot of tension. There is no peacefulness, or blissfulness. And, we are always fearful of death. All these illusory concepts are to be demolished. Demolish all your concepts! This is the main goal of spirituality.

59. How can I discard all these concepts?

Spiritual Science teaches that you are just like the sky or space. The sky is everywhere. It is not limited to India. It is everywhere. The sky does not have any special identity. It does not have any individuality. It is vast. Your Presence is vast, formless, expansive. Your Presence is in every being. The bodies may all appear different, but Presence is One. How do you identify yourself? Meditation and reciting the Naam Mantra will hammer all your concepts, and then you will be able to identify yourself.

When the Spirit clicked with the body, the entire world was projected. It is just like when you are dreaming. Who created this dream world? You see the entire world. You see the sun, the moon, the gods, the goddesses, friends, your father and mother, all kinds of things, everything, in fact. Not even that, you also see yourself playing different roles.

At the time, you feel that the dream is true. You are enjoying it, or not enjoying it. It may be a good experience, or a bad one. Who is experiencing that dream? Who is watching that dream? “That is your Identity.” Because you are sleeping, there is a subtle, subtle Identity, which is called Brahman, Atman, Ultimate Truth. I am talking about that subtle, Unidentified Identity which is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, That You Are!

Though you are holding the body, when all your concepts have been discarded, you will no longer be concerned with the body. Absorb the Reality, your Reality! You have literal knowledge and literal conviction. Your Conviction is to be Spontaneous Conviction. Once you have that Spontaneous Conviction, though the thoughts – both good and bad – continue to flow, you will not give them any importance. They will not be an issue for you. You will treat everything, as you treat your dreams on waking up: “Oh! I had a good dream!” or “I had a bad dream!”, (knowing that there is no good or bad: “good” and “bad” are mere concepts!)

King Janaka, once had a very, vivid dream in which he was begging. He proceeded to question his stalwart, spiritual counsellors, “Is that dream true, or is this life true?”, “Was that a dream, or is this a dream?”. This story appears in the Ashtavakra Gita. Ashtavakra was a great spiritualist in those days. He was only a fourteen or fifteen year old boy then, but he had exceptional Realization.

Janaka asked him: “I had a dream where I was a beggar. And now, I am a king. The only question I have is whether this, (the world), is true, or that, (the dream), is true?” Ashtavakra replied, immediately: “This is false, and that, is also false”.

Everything you see in a dream is illusion. And everything you see with this body-form, is also illusion. But, the Presence in a dream, and the Presence in this body-form, are one and the same. Without Presence, you cannot watch a dream, and without Presence, you cannot watch this body-based knowledge. Therefore, your Presence is here, and it is also there. [there is no “here” or “there”] You are counting yourself as the body-form. That concept must dissolve.

60. Why do I need meditation, a Master, and all this spiritual knowledge?

Why? To know your Selfless Self! We know ourselves in the body-form, and that is illusion. You are Formless. All that you see is illusion. Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator, on the Invisible Seer, within you. If there were no Seer, how would you be able to see the world?

To say, “this world”, to say, “God”, to say, “Brahman”, to say anything, your Presence is needed. Presence is a prerequisite. That means that, “The Entire World is Projected Out of Your Invisible Presence”. You do not know yourself. To know who you are, you need to meditate. Meditation cannot be avoided. It will give you a solid foundation. Strong willpower is needed, too. Be determined and strong-willed, so that you will be able to discard all of your dearly-held concepts.

You will not be able to identify yourself, unless you dissolve all the concepts. There is always the temptation to visit different Masters. You won’t find anything. There is nothing there. Visit your own Master!

Reading endless books is meaningless. What is the purpose behind the books? What do all these spiritual books indicate? The gist, the summary of all these spiritual books is: “Except For Your Selfless Self, There is No God, No Brahman, No Atman, No Paramatman, No Master”. This is a statement of fact, but, you are reluctant to accept it. You have some doubts: “Why? How? Really? How Come? Are you sure?”, etc. This happens because the mind, ego and intellect keep stinging us, or pricking us all the time, trying to disturb and distract us from Reality. That is why the practice of meditation is essential, so that you can know, and accept Reality, and dissolve illusion. If you do not follow the Master’s recommendations and instructions, you will continue to be distracted by illusion.

This knowledge is not the knowledge of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. It is the knowledge of the Invisible Listener within you, that is Formless, and, not subject to birth and death.

We are not accepting Reality, therefore, we feel all this sadness and depression. You are trying to find the Reality, roaming here and there, from South India, to North India, looking for this Master, and that Master. And all the time, you are neglecting your own Master within you. You are like a spiritual tourist. Why do you still have the urge to go elsewhere?

The search is supposed to come to an end. When are you going to end your search? There must be a full stop! Why? It is simple: “Because The Searcher Itself is Ultimate Truth”. But you are ignoring “That”. You are ignoring “That” within you, and trying to search for a Master that is out there.

There is no Master! Who is the Master? You are the Master. Your Invisible Listener Is The Master. You have been neglecting yourself, underestimating yourself. Dive deep within yourself. There you will find the treasure. Know that everything is within you. Be calm and quiet. Your search is over!

Why am I sharing this spiritual knowledge? To identify your Selfless Self. This knowledge “Invites the Attention of The Invisible Listener Within You, That There is No Difference Between The Invisible Listener Within You, And The Invisible Speaker Within This Body”. Ramakant Maharaj, and everyone else, are one and the same. There is no difference, except for the appearance of the body-forms.

When, say, someone called Peter, leaves the body. We don’t say, “Oh, this is Peter’s body, Peter’s Spirit. Or, if Ramakant Maharaj left the body, we don’t say, “This is Ramakant Maharaj’s Spirit”. It is not like that! It is all one and the same. We are all one and the same. It is only for teaching purposes that I take on the role of Master, and you take on the role of disciple. But, there is no difference at all, except for the bodies. That Identification, that Conviction is supposed to arise spontaneously.

61. Why spiritual books and Masters?

We need to use different sources to identify ourselves. You have not found any peacefulness or happiness because you have forgotten your Identity. Since we are holding the body, there is instability, tension, fear of death, etc. We need spirituality to come out of the circle of illusory concepts.

Spirituality is a concept. “I am Brahman”, is also a concept. But, it is a concept based on sattva guna. It is a good and helpful concept, through which you can identify yourself. After Identification, after Conviction, you will not need any kind of practice, not even meditation, bhajans, or the Master’s help. You need the Master until you are able to stand on your own feet. You are under the mistaken impression that you are not whole. You think you are lacking, or handicapped in some way. You don’t consider yourself to be strong and independent, and therefore, you feel dependent upon the blessings of the Master, or God’s blessings.

The Master is not separate from you, but you lack this Conviction. For you to have strong faith that you are a Master, a process is needed. Meditation is required as a form of hammering. Breathing and concentrating on the tip of the nose, all these aids are there. If, however, you have full confidence that you are Brahman, then nothing is required. But this very rarely happens, as the mind does not easily accept Reality. And that is why a process is necessary.

Reading books, listening to the Master’s words, and meditation, are all needed to regain your original memory: “I am Ultimate Truth”. This Reality needs to be absorbed in you. The gist of all this is: Except for Selfless Self, there is nothing else. The Master and the disciple are the same. God and the devotee are one and the same. It is just the bodies that differ. This body is nothing but a dream body. The entire world is projected out of your Presence. Listen to me! Once you accept this principle, you will have no need of anything else. Even meditation and bhajans will no longer be necessary, as, after all, everything came out of nothing.

There is confusion around because of the mind, the ego and the intellect. You cannot find peace or happiness. You feel insecure and fearful. To come out of this bad patch, you have to undergo meditation. It is unavoidable. Meditation will help you. It will enable the attainment of direct self-knowledge. Read books that contain direct information, direct, spontaneous knowledge. Don’t read theoretical books! They will only confuse you further. Nisargadatta Maharaj, Siddharameshwar Maharaj, Ranjit Maharaj, all these saints have placed before seekers, the Ultimate Truth. They were not simply talking about Ultimate Truth, they were living the Ultimate Truth.

Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. God is not separate from you. The Master is not separate from you. This whole process, and all this theory, is there solely to convince you that you are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. You are God. You are the Master. This is short and sweet, spiritual knowledge.

62. Why is a Master Needed?

The Master shows you Ultimate Truth, just like in the famous spiritual story, of the lion who grew up with the sheep. A lion cub is brought up amongst a flock of sheep, and so, inevitably, it also starts to consider itself to be a sheep. When a lion in the forest sees the small cub in the company of sheep, he asks: “What are you doing with the sheep? You are a lion, the king of the forest, the king of all animals!” The cub replies, “No, no, how can I be a lion king? I am a sheep!” So, the lion shows him the different parts of his body. When the cub is finally convinced, with self-recognition and realization, he says, “Aha! So, I am a lion!” In a similar way, the Master shows you that you are Ultimate Truth. You are Brahman.

Be serious! Recite the Mantra, and sit for meditation. After Conviction, there will not be any further need of this. That Identification, that Conviction is only possible with meditation. Dry knowledge and dry talk regarding spirituality, and dry listening, are all totally meaningless. You must start with you, because you are the starting point. You are the central point. “Everything Starts From You, and Everything Ends Within You.”

It is just like this body has been called a “man”, so you are acting as a man. In a similar way, the Holder of the body is called Brahman. So, you are acting as Brahman, and are unconcerned about everything else. There is no doer, and there is no deed. There is no experiencer and no experiences. There is no witness either.

Does the sky experience anything: “I am the sky”? No! You are the projector of the sky, the projector of the world. That Identification, that Conviction will arise, if you undergo the meditation. Dry knowledge, dry spiritual talk, and dry listening are all pointless. You have to start with yourself, start from you!

The Master is needed, so that we can not only know Reality, but live Reality, live like Brahman! We are always under pressure from the body, the mind, the ego, and the intellect. Thoughts are racing all the time, trying to leave their impressions behind. Follow Your Inner Master! Listen to your Inner Master. Through the meditation, you are giving encouragement, strength and power to your Inner Master, to open the door to Truth. Thereafter, your external identity will dissolve. There will not be any remnants left of your former, illusory identity. You merge with Selfless Self. “You Become One With Your Selfless Self.”

63. What exactly is this body-form?

Forget about spirituality for the time-being. Apply simple logic, and you will see that the body-form is a temporary carrier. Sit calmly and quietly. What is in the body? Nothing but glimpses of “I”, just glimpses of “I”. The body is not eternal, that’s for sure. It is limited by time, age, etc. Don’t give anything too much attention. Whatever appears upon your Presence, whether it is agreeable or disagreeable. The body belongs to the five elements. When there is an imbalance of the five elements, you will feel it. Sometimes you feel depressed, or there’s an unpleasant atmosphere. This happens because you are holding the body. If you are suffering from a cold, there will be some weakness. Understand that whatever bodily feelings you may have are fleeting. They will come, they will go, changing all the time, just like the seasons.

Stay loyal to your Master. If you still have the urge to visit other Masters, Self-enquire, and find out what it is that you are still looking for. This knowledge that I have shared with you is the Final Truth. It is direct knowledge. There is nothing beyond. If you visit other Masters, you will soon be back in the ditch of illusory, conceptual knowledge. The clouds come, and the clouds go, but you are not going anywhere. You are there, and there only.

You are to convince yourself. How? By hammering yourself all the time, and reciting the Naam Mantra non-stop. You should not be attracted to visit another Master, for some other kind of knowledge, a different kind of knowledge. This will only create confusion, and, as a result, it will damage your faith. Don’t be tempted! This is a red alert. Don’t be attached to anyone’s thoughts, as it will create problems for you, and undo all your efforts. What are you going for? You already know Reality. You know that you are Ultimate Truth, so, what more do you want?

It is the restlessness in the body-form, that is prompting you to wander again. If you meet another Master, he will command you to “do this, and do that”, and soon, you will accept the grand illusion once more, that you are a doer. This Master will talk to you about your past life, and your future life. There is no life at all! He will reintroduce you to the concepts of sin and guilt, karma etc, and before you know it, you will be caught up in the vicious circle of illusion, forsaken, and, once more stuck in the illusory ditch!

Here, we are guiding you to remove all your illusory concepts. Elsewhere, you will be asked to do various things, like carry out acts of self-denial, or even, to hand over all your material possessions to the Master, in order to prove your faith in him!

After listening to this knowledge, you are to make yourself spiritually very strong. Try not to hurt anyone’s feelings. Comparing yourself to others, will only create struggle. Don’t hurt anyone’s heart. Remove the ego that feels, “Oh, I have so much knowledge. I am a spiritual Master”. It is not like that.

Don’t count yourself as an individual. Everybody is a Master. Accept the Reality of your Formless Self. If you don’t, there will be confusion again, and illusion. Be strong! This human body is such an opportunity for you to know yourself. Don’t waste any more time. Attend to your work and your duties, and take care of your health. If you take this knowledge lightly, and casually, then you will become a victim of your own desires. Make this your Last Terminal. No birth! No death! There is absolutely nothing. So, be strong, be spiritually strong. Okay? It is simple! Accept the Reality of your Formless Self.

64. Why is Conviction necessary?

We are under the pressure of various anxieties, fears and tension. Happiness and peace always seem to be out of our range, because we are identifying ourselves as the body-form. When you identify yourself in a true sense, all your tensions and fears will simply evaporate. There will be peace and happiness in abundance. Find out who it is that wants happiness? Who is it that wants peace? Who wants a tension-free life? Who wants a fearless life? The Spirit does not want it.

We are always worried about our bodies, because our consciousness is mixed in with the body, and this is what makes our existence in the body-form intolerable. We know that this body is a temporary state, but, even so, we are still very much attached to it. We fret about the slightest ailment, to the point of neurosis. And, no matter who we are, or how spiritual we are, deep down, we all wish for a long life. By all means, look after the body, but, at the same time, you must identify yourself. Identify “Who am I? If I am not the body, then who am I?” Identify your real nature, your true essence.

The Questioner That asks “Who am I?” is Itself Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. You can visit as many holy sites and temples as you wish, but if you do not visit the Visitor, then all your pilgrimages, will have been in vain.

During your search, you may have discovered various deities, but you are still searching for more. You are still searching for something, that you feel is missing deep down. You are looking for something to fill that hole, that gap that makes you feel incomplete! How long are you going to keep searching for? And how many more gods are you still hoping to discover? Stop the search, and realize that you, the Searcher Itself are God. You have simply forgotten! In order to regain your original memory that you yourself are God, that you are that Masterly essence, that you are, in fact, the missing link, you must undergo strict meditation. Look at you! You are God! You are Almighty! There is nothing out there. Everything is within you.

Don’t waste your time. If you don’t identify yourself during this human life, there will be another dream, and you will continue to remain in some type of body-form. Be very serious about this knowledge. Think about it very seriously and carefully.

Read books like I Am That as well as Siddharameshwar’s Master of Self-Realization. And, also read Selfless Self, thoroughly. Pay attention to what these books are trying to convey. Identify their message behind the words. You are not here to analyze the words, but to accept the truth that is placed before you. These Masters give one message only, and that is: “Except for your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman”. This knowledge is priceless, and free. There is no charge because it is your innate knowledge.

The Master tells you: “You are a Master. You are God!” But, you don’t believe the Master. You doubt what he is saying, and question this preposterous notion, saying, “how can I be God”? Yet, you never question: “How can I be a man?” All the body-based-knowledge impressions over a lifetime, are preventing you from accepting the Reality that the Master is placing before you. We know Reality, but not Practical Reality. We only have the theory. The Master tells you that you are Brahman, God, beyond God, but you are not accepting the Truth. Instead, you want to go exploring again, and see new vistas, new experiences, fresh entertainment. Why visit so many places? Visit your own place within. Visit your inner temple, your inner sanctuary.

This is your unique opportunity to find yourself. You were never lost, only forgotten. The Finder is Ultimate Truth. Identify yourself! Any questions? Be free! If you have any questions regarding spirituality, just ask. And read all these books very carefully, very thoroughly. When you read them, again and again, each time, you will receive a different message because it is the Reader’s information that is unfolding.

What is arising, is information that is coming directly from the Invisible Reader within you. Nisargadatta Maharaj, Ranjit Maharaj, Siddharameshwar Maharaj – they were all such saintly people. Read their teachings. The knowledge is priceless. And there is no need to spend one single penny for it either. Money contaminates the knowledge. Our lineage has firm rules, that categorically forbids, charging any money for spreading the teachings. All these saintly people taught for free. Sadly now, in our day, whatever is offered for free is considered valueless. If a teacher said, “give me one lakh of rupees”, he will be esteemed a great saint!

Welcome this glorious opportunity to find yourself. The Finder itself is Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. Therefore, “Be With You All the Time”. Work, and take care of your loved ones, but also, identify yourself. This is your time, the right time. You don’t want to endure another dream which has been called “rebirth”, [“rebirth” is merely a concept] There is no rebirth, no past, or future birth. There is no past karma, future karma, or any kind of karma. How can there be karma, when there is no doer and no deed?

Countless concepts were impressed upon us throughout our lifetime. You have become used to living with them. Now, you are being asked to throw them all out. Why? Because all your concepts are borrowed. Why become a victim of someone else’s concepts? For example, you accept your birth as fact, and yet, no-one has any memory, of his or her birth. So, forget about birth, past birth, future birth! This knowledge has all come out of the realms of the imagination.

Do you have any memories prior to your childhood? No! None at all! Therefore, stop accepting everything that you hear! Apply some intellect, and use it to discriminate. Don’t become a victim of your mind. You are beyond that! Prepare now! Identify yourself now, before your life-span in the body-form terminates.

Just listen! Spontaneous Conviction is not only necessary, but essential, if you are to dis-identify with the body-form identity. The emergence of Ultimate Reality, will only happen when all the body-based knowledge, with which you have constructed your identity dissolves. Be courageous, and accept the Reality. Why do you need courage? Because you are letting go of everything that you know, and everything that you are attached to. And, even though it is all illusion, it provides you with an illusory sense of safety and security.

Don’t underestimate yourself. That Masterly Essence is in you. It is not separate from you. You were not the body. You are not the body. You are not going to remain the body. This is the message behind spirituality.

65. How do I identify myself?

You know that the body is not your identity at all. Think about this for a moment! Who is speaking from this body? Who is asking questions? Is the body asking questions? Is the mind asking questions? There is some essence within the body, an Invisible Presence that is the Source of all Power. Who is watching your dreams, projecting your dreams, and that whole dream world? Have you given this any consideration? Who or what is projecting this dream-world? Self-enquire! Who is the projector of this world? Identify yourself. It is the Invisible Listener, the Invisible Experiencer – That you are!

You are formless. This five elemental body is like our clothes, that will only last for a certain length of time. The sooner you wake up to this fact, the sooner you will be at peace, as you will no longer have to worry about “dying”. There is no death for you. The body will expire one day, but you will never expire because you are immortal.

You were once a small child, who grew up into a young man. And now, you have become an old man. Soon, this bag of bones will crumble, and the time will come for you to leave the body. Why not prepare for a peaceful death, so that you can leave the body willingly, without any fear. Because when you know what is actually taking place, that you are simply discarding a layer, and not dying, this transition can be a beautiful event.

Identify yourself in a real sense, by knowing that you are not the body, and the rest of your life will be filled with happiness and peace. It is up to you. Accept the facts, the Reality, your Reality, or, perpetuate the illusion, suffering and misery!

66. What is the best way to go beyond, or prior to, all this?

It is not a question of going beyond, or prior. You are not going anywhere. Reality has no “coming”, and no “going”. Does the sky in India want to go to Germany? Or, does the sky in Germany want to go to America? The sky is everywhere. Likewise, your Invisible Presence is everywhere. You are everywhere. There may be many, many different body-forms, but these body-forms are impermanent. Your Presence, however, is permanent. When the body expires, it dissolves into that Presence, and the vastness of that Presence.

Just now, we can see a variety of bodies around us. They come in all sorts of shapes and sizes. There are so many different body-forms, but after a hundred years, how are these body-forms going to appear? They are not! They will not be around, guaranteed.

It is your Presence that keeps the body alive. When the body expires, Presence becomes omnipresence, dissolving in its vastness. Just like if you pour a bucket of water into the sea, it will merge and become the sea. There is no duality. You experience illusion because you are considering yourself to be the body-form. Within that illusion, within that duality, lies Reality, an exceptional Presence that cannot be defined. There is neither an experiencer, nor any experience.

Presence does not know that, “I am Presence”. This stage, or Ultimate Status is to be absorbed. The only way this Stateless State can unfold, is with, and through, meditation. It is the only way. It is the base, the foundation. Without meditation, you cannot know yourself directly. At best, you can only know yourself through words.

67. How do we absorb this Truth, totally and completely?

This will happen spontaneously and automatically. Faithfully follow the meditation, for a period of time, without thinking about the consequences. The process is not about your transformation into Reality because you are already Reality. But, because the ego is in the way, and the mind keeps interfering, all this stops you from absorbing the teachings, and knowing your Ultimate Truth.

We have had so many discussions together, and throughout all of these, everything has been recorded within you. Just contemplate, over and over, all that the Master has conveyed to you. Remember what was said, and you will see the dramatic changes occurring. Through the process of meditation, illusion will dissolve, and Reality will come to the fore.

You will regain your “original memory”. This memory has nothing to do with the body. Your Presence is Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. Reading books, and entertaining yourself with spiritual words, is futile. Ask yourself, what purpose they will serve, after you leave the body?

What we see is the Seer’s reflection. Don’t take these words literally, but here, the Seer is most important. The Seer is the Invisible Seer, the Invisible Listener within you. It is that which you consider to be the body-form, the human-form. The human form is not the Reality you take yourself to be. But, in order to have this Conviction – that you are formless, and that your Presence is everywhere like the sky – spirituality is most important, as you must be convinced that you are not the body-form.

Meditation is central to bringing about this Spontaneous Conviction. It is the groundwork, the foundation, the hammering that is necessary in the beginning. Meditation has a temporary function, that of shattering illusion. Prior to beingness, we did not meditate. And, after leaving the body, there will not be any meditation going on. Meditation means hammering yourself with the knowledge of your true nature. It means reminding yourself of who you are, again and again, like brainwashing. Its repetitive nature clears out all the debris of your illusory life, and establishes Ultimate Reality. After listening to the Master, and continuously hammering yourself, Reality will be absorbed, and the Truth opened up, and flowing within you.

68. So, we need to put in effort, but not struggle?

Why struggle? We are always struggling with our thoughts. It is the nature of the body to manufacture thoughts 24/7. The thoughts are always flowing. You give them too much attention, and by doing this, you let them control you. This will change with meditation. Why be a victim of your thoughts? Just let them flow by you. When you ignore the thoughts, your confusion will lessen because you are no longer entangled in them. Keep ignoring the thoughts. This will lead to thoughtlessness.

In our lineage, we practise systematic devotion: singing bhajans, saying prayers to keep you alert, as well as meditation, and listening to knowledge. All these activities are designed, to prevent you from falling victim, to somebody else’s thoughts and concepts, or your own concepts. If you are dedicated, no one will be able to play tricks on you again.

You must be dedicated at all times, so that you remain alert. You don’t have to go to an ashram, or visit a temple. You can be anywhere, reciting the mantra, and sitting for meditation. “Wherever You Are There is Your Ashram.” Remember that the uplifting atmosphere that is created through singing the bhajans, serves to keep the mind in check. The mind cannot get up to any mischief, while you are singing.

The mind is always, always, trying to distract you. Everyone says, “Yes, I know Brahman. I know Brahman. I know Brahman.” It is like the story of the blind men and the elephant. Whatever part of the elephant they touched, they concluded it was such and such. But when the whole elephant is seen, there is no discussion, or argument. When you know the Reality, why struggle? What are you struggling with? There is nothing.

If you have any free time, then come and be with the Master. But stand on your own two feet, both spiritually, as well as, physically. The Master is always there. The Master is always with you. Even if the Master is not with you physically, he is still there. So why go looking for other living Masters? Many disciples say, “Oh, I have to find a living Master”. What do you mean by a “living Master”? You are a Living Master!”

69. How can I Realize?

Who says that you are not already realized? How can you not be realized? The Spirit within the body is already realized.

Spiritual knowledge will help you to identify yourself. And then you will, “Bow Down to That Through Which You Know Your Self. “Bow to Your Selfless Self.” “Bow Down Only to Selfless Self.” Bow down with your heart, and not just mechanically. Accept the Reality! Don’t just take what I am trying to say literally!

Convince yourself that “You Are The Architect of Your Own Life”, your spiritual life. “Everything Starts From You And Everything Ends Within You.” So, be humble, be simple, be normal. “And, Tomorrow You Will Be a Master.” There are no restrictions. My Master says, “If You Are Realized, Make Others Realized”. “I Am Not Making You Disciples, I Am Making You Masters.” It is not difficult because you are already a Master. Live Like A Master! The Master Is Your Ultimate Truth. You Are Ultimate Truth. Why are you spoiling yourself, wasting yourself, ruining yourself?

70. Is it possible to identify what I am positively? It seems we can only know what we are not…?

There is no positive, and no negative. Even to try and find out, “Who am I?” is an illusion. In order to know “I am”, you have to take ego: “I am something”. There is nothing. There is no “I”, there is no “you”, no “he”, “she”, “it”. These are the concepts, the words we need to use for communication, just for understanding purpose. Therefore, I am always insisting that you don’t play with the literal, and spiritual words. That “I” is to dissolve totally. Okay, we can use these pronouns for daily conversations, while knowing that they are concepts. You say that Brahman symbolizes God. Which God? Do you know anything about God? Have you seen God? Have you seen Brahman? How can you see Brahman or God? You cannot – because You Are That. You cannot see yourself without using a mirror. Because of your book-reading, you have become victims of literal knowledge. Knowledge is not separate from you. Brahman is not separate from you. “You Are The Final Destination.” “Where Everything Ends, There You Are.” Prior to beingness you knew nothing at all. Absolutely nothing was known to you. Find out what you are not!

71. What do you mean by total involvement?

Total involvement means that you are always with Selfless Self. You are always reciting the Mantra. You are earnest, and on fire. You must know the answer to, “Who am I?” You have to know. This question should become so vital to you, that pursuing it, becomes almost a matter of life or death. It is so important to you, that you are always thinking about Reality, contemplating your true nature, and reciting the Mantra.

Your Unidentified Identity is nameless, therefore, using basic language, and simple meanings, we are trying to impose Reality upon the Invisible Listener.

Be convinced that without Presence, your body is nothing but a dead body. Can a dead body see anything? Can it hear anything? If there is no power, no energy, no spiritual strength, then there can be no activity, or functioning whatsoever. Who sees? Who listens? Who tastes the food? It is that supernatural power in you, that supreme Essence, that Invisible Presence called Brahman.

This human body has a very important purpose. It is the vehicle for Self-Realization. Through this body, you can identify yourself, know yourself, and realize that you are not the body. You were not the body. And, you are not going to remain the body.

Listen to these discourses, and after a few days, I will teach you how to meditate. If you are serious, I will give you the Mantra. But, until then, listen with complete attention and involvement. And read Selfless Self thoroughly. Then you can make up your mind, about whether you wish to take the Mantra or not. If you feel it is right for you, I will guide you. It is up to you. Taking the Mantra is not obligatory. And I always tell seekers, not to take the Mantra if they have any doubts. Take it only if you have full confidence and faith.

When you listen to these discourses, some impressions will be engraved within you. We are hammering Reality into you. In brief: “You are not the body at all. You were not the body. You are not going to remain the body”. The concepts of death and birth are only connected to the body, not to you. Your Presence is wholly separate from the body. The body is a food-body. You are not that. The body is made up of the five elements. You are beyond that.

Listen carefully! Absorb the knowledge! You are not the body at all. You are invisible. You are like the space or the wind, acting invisibly within the body. Just like the wind does not know that it is the wind, the Spirit does not know that it is Spirit.

I am happy to see that at this young age, you have embraced spirituality, and are taking it seriously. Seriousness, and deep self-involvement in spirituality are essential. It is also easier to adapt when one is still young, and not set in one’s ways, views or beliefs. With the onset of old age, it is not so easy to reject a lifetime of ingrained concepts. It is almost impossible, in fact.

Don’t use spirituality as an escape from life’s responsibilities. You need not quit your job. If you are studying, complete your education, don’t abandon it, saying:

“Oh, I am going to give everything up, renounce the world and live a pure, spiritual life. I will travel to the Himalayas and live in a cave”. This kind of talk is nonsense talk! If you do this, nothing is going to happen, except that you will move your body from A to B.

Thousands of people leave home on a spiritual whim, discarding everything, and going for spirituality full-pelt! This kind of decision and action is entirely irrational! You cannot run from the battlefield. Renouncing the world is pure escapism. It is running from the battlefield. Face the battlefield! “Yes! I can remain a part of society and, at the same time, still live a spiritual life!” The two are not mutually exclusive. “I can find out who I am, while still going about my work and business, and attending to my family”.

The same Spirit that is in all the saints, resides in you. But, alas, you do not know yourself. You are unaware of your true nature, your divine essence. It is a tragedy to go through life, year after year, never knowing who you are. It is a tragedy to go through life asleep, unaware that this is nothing but a long dream. So many tears! So much suffering! It is all illusion, and such a waste of the opportunity you have now, to free yourself from all illusory bondage.

Here we are sharing practical knowledge. How will this knowledge bring about change? You will carry on as before, except with one difference, that you will no longer take it all for real. When there is Spontaneous Conviction, you will know that you are playing a role because nothing is true. “The World is Projected Out of Your Spontaneous Presence.” You will stay with the Seer, and not get drawn into the seen.

When Reality is established, the implications are far-reaching, and intensely liberating: All your fears will be gone, because you will know that there is no death, no birth, no past or future births, no heaven or hell. These fears that accompanied you through life, will simply collapse like a pack of cards. You will no longer have any cause for anxiety or worry. When you recognize all the concepts, that have had a stranglehold over you, they will simply dissolve.

When you know who you are, you will tap into the Source of your Power. You are Almighty, Ultimate Reality. You are the Source of this world. You are the central point of the universe. When all your concepts have been erased, you will be free from all bondage. You have always been free, but you were not aware of this, because of mistakenly accepting your identity as the body-form.

Dissolve each and every concept! Be ruthless! Get rid of all your concepts. This is the principle of spirituality. Remember that Ultimate Reality will not emerge until all illusion has dissolved. You are formless. You are unborn, vast, expansive. Live like That! Don’t be casual about your spiritual practice. It is only with deep and full self-involvement, that you will progress, and inch closer and closer to Selfless Self.

Start reading Selfless Self and I Am That, and then you will understand the principle of spirituality, and the importance of meditation, and the Naam Mantra. Then knowledge will begin to flow. This is your innate knowledge. Everything will be revealed to you spontaneously. Your Inner Master will start communicating with you. All your questions will be answered because you have arrived at the Source. There will be happiness and peace, and unimaginable silence. These qualities are the fragrance of Selfless Self. Keep this Truth, near to your heart at all times: “Except for your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman”. You are Atman. You are Brahman. You are Paramatman. All the spiritual power is in you. All the supernatural power is in you. “Everything Starts From You, and Everything Ends Within You.”

If any miracles occur, don’t be impressed by them, and don’t be fooled into thinking that someone made them happen. There is no one who is greater than you. You must have this Conviction of your greatness within you. All miracles start from you, so do not be impressed by anyone performing miracles. No one is greater than you. And, at the same time, show respect to the Master who has shown you your greatness.

72. What does Selfless Self mean?

You are not the body. You are not the mind. You are not the Self. Self refers to identification with the body. You are Selfless Self. This means that there is nothing there. That which you are is beyond words. Selfless Self is beyond any words, and you are beyond Selfless Self. Everything that came along with the body is illusion, and body-based knowledge. When these illusory layers on your Presence have been removed, we call that which is left, “Selfless Self”.

Selfless Self is one’s Spontaneous, Invisible, Anonymous Presence which is beyond any identification whatsoever. This means that your identity is invisible, anonymous, unidentified identity. You are unborn, formless. It is a fact that a hundred years ago, you did not know anything about yourself. You did not know who you were. In a hundred years’ time, again, you will not know anything about anything. When the Spirit clicked with the body, and you became aware of your existence, you started to consider yourself as the body-form. This body-form existence, with its never-ending cycle of needs, made life intolerable. When you accepted the body-form as your identity, you experienced unhappiness, dispeace, tension and fear. But, as you know, the body-form is not your identity. You are formless, unidentified identity. There is nothing except Selfless Self. Except for Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master.

73. You often mention “glimpses of I”?

It is just that feeling of “I”, just “I”. That feeling has no specific identity or form. In the early morning, when you first awaken from deep sleep, at that particular moment, even though you are holding the body, there is just a feeling of “I” there. It has been called glimpses of “I”. In this fleeting instant, there is no identity of maleness, femaleness. There is nothing, just “I”. This glimpse is an exceptionally, peaceful feeling. There is no feeling or sense of the world – nothing at all. That exceptional state was there while you were in deep sleep, and that feeling of blissful peace lingers, just for a brief moment, on awakening.

You can compare it to samadhi. In the samadhi state, there is no awareness. There is nothing but glimpses of “I”. Don’t take the words literally. We have no choice but to use language for understanding purposes. At that particular stage, there is no gender, no form, absolutely nothing. After this glimpse has been felt momentarily, then the body-form kicks in, and declares: “I am”, followed by a stream of illusory memories.

But prior to that, there is only that pure, untainted feeling of, just “I”. This peace is momentary. It is there before the world is projected, and before the illusory feelings arise. At the Ultimate Stage, there Is no Experiencer and no Experience. It is because we are holding the body, that we are feeling “I”, “you”, “he”, “she”, “it”. You know so many things, but as a matter of fact, your Presence or Unidentified Identity is unknown. Knowledge came afterwards. If there were no body, how can you identify knowledge?

Even if you try to imagine the state prior to beingness, using the intellect, you cannot. You were totally formless. It was only when Presence touched with the body, that you started saying, “I”. And that “I” took the form of either a man, or a woman, or of any animal, or being. That beingness is coloured with some form. It is not permanent. As long as you have a body, you will feel the beingness.

74. You never talk about death?

There is no death. You are unborn. Death for whom? You are formless. Nobody has ever experienced death. We say, “he, or she, died, and has now taken birth”. But that deceased person does not know whether he died, or whether he has taken birth. This is all imagination and hearsay. Prior to body-based knowledge, nothing was known. Identify that nothingness. Don’t take the words literally. Throw all these concepts, along with their associated anxieties, in the garbage can.

“Everything Came Out of Nothing, and Everything Dissolves Within Nothing.” Identify That Nothing. Using different words, “I Am Trying to Invite the Attention of the Invisible Listener Within You, That Except Your Selfless Self There is Nothing. Though the Bodies are Different, the Spirit, the Invisible Listener, is One and the Same.”

Spirit has no form. It is totally formless. But, we are always measuring ourselves in the body-form, and we accept the knowledge through the body-form. “The Body-Form is Not Your Identity at All.” Sit for meditation, and then that Conviction will arise spontaneously.

You are immortal, indestructible. If you were never born, how can you possibly die? You are formless, omnipresent. In the Bhagavad Gita it says, “Your Presence is everywhere. It is formless”. Your Presence is just like the electricity that powers the lights or fans, and other items. Your Presence is invisible, like electricity. It is an invisible power, an invisible energy. The speaker in this body, and the listener in that body, are one and the same. This Energy is the power that enables us to act. Without that Energy that is Presence, I cannot speak, and you, cannot listen. It is as simple as that.

That Energy is One Energy. That energy is the Source. That energy is eternal. All the body-forms will expire at some point, but not that Invisible Energy. Conviction is needed because of the illusory concepts, that have been impressed upon us, such as: “You are going to die”, and, “this birth will be followed by another birth”. Or, “In a past birth, you did something wrong”. Then there are the concepts of heaven and hell. The only way to erase them all, once and for all, is with meditation.

It is both very easy, and very difficult, at the same time, because “You Must Have Strong Faith Within You, and Strong Faith in Your Master”. When your Master tells you that you are Brahman, you are Brahman. Accept it! There are to be no, “Yes, buts!” And then, stay with your Master. Be loyal to Him! Be loyal to yourself. Don’t grow restless, and with itchy feet, impulsively go looking for change, or novelties.

It is a habit of the mind, to go looking for distractions and new entertainment. You are wasting your time, and allowing whims to distract you from Reality. I keep telling you that Reality is within you. Stay where you are. You keep wanting to go on your travels again. What is to be done? “Reality is Not Separate From You. Reality is Within You, and Nowhere Else.” But, in spite of knowing this, you are tempted to go, and see other Masters: “Oh, I have heard about this Master. I will go and check him out. And then, I might visit that other Master nearby, while I am at it”.

There is no such thing as a disciple, and there is no such thing as a Master. No one has ever visited a Master because there is only One Masterly Essence that is Formless. That Masterly Essence is in you. You are the Master. “The Master is Not Separate From You.” But the mind creates confusion, and is always trying to catch you unaware, ready to dump you back into the illusory ditch. Therefore, be alert, be cautious, and try to identify yourself because “There is Nothing, Except Your Selfless Self”. Be serious! Take on this challenge. Grab this valuable moment to know yourself in a real sense. If you neglect it, if you take it lightly, one cannot say what kind of illusory, body-form might be projected again. Once you accept Reality, there will never ever be a re-appearance of form.

“Stay as You Were Prior to Beingness!” You did not know yourself. You did not know anything. Stay with “I Don’t Know”. Forget all the knowledge and the concepts: “Oh, my last birth must have been a nightmare! What will my future birth be like? This birth, that birth, blah, blah, blah”. If you don’t get rid of all the concepts that you hold just now, they will continue to create more concepts, and then, multiple concepts will keep appearing and re-appearing.

Get rid of all the guilty feelings too. You have not done anything wrong. You cannot do anything because you are not a doer. This is a long dream in which nothing has happened. Nothing will happen, and nothing is happening. We are talking about the unborn child.

75. What kind of changes will take place?

Since your childhood days, you have accepted the body-form as your identity. After strict meditation, and reciting the Mantra, you will notice some changes beginning to take place. There will be less internal clutter, because some of the illusory concepts, the rubbish, or garbage, has been removed. Generally, you will feel more peaceful. You will not be affected by outer circumstances, as you once were.

Overall, you will feel more content and happy, extremely happy. There will be a kind of inner joy. This joy or bliss is not a response to something, it is just a natural, flowing state, your natural state. Slowly, and silently, there will be peacefulness.

I have received messages from many foreign devotees, who tell me, that after reading Selfless Self, and meditating, they are experiencing exceptional pleasure. Even when they are facing unpleasant circumstances, this feeling of exceptional happiness and peacefulness remains.

When you have the Conviction that you are not the body, you will no longer be so concerned about what is happening around you. This can happen to you, too! While holding the food-body, at the same time, there should be the Conviction that “I am not the body at all. I was not the body. I am totally formless”. There is no death or birth. Pleasure and pain are connected to the body, and not to You. They are body-related, and have nothing to do with your Reality. Where was pleasure and pain, prior to beingness? There was nothing there.

You are already free. You have always been free, but you feel that you are in bondage. When, through meditation, these changes take place, you will live as free as a bird, permanently happy and peaceful.

76. How do I concentrate on the Concentrator that is formless?

Just follow what I have told you: except for your Selfless Self, there is no Brahman. So, at the initial stage, you have to act deliberately. Concentrate on that Invisible Concentrator within you, which has no form. The Invisible Concentrator within you is witnessing everything. You feel “I” in the body. Without Presence, you can’t feel “I”. In the beginning, you are to make an effort to find this “I”. Then, after finding out, that Finder will disappear. There is no finder!

With constant hammering, the Spirit within you will selflessly self-enlighten. That Realization will be Spontaneous Realization, Conviction, “I Am That”, without ego, without words. You are thinking, “I have to concentrate”. That invisible “I” indicates “I Am Ultimate Truth”. These are only words! Through this vehicle of words, we are trying to invite the attention of the Invisible Concentrator. Words are not Ultimate Truth. It is only language and meaning. Through various words, we are trying to invite the attention of the Invisible Listener within the body, that except your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman.

After concentrating on the Concentrator, the Concentrator will disappear. Both the concentrator and the concentration will disappear. There will be nothing left because everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing. There is no deed, there is no doer. Unless you stop measuring yourself in the body-form, you will not be able to identify yourself in a real sense. It is an open fact: the body is an external cover.

77. “Be strong! Have courage!” What does that mean?

Strength and courage are needed to surrender all your concepts, beliefs, experiences, and your whole pseudo-identity as the body-form. “Try to Identify The Invisible Identifier Within You.” You must have the courage to accept the Reality, “That Except Yourself, There is Nothing”.

You have accepted so many concepts. Suppose that when you were a child, you used to collect, and save various currency notes. Then, some time later, after diligently collecting all this money, you found out that they were fake notes. When you discover this, you will need to find the courage to throw them all out! Similarly, after Realization, you will know, that whatever knowledge you have collected from various sources, is fake knowledge. All your knowledge of the gods and goddesses, your knowledge of spirituality, etc, etc, is, in fact, all fake knowledge because Ultimate Truth is not separate from you.

“No Knowledge Is Knowledge.” The concept of knowledge appeared upon your Presence. It is a layer. What is knowledge? Knowledge means just to identify oneself in a real sense. You identified yourself as the body-form. That is not knowledge, but ignorance, illusion.

78. Even though I am convinced intellectually, I still have material needs

This body-based knowledge still has a strong hold over you. Again, you are functioning within the illusory circle. I have repeatedly told you, that you are not the body at all. Where were those thoughts prior to beingness? And will you still have material needs after you leave the body? There are no thoughts after leaving the body. It is a thoughtless state. Thoughts come, and thoughts go. Don’t be a victim of your mind!

What is the truth? After you leave the body, will there be any thoughts there? Any actions? Not at all! Was there anything there prior to beingness? Did you know anything, whether you were a man or a woman? Were there any gods or goddesses there? Meditation is the way to disidentify with the body-form, and pierce through all your illusory concepts. Dry, spiritual knowledge will not help you to dissolve the body-based knowledge. Your original state is stateless, thoughtless, and action-less.

79. Can we know anything?

Be normal! Don’t think so much! Don’t struggle with your thoughts. Know, that there is nothing to know. You are trying to find something, so that you can grasp a hold of it. There is nothing to grasp hold of! You are forgetting that knowledge is only needed, to inform you that there is nothing to know. You cannot know what you are because you are Unidentified Identity. You are Ultimate Truth. “The Finder is Itself Ultimate Truth.” You are ignoring yourself, neglecting yourself, and searching for Brahman, somewhere outside of yourself.

Your Inner Voice is most important, your Inner Master is most important. So, listen very carefully! “The Master is Not Separate From You.” “Be With You, and Listen From the All.” Don’t play with all these spiritual words. You are not to be found in words. Be deeply involved in your Selfless Self, your Inner Master. Don’t underestimate, or ignore, your Inner Master!

80. If I am not the body, what am I?

The answer is: “You Are Everything”. You are not limited to the body. You are unlimited. “Your Presence is Everywhere, Just Like the Space or the Sky, for Which There is No Death and Birth.”

Because we have forgotten our identity, we need to regain that original memory of our Reality, our true Identity. So, we need hammering, non-stop hammering. The Master convinces you, saying, “You are Brahman. You are Brahman.” Then you must convince yourself, “I am Brahman. I am Brahman”. After sufficient “brainwashing”, the Spirit/Presence will accept the Reality: “Yes! I Am That!” And then Knowledge will flow from within you.

You will feel an inner transformation. All your questions will evaporate as, one by one, what appeared to be some very tough, even insurmountable questions, will be resolved automatically, with ease. Your Inner Master will answer all your questions. And, not even that, you will be blessed with the gift of foresight, and miraculous experiences as well. But even these are not Ultimate Truth. These are progressive stages. Miracles are not Ultimate Truth. Forget about them! How do these miracles happen? Where do they come from? The Master does not perform any miracles. Your Presence alone is the Source, the cause of all these miraculous experiences.

When you know who you are, as unlimited, formless, and eternal, there will not be any more fear. There is no one there to fear, and, there is nothing to fear. Fear is a concept that arose out of your mistaken identity, when you took yourself to be the body-form. Now, you can live a life free of pain and suffering, a fearless life, that is filled with peace and happiness, because you are not dependent on the body, or the world for your happiness. Basically, there is no doer, and there is no deed. “The Entire World is Projected Out of Your Invisible Anonymous Presence.”

81. What value does this body have?

Your body is a dead body. What value can a dead body have? By itself, it has no value. It is your Presence that gives it value. If Presence were to leave the body, just for one split second, the body’s value would drop to minus zero.

Shankaracharya says: “This body is the dirtiest of bodies, but within this dirtiest of bodies, lies the Purest Presence. Therefore, this body has great value, untold value, unspeakable value, because without it, you cannot, you will not be able to know yourself. The body is the medium, through which you can know your Identity. “The Body is Not Your Identity. The Holder of the Body is Your Identity.”

The Holder of the body has no shape. The body-holder or Sustainer is formless. Meditation is essential, to establish a strong foundation, so that you can identify yourself. You may find spiritual discussions stimulating and entertaining, but they will not help you to identify yourself, and bring about Conviction. Meditation is illusion, but, through it, you will be able to know yourself directly. Spiritual discussion alone, will not cut it. It will only enable you to know yourself via second-hand knowledge, through words, and therefore, indirectly.

82. What is our lifestyle based on?

Our lifestyle is based on all the concepts that were engraved, and continue to be engraved in us. We have been told so many different stories, which we have accepted at face value. We were told many things about the existence of God, Brahman, Atman, and the Masters. But you do not know your Reality because of the influences of the body-form. You are unaware of your true identity because you are holding the body. Spirit lies within the body. Along with the Spirit, consciousness appeared. Your Presence is beyond consciousness. Consciousness has taken on a colour that says, “I am a man”, or, “I am a woman”, or “I am something else”. Prior to consciousness, you did not know yourself.

As I have told you so many times, there are numerous concepts around, regarding death and birth, past birth, future birth, salvation, God, Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, Master, disciple devotee, liberation, etc, that we have accepted them blindly. They are, in fact, nothing but allegations, without any substance. They are all illusion! However, these mere concepts have bombarded us for so long, that they continue to carry immense power, to influence and confuse us.

83. I know I’m not the body, but I still want a long, and happy life?

Who wants a long life? The body is a dead body. Who is acting from that body? Who is listening from the body? Who is enjoying this worldly knowledge? That Invisible Presence called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master – That You Are. You are formless, without fate, rebirth, past birth, or future birth.

You are Almighty God. God means Ultimate Truth. God does not take birth. To know yourself in a real sense requires strong confidence, and strong faith in yourself and your Master. If you have a wavering mind, you will be here today, and gone tomorrow. You will quickly forget about your Master, and exchange him for someone else the next day. Changing Masters is like changing wives, Mmh! How can you find anything, if you go hopping from one Guru to another? There should not be this kind of polygamous mentality. You are to remain faithful to yourself, and to one Master. Don’t sell yourself! Don’t be a prostitute! You may feel that this is a slanderous word, but abusing your Spirit in this way is like that. Show yourself some loyalty. Be loyal to yourself, and be loyal to your Master, too.

Time is very short. Each and every moment of your life is very, very important. You are lacking spiritual confidence. Nothing has been hidden from you. All has been revealed to you. It is Open Truth! What more do you want? There is nothing more. Accept it: “Yes! I Am That! Yes! I Am That”.

Basically, there is only one Spirit, within all the billions of human bodies. Forget about human beings and human bodies, you are Spirit. Other beings are not able to identify themselves, but we can, with the help of our intellect. Now forget about that!

Here, the principle of spirituality is to identify yourself in a real sense. And, in spite of many dialogues, the concept that you hold of, “I am somebody”, is still not dissolving. This is a tragedy! The only remedy is meditation, and Mantra recitation. You are not meditating regularly. You will only be able to identify yourself through meditation. Concentrate on how you were prior to beingness? Contemplate! There is no form, no needs. You are totally unaware of “happiness” and “unhappiness”. All these concepts came with the body. Identify yourself, and then, you will not be so concerned about the body, and living a long life.

84. Is it okay to follow my family tradition, of devotion to Rama and Krishna?

Do what you like! Engage yourself in that particular spiritual atmosphere, if you wish. When you are worshipping and singing bhajans, it keeps you in a sattvic atmosphere, where you are always thinking about your Reality, your Master, and spirituality.

When we recite the Mantra, we are doing it to halt the flow of concepts. You will enjoy reciting the Mantra and singing the bhajans.

Rama and Krishna are the names that were given to the Ultimate Truth. Rama and Krishna do not have any independent identity. Who knew of Rama prior to beingness? And after leaving the body, will Rama still be there, or Krishna? You started to identify Rama and Krishna, only after your identification with the body-form. If the Spirit disappeared from the body, you will not be able to identify Rama, Krishna, or any Master or disciple?

Prior to beingness, you did not know anything. You did not know of Rama, Krishna, or any other Master. Nothing was known. So that Reality is to be absorbed. Rama, Krishna, etc, are only names for that Supernatural Power within you.

Be firm! I am specifically asking you to be firm. Do not allow any illusory concepts to enter. There is nothing happening. No one is going to give you a boon. And no one is going to curse you. You are All, and All is you. You are alone. “You Yourself Are Almighty God. Your Invisible Presence Is Almighty God.”

Everything is there within you: Sri Ram, Sri Krishna, everybody. Dattatreya as well! You are Dattatreya! It is a fact, but you refuse to accept it. The Listener within you is Almighty God. What more do you want? You are subtler than the sky or space. You are! You are everybody. You Are That! Accept what I am placing before you, because it is your Truth.

3 THE MEDICINE: MANTRA, MEDITATION, DEVOTION

“Through meditation and spiritual knowledge, you are sweeping everything away. This cleaning process purifies the body. Shankaracharya says that this body is the dirtiest body. But within it lies the Purest Presence. It is this Presence which gives the body its high value. Without Presence, the body is worthless because it is a dead body. This is the principle.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

85. How can I digest the knowledge?

Meditation is needed to digest the knowledge. The Invisible Presence within the body is very sensitive. It is impressionable. Therefore, when a Mantra is given, such as “Aham Brahmasmi”, “I am Brahman” or “Soham”, it has a strong effect on the Spirit. Every lineage initiates disciples, using different words. These words create powerful vibrations, when you are reciting the Mantra, meditating with the Mantra, and concentrating with the Mantra.

Meditation is very important, as without it, you cannot digest the knowledge. Without meditation, the knowledge will remain at an intellectual level. Intellectual knowledge is insufficient. You need practical knowledge, so that it can be applied to your daily life.

In the beginning, you must be disciplined. Sit crossed-legged with your eyes half-closed. Concentrate on the tip of your nose. Why place your focus here? Because your mind is a crazy mind. To keep it busy, we ask you to concentrate on the tip of the nose. While the mind is concentrating on the tip of the nose, you are reciting the Mantra. The mind cannot distract you, when it is kept occupied, so you are able to recite the Mantra without interference.

Concentration keeps the mind busy, so that you are not allowing it to create any questions, or some other crazy activity. When you recite the Mantra, you are directly hammering your Selfless Self with: “I am Brahman. Brahman I am, I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. After a period of non-stop recitation, your Originality will open up: “I Am That!” Exactly when this occurs will vary widely. It depends on your approach, your involvement, and your spiritual maturity. If you are very serious, earnest and sincere about uncovering your Reality, and if you are fully involved in the pursuit of Truth, then, you will find it easy. However, if you are casual and half-hearted, then, you can forget about it! It is not going to happen! The ball is in your court! It is up to you!

Don’t take these words literally, but the Heart must long to know Itself. There must be some anxiety behind your quest, an urgency, a deep, burning feeling within you, that is driving you forward to know who you are. You are anxious to know. You are on an urgent mission. Self-Realization has become your one and only purpose. You will only find the treasure by diving deep within. Have faith in yourself, and faith in your Master.

When you accept what the Master says, Reality will open up within you in an instant. And, finally, you will be Home. You will forget about the body-form. You will forget about everything. And you will experience, exceptional peacefulness and happiness.

The waves of energy, or vibrations coming from the Mantra, create a spiritual atmosphere which helps to absorb the Reality. In the beginning, meditation is to be strict, and very disciplined. Literal knowledge or dry knowledge, will not help you. Be strong! Have the courage to accept the Reality! Hold the Conviction that “I am not the doer, and there is no deed”. It is a fact, that there is no doer and no deed. A form is needed for there to be a doer and deeds. You don’t have any form. You are basically formless. You know that this human form is not going to last, so, it is time to be serious about your practice. After Conviction, you will be detached from all the concepts, that used to cause you so much confusion and problems. You will practice discrimination, and be alert at all times, so that you don’t let illusion back in.

You will become your own teacher, as you learn, to first witness, and then accept, the useful thoughts, while rejecting those thoughts that are unhelpful. All your attachments will dissolve, when you know that they are illusory. Your desires will subside, and then, completely disappear. Previously, when we did not know any better, we were slaves of the mind, ego and intellect. The mind was controlling us, dictating to us: “do this, and then, do that”. But now we know, that the mind is totally dependent upon our energy. Without our Presence, how can the mind work? If there is no Presence, the mind cannot function.

Prior to beingness or consciousness, there was no mind, no ego, and no intellect. There were no body-based issues. The issue of thoughts never arose. The question of existence never arose. You are aware of your existence now because of the body-form. You feel it. But, who is acting? Who is listening? Who is carrying out the activities? It is not you, but the Invisible Presence called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, Ultimate Truth, That You Are. It is Final Truth.

This is your time. Apply the knowledge, recite the Mantra, and abundant happiness will be yours. Abundant peace will be yours. Where will this happiness and peace come from? From you, of course! From your Source! You are the Source of Happiness. You are the Source of Peace. “Your Nature is Happiness, Peace and Bliss.” Though you are living with this body, when the Spontaneous Conviction arises, and the knowledge has been digested with meditation, happiness will begin to flow. You will be overflowing with happiness.

You are in the world, but not of the world. You can live without desires or attachments. When the knowledge has been absorbed, you will no longer be a slave to the mind, ego and intellect. Before, when you lived in the darkness of ignorance, the mind was dictating the terms. Now that the light of knowledge, the Truth has been illuminated, you know that you are the only Source. You are the Source of Power, that enables the functioning of the body-mind.

When the knowledge of your Reality is digested and absorbed, there will be no more thoughts, and no more questions, about your bodily existence and experiences. You are that Invisible Presence. You are Final Truth. Through the medium of the body-form, that Conviction of your Reality, will explode spontaneously within you. You will not be able to contain your happiness, your ecstasy, which will be so explosive, that you may feel that you are going to burst! There will be so much fire within and around you, that you may feel that you are going to combust!

86. How can I control this crazy mind?

You need practical knowledge. Theoretical knowledge can be grasped intellectually, but by itself, it will not serve to establish Ultimate Truth in you. The Naam Mantra will give you that practical knowledge. If you don’t have the Naam Mantra, you can recite “Aham Brahmasmi”, or, “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”.

The human body is a structure that contains the mind, the ego and the intellect. This trio always functions together. The mind is very crazy, always creating problems, moods, depression. Sometimes, there are good thoughts flowing, and sometimes, there are bad thoughts. Bad waves of thoughts create confusion, depression, nervousness, disappointment, negativity. They disturb our spirituality.

Today I will talk about how to control the crazy mind. You know the theory: “I was not the body. I am not the body. I am not going to remain the body. The body is not my identity at all.” Therefore, the implications are that there is no birth, and no death, no past life, and no future life. But, that whole bunch of concepts, which you have accumulated since childhood until today, still have a very strong hold over you. To combat this, we advise regular meditation. This will place all your concepts in the melting pot. They must all be melted, dissolved, or burned away. This can only happen with the practice of meditation.

That crazy mind lifts our mood at one moment, and then brings it crashing down, at the next moment. This see-saw effect disturbs our spirituality. Meditation will make us Masters of the mind, so that the mind will no longer control you. “Don’t Follow the Mind. Let the Mind Follow You.”

What is meditation? Meditation means practical concentration. Your concentration should be very strong, so that if bad thought-waves arise, you can ignore them. To be able to ignore these negative waves of thought, takes self-control. And this is where meditation comes in.

Don’t struggle with the thoughts. Learn how to tactfully avoid them. Suppose that in the distance, you see an undesirable person approaching you. You may either avoid him, or, if that were not possible, you will just exchange pleasantries, “How are you? Good morning” etc. and quickly, be on your way. The aim here is to avoid this unwanted encounter, but in a tactful manner. In a similar way, when undesirable thoughts approach you, you are to skilfully avoid them, because these thoughts will create some unpleasantness and dispeace. Your blissfulness will be affected by the encounter. So, number one is meditation. Meditation will control the crazy mind.

87. What is Meditation?

You are Ultimate Truth. The practice of meditation invites the attention of the Meditator within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. But, you are so wrapped up in concepts, that you do not know who you are. You are not the body-form. Who is holding this body? Meditate, and you will find out! You have to go deep within your Selfless Self. Only then, will you discover that you are not separate from Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God or the Master.

The body has a time limit, an age limit. You are a small boy, who then gradually, becomes a young man, and then, an old man. Some day or other, willingly or unwillingly, you will leave this body. This means that the body is not your identity at all. Who is holding this body? You must go deep, and deep, into your Selfless Self. There, you will find out and realize: “Oh! I Am That”! The Conviction that you are Ultimate Truth, will appear spontaneously with meditation.

The outcome of the process of hammering yourself with sacred words, is that your true identity will be re-established. Here is an example, supposing that for some reason, you temporarily forgot who you were, like in the case of an amnesiac. In this situation, family members will show you familiar objects, photos, etc. They will try and remind you of events and associations, in the hope of triggering your memory, so that you can regain your identity.

In a similar way, the Master is trying to convince your Inner Invisible Presence of your eternal, but forgotten, Identity. What you see is illusion. That through which you see is Reality. That is the principle of spirituality. Dry discussion alone about “Brahman, Atman, Maya, Paramatman”, is meaningless because you are only grasping the words about Ultimate Truth, descriptions of Ultimate Truth, but not Ultimate Truth directly. Words are just that, words. Where were these words prior to beingness? There were no words, no language prior to beingness.

Meditation means concentration. Meditation means reminding ourselves of That forgotten Identity. We have lost our memory. We are mistakenly posing ourselves as men or women, male or female. That is our external cover. But within that, there is that Exceptional Invisible Presence. That Reality That You Are must be established.

The purpose of spirituality is not about adding more theoretical knowledge. It is about subtracting all the illusory knowledge you have gathered. It is about removing the ignorance, or, one could say, replacing the “wrong knowledge” with “right knowledge”. [not that there is any “right” or “wrong” – concepts only!] When this happens, you will realize that what you took yourself to be throughout your life, was not your identity at all. That through which you are able to know yourself, is your Identity.

Even though we know that we are not the body-form, we continue to ignore this fact because of the bundle of concepts, that are still wrapped around us. Melt all the concepts! Visiting different Masters, and reading endless books, is meaningless. Why? Because unless you approach your Selfless Self, you will not be able to identify yourself.

The basic principle is that in this human body, in this human life, we are not identifying ourselves. We are identifying everyone else, “How is he? How is she?” But we are not identifying how we are! The books say it all. They tell you everything about Reality. However, that Reality is not absorbed. It is not digested. To digest this Reality, you are to undergo strict meditation. Meditation is the only way. You may have any Master of your choosing, but you must have strong faith in that Master. You must have confidence and faith within your Selfless Self. This is a very important ingredient, essential, in fact.

“Last birth, future birth, last destiny, present, past”, these are all illusion. There is no last birth, no future birth. All these concepts have been sourced from our imagination.

Of what importance is spirituality? Did you know anything about spirituality, prior to beingness? No! Spirituality has one purpose alone, and that is, to remind you that everything is within you. You are the only Source. You are Ultimate Reality. You are Ultimate Truth.

We want to be Masters of Literature, Masters of Philosophy, but not Masters of ourselves – not Masters of Selfless Self! The Masterly Essence is within you alone. We are always forgetting our Own Master, the Reader Within, the Listener Within, That Divine Essence. Through spirituality, and more specifically, through meditation, you can identify yourself. Your Identity cannot be grasped, through the mind or the intellect. But with disciplined meditation, you will be able to identify yourself. You have not been able to identify yourself, because of the ego that still believes itself to be somebody.

Existence in the body-form is intolerable. Body-based knowledge is unbearable, and because of this, we are always looking for comfort, distractions, or relief from various material sources that will alleviate this discomfort, if only momentarily: food, alcohol, entertainment, power, sex, fame, gambling, etc. All our desires, requirements and needs exist to make our precarious situation a little more bearable.

Who wants happiness? Who wants satisfaction? Who wants peacefulness? It is neither the body nor the Spirit. Self-enquire! Who is acting? Who is listening to this dialogue? Who is reading this? What will I get from all my reading? You don’t know because you are always searching, and never reaching a conclusion. There must be a full stop.

We are always analyzing what is being said, analyzing words, instead of accepting, what the Master is trying to convey. This is a big stumbling block! Don’t try to define the words of the Masters. We created language, and gave words their meanings. Instead, try to identify yourself! In the light of all the spiritual knowledge, find out where you stand. What is your position? Travelling, searching, journeying here and there, is not going to lead you anywhere. “You Are the Destination!” Look within and meditate. Look at You, not at the world.

If I am not the body, then “Who Am I?” This is the question that demands an answer. After searching, and searching some more, the searcher will disappear. The whole experience of this illusory world will disappear. Exceptional peacefulness will be there, without any identity, or experience. This state is stateless. The thoughtless state will be there continuously. There will be no thoughts.

But, in order to reach this Ultimate Stage, knowledge is needed to remove the ignorance and illusion. And, meditation is needed to absorb the knowledge. Just reading, reading, and reading some more is meaningless, and only perpetuates the illusory, body-based knowledge.

You can read thousands of spiritual books, but if you still do not know who you are, if you still think that Ultimate Truth is separate from you, then you have wasted all your time and energy. “The Searcher is Itself The Master.” The Master is not separate from you. I am helping you to regain your memory of your Identity. Meditate on that Masterly Essence within you, and refresh your memory! Meditation will dissolve everything that you are not.

88. What is the principle of meditation?

The principle of meditation is that the Meditator within you, which is called Brahman, has forgotten its Identity. In order to re-establish your true identity, we use Mantra Meditation. There are various, sacred words, such as Shivoham, Aham Brahmasmi, etc, that are used as hammers, to remind you of your Ultimate Truth, the Ultimate Reality that you are. The Spirit is highly sensitive, and will absorb whatever is in its vicinity. Therefore, with constant repetition of “I am Brahman, I am Brahman”, that Reality will eventually be accepted. If you hear something often enough, it will become part of you.

The Spirit within you, or Energy, Atman, Paramatman, or whatever name you wish to call it by, is the Invisible Power, that enlivens, or animates, an otherwise, inanimate or dead body. The Invisible Spirit within the body through which you are acting, through which you are watching, through which you are listening, that Invisible Presence is Ultimate Truth. What happens is that when the body-consciousness appears, it forgets its Identity and assumes an independent pose: “I am somebody, an individual”.

Prior to beingness, how were you? You say, “I don’t know”. After leaving the body, how will you be? “I don’t know”. “I don’t know” means you are formless. The answer is correct. I often give this very, simple example of the children’s game: “Knock, knock, Who is There?” One child is at home. The second child knocks on the door, asking, “Is there anybody there?” The first child replies: “No! There’s nobody there”. The child who says, “there’s nobody there”, is there! In a similar way, when we say, “I don’t know”, this means that “I am not in any form. I am formless, but my Presence is there”. Your Presence is everywhere, just like the space or the sky. When the meditation has done its job, there will be Conviction. You will know: “I am Brahman. I am Paramatman. I am God. I am Master”. And you will live like That.

89. Is meditation absolutely necessary? I am averse to it

Meditation is most important because through it we are always hammering, and impressing Reality in you. Mantra meditation is essential, to encourage, and bring about the Spontaneous Conviction, that you are Brahman. With continuous hammering, the Spirit will accept its Reality. It is bound to happen, as long as you put in some effort, in the beginning. Afterwards, it will not be necessary.

Your Presence is Ultimate Truth. That is your Secret Asset, your Confidential Asset, your Invisible Asset, that is within you. But most of us are unaware of That, and so we go wandering here and there, in search of a Master, in whom we hope or believe, can give us what we are looking for.

That Spirit or Presence, that is acting through the body is not limited to the body. It is beyond the body. Knowledge means the identification of your Secret Asset, your Ultimate Truth. In theory, we may know that we are Brahman, but to make this knowledge practical knowledge, meditation is a must.

We need meditation because we are always under the pressure of illusory concepts. You rely on God to help you lighten the load, saying to yourself, “God will help me. God will bless me”, while at the same time you are fearful, that if you do something wrong, He will punish you. These are some of the concepts, that you need to look at, and dissolve.

There is no God out there who is going to help you, or bless you, or punish you. God is not separate from you. You are Ultimate Truth. You are Almighty God! Find this out for yourself! Ask yourself: “Where do I stand? Is this world true or not? What is the fate of this world?” To emerge from all this confusion, the secret of spirituality is revealed to you, along with the Mantra.

It is only your firm and deliberate meditation, that will shift the entrenched, illusory concepts, that have been part of your life since childhood. We have been living in the illusory field of the body-form, feeling trapped and unfree. You are actually free already, but you feel that you are tied up, bound, and wrapped up by a bundle of concepts.

Reality has remained hidden from you, in the dark, because of these concepts. But, when all the illusion is removed, your Originality will emerge, and you will exclaim: “Yes! I Am That!” This will be the happiest moment of your life!

You will see amazing results. You will be aware of all the changes within you, dramatic changes. Previously, you may have been intolerant, even violent. But, after Conviction, there will be exceptional tolerance, exceptional silence, and exceptional peace and happiness. All these qualities are already within you, but you are not aware of them. After removing all the illusory concepts, your Reality, your Originality will open up within you. This feeling will be spontaneous.

Meditation is essential. Without it, we cannot know our Identity. Our present conviction is, “I am the body”, or “I am John”, or some other name that has been given to the body. With meditation, you will uncover your true Identity. You are Ultimate Truth, Ultimate Reality.

90. Why do you insist on continuous meditation?

People often ask, “Why do I have to meditate, when I already know that I am Brahman?”. It is not enough for you to know that you are Brahman, because when you make this statement, the subtle ego has crept in, along with the mind and the intellect. “That Ultimate Truth That You Are, is to Be Established Without the Mind, Ego and Intellect.” It is just like this body is called a “male body”, or a “man”. I am living as a male body, but I am not thinking, “I am male”. This body was named “Ramakant Maharaj”. I don’t have to repeat, “I am Ramakant Maharaj”, over and over again. That name has been accepted, so that, if anyone calls out, “Ramakant Maharaj”, I will respond, and act as Ramakant Maharaj. The form is Ramakant Maharaj. But I am acting spontaneously. I am not thinking, “Oh, I am Ramakant Maharaj, and so, now I have to behave in a certain way”. Deliberate action is not needed because the name, “Ramakant Maharaj”, was accepted a long time ago. Likewise, You Are Ultimate Truth, Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, That is the Established Truth, Final Truth. Deliberate action is not needed, such as, “Oh, I am Brahman, so I have to accept it. I have to prepare, or plan, etc.” No action is needed, no thinking is needed, and no analysis is needed. “Accept It as It Is, Without Thought.”

If you have a question, you will receive an instant answer from within, because you are the Source. Selfless Self is a fast computer. When you need some information, and you Google it, you will receive a response. When you want some information quickly from your very own, inbuilt computer, you will get it instantly. Selfless Self runs faster than Google!

Continuous meditation does not mean sitting still in one place, for hour after hour. Continuous meditation means that we are remembering our true nature all the time. We are staying with Selfless Self, and not being pulled into the world. Meditation is concentration.

Yesterday, there was a lecture in Marathi regarding the Dasbodh. It described how there are many layers of bodies: the food-body, the subtle-body, and this, and that other body. These are the concepts, or layers, upon your Ultimate Truth or Presence. “Through Meditation, You Are Hammering Selfless Self, With the Result That the Reality Will Open Up.” You could say, that we are giving psychological treatment, which will cause you to forget your food-body identity. Then the door to Reality will burst open wide.

“What is Reality? You Are Nothing to do With the Body-Based-Knowledge.” Body-knowledge is illusion, that is related to a temporary body-form. So, until that touch of the body-form dissolves, you need to keep the meditation going.

I am insisting on the Naam Mantra, and on meditation, so that when your time comes to leave the body, there will not be any concepts around like, “I am dying”. Death and birth do not apply to you. Every day, I am shouting out the same thing: “You are not the body. You are not going to remain the body. You are Ultimate Truth. You are Brahman. You are Atman. You are Paramatman. You are a Master”. Is it just going in one ear and out the other?

The entire world is the Seer’s reflection. If there is no Seer, nothing can be seen. You are enjoying the seen, but if there is no Seer, what importance does the seen have? You have become a victim of your own concepts: “I am somebody”. And with that concept, you are trying to identify yourself. It is an impossibility. Unless you throw away your copper coin, you will never be able to enjoy the golden coin! You will all be familiar with the psychology of a dog and its bone. If he catches a bone, he is not going to leave it alone for a moment, even if you place a delicious dish in front of him. [Maharaj chuckles]. Human beings are like that. You have accepted so many concepts, that you steadfastly refuse to leave them behind, even for this treasure!

Even when the Master says that, “You are Brahman”, you reply with “No, no! How can I be Brahman?” This is just an example I’m giving you. Don’t take what I am saying literally. What I am saying is that you have to change your psychology, and change your identity. Mould yourself according to this spiritual knowledge. Spiritual knowledge just means Perfect Identification, Spontaneous Conviction. It is a simple thing, but courage is needed for you to accept the Reality, that you are Brahman. You are no longer a disciple, or a devotee. It is a fact, and not a concept, because you are Ultimate Truth.

91. Why the Naam Mantra?

The origin of the Naam Mantra goes back to Dattatreya, the founder of our lineage. Then came Revanath Maharaj, and for the next thousand or so years, this Mantra has been given to devotees and disciples. The Naam Mantra has been passed down, from one illustrious Master to another, and more recently, from Bhausaheb Maharaj to Siddharameshwar Maharaj to Nisargadatta Maharaj, who passed it on to all his disciples, including myself. Don’t underestimate its power. The sacred words of the Naam Mantra, are used to hammer the ego, in the preliminary stage.

The Mantra is prescribed, so that you can come out from the vicious circle of illusion. After Spontaneous Conviction, comes the “Stateless State”, or the way you were prior to beingness. This will unfold naturally, without any deliberate act on your part, or without the use of the imagination. You will feel: “I am totally separate from the body, separate from all these bodies, separate from the five elements. “I Have Nothing to Do With Anything.”

92. Why do we have Naam Mantra meditation?

When you recite the Naam Mantra, you are impressing that invisible consciousness with Reality: “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”. This deliberate act will bring about spontaneous living. You will forget about yourself. You will forget about everything. This state is called samadhi trance. It is one in which your body-identity is completely forgotten. The consciousness is absent. Though your Presence is there, there is no consciousness in any form. In this state, the consciousness is unknown. It is invisible consciousness, Invisible Presence, where there is no fear of death, where there is no need of happiness, where there is no need of peacefulness, where nothing is needed. “That is Your Original Place of Original Things.”

The Naam Mantra clears away all the mind’s habits and confusion, and rids it of its illusory problems. Use the Naam Mantra with full faith and confidence. It is a very powerful tool. At the same time, accept and absorb what the Master is saying. Do not dissect the words, as this only brings about mental struggle and contradictions. The power behind the Master’s words will ignite your Inner Master. If you question, and doubt what the Master is saying, you are just wasting your time. There are no contradictions. The Master has only one message. It is the Final Truth: “Except for your Selfless Self there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master”.

Because of the consciousness, you consider yourself to be a man or woman. You view yourself as a human being. Consciousness is working in that human form. All the activities are performed through consciousness. The mistake was made when consciousness accepted the illusion, “I am the body”. This identification with the body-form created all the problems. The Naam Mantra is an effective tool that will reverse the process, and correct the mistake. Reality will replace illusion, and “I am Ultimate Reality” will supplant “I am the body”.

To return to your place of origin, all the layers that have covered over your Presence, need to melt, so that there are no add-ons left. The power of the Naam Mantra will demolish everything that is not permanent, and changeless.

93. Will the Naam Mantra help my spirituality?

I am asking you to recite the Mantra, at all times, with full faith. The power of the Mantra, the strength of the Mantra, the transformative power of the Mantra depends entirely on the value and importance that you place on it. If you value it highly, and with complete faith, and deep self-involvement, it will take you to the bottomless bottom of Reality. The Naam Mantra has immense value, but, if you do not take it seriously, and recite it in a mechanical fashion alone, it will simply not work. It will not empower you.

The Spirit or Presence, through which you are talking, through which you are listening, through which you are watching, through which you are understanding, through which you are doing all your activities, is highly sensitive. Whatever is impressed upon it is immediately reflected.

I often use this example of someone who abuses you verbally. Your response is immediate. You wish to retaliate with similar abusive language, or maybe even punch him on the nose! This interaction demonstrates how seriously we take words and their meanings. How easily we absorb everything! If someone uses abusive language, we see it as a “personal attack on the ego”. This creates an atmosphere. Someone calls you “an ass”. You are offended. So, you react, and call that person an ass as well, and so it goes on.

The sacred words of the Naam Mantra mean “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”. They are imbued with vibrations, energy that have a profound effect on Spirit. Do you follow? Therefore, taking into account, the sensitivity of Spirit, we give these sacred words. And after continuous reciting of the Mantra, the effects will be absorbed by the Invisible Listener within you. The Naam Mantra is working on your Invisible Presence, not on the body-form.

That Invisible Listener within you is hidden. I am addressing the Invisible Listener within you, not your body-form. It is not the body-form that is listening, but the Spirit or Presence. And, that Spirit or Presence is absorbing the powerful vibrations of the Naam Mantra. The Mantra confirms your real Identity, your true Identity. That is its purpose.

Of course, the Mantra is also illusion, but we need to use a secondary thorn to remove the primary, illusory thorn. Will the Naam Mantra help you spiritually? Of course, because it is a practical tool, a medium, that will make your spirituality pragmatic. The Naam Mantra will establish a strong foundation, by removing all the illusory concepts, with which you have constructed your dream life. It will make your spirituality real, and alive. You will live it!

How many so-called spiritual people, end their life trembling with fear on their death-bed? This means that their spiritual knowledge has not been absorbed. Recite the Naam Mantra at all times, and then, that pressure of death, that fear of death will dissolve, because you will be convinced that there is no death. There is only death for the food-body-form. After Conviction, there will be no more tension or fear, unhappiness or dispeace. The Naam Mantra is the Master Key that opens the door to your Ultimate Reality. Respect it, value it, and use it at all times!

94. Why is the Naam Mantra required?

Because you are under the false impression that you are somebody, and Brahman is something else, that is separate from you. Your Original Identity is Brahman. You, yourself are Brahman. Brahman is not separate from you. Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. It is like you have been under some kind of a spell looking for Brahman.

The concepts of “God” and “religion” were also created to offer comfort to the masses, as well as trust and faith. They are there to provide security, and to give us something to aspire to: “God is great! Oh God, bless me! God will help me!” This is all okay to give us some temporary relief, however, what is being dished out to the masses, is not the whole truth. There is some truth there, but it is not the whole elephant!

God is not separate from you. If there were no Presence, who is going to identify your God? For you to even utter the word “God”, your Presence is essential. Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence is most important. Reciting the Mantra will establish this Conviction. Non-stop concentration and hammering will lead to the realization of your Reality: what you always were, are, and always will be – “I am That”. That Spontaneous experience will appear, and then, there will be peacefulness, beyond your imagination.

95. In the beginning, I must put in some effort?

You have accepted the concepts, without any discrimination. You have accepted that you are a man or a woman, a father, son or daughter. You have accepted that you were born on a certain date, and you expect to die at a certain age. You have absorbed all these illusory concepts like a sponge. It is not your fault, because as children we had no control over, who or what, was influencing and conditioning us.

This indoctrination has made your ego very strong, and set in its ways. To loosen the stronghold that the ego has over you, the Master gives you the sacred Mantra. The Master tells you that you are Brahman. You are Almighty God. You are Ultimate Truth. But, tragically, you are not accepting the Truth. You are accepting your gender, your position in society, your adopted faith or religion, without question, but when the Master places your Truth before you, you laugh, and say, “How can I be Brahman?” And maybe you even think that the Master is making fun of you, by proposing such a preposterous idea!

What the Master says is true, but you are unable to accept it, because of your long association with the body. You have forgotten your identity, and therefore, you will need a lot of hammering, to convince and remind you of your original identity.

The Master says: “Except for your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, Atman, Paramatman”. However, you are not accepting this. It is such a waste of your life! But, if someone calls you an “ass”, you accept it instantly, and retaliate with full force.

When the Master tells you that you are Ultimate Truth, Ultimate Reality, you should be deeply touched, stirred and moved, moved because Spirit is hearing its own story. It is being reminded of its Identity. But, because your concepts are in the way, the Master’s words are not penetrating these illusory layers, that have covered over your Presence.

The Naam Mantra will reduce the force of the mind, ego and intellect. The process is a melting process. You are covered in ash. The Master removes the ash. And underneath the ash, the fire is burning.

Various words have been used as Mantras: Aham Brahmasmi, Shivoham, Soham, etc. Concentrate on the words given to you by your Master. It is only by concentrating on these words, that they will be absorbed. And then, eureka: “Aha! I Am That”.

96. So, will the Naam Mantra help me to identify myself?

Words are only words, however, through these specific, sacred words, you will be inspired from within. When you hammer yourself with “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”, you are removing concepts, that are obscuring your identity. For example, if you consider yourself to be female or male, then this identity is stopping you from accepting your true Identity – that you are Ultimate Truth. This illusory concept, and many others like it, are barriers to your ability to accept the Reality. These concepts narrow your vision, and keep you functioning as a mere, limited, powerless, body-form. Even though you know intellectually, that you are Ultimate Truth, or Brahman, that knowledge, is not known to you. It is still out of reach. You have not been able to absorb this knowledge because of the illusory, conceptual clutter that is in the way.

And even though you may know everything about spirituality, and about Brahman, you are still searching outside of yourself to find Brahman. You are one with Brahman. Ultimate Truth is not to be found anywhere, but within you.

“Try to identify the Searcher within you. The Individual Searcher within you, is Ultimate Truth, Through Which the Entire World is Projected.”

Listen carefully! Wake up to this fact. I am repeating the same thing, again and again. Without Presence, your body is a dead body. Accept this Truth. If you accept it, you will stop taking the body-form for real. Absorb this knowledge! If Presence is not there, who will talk about the world? Who will talk about the gods and the goddesses? All the gods and goddesses came along with you, when Presence touched with the body. Will you still know of these gods and goddesses when you leave the body? Will you still know Rama and Krishna? Where was Rama and Krishna prior to beingness? And where will Rama and Krishna be, after your body dissolves?

So many stories came along with the body-form, fictional, fairy stories. I am not criticizing these stories, but, be clear, in order to identify Rama or Krishna, or any god for that matter, and in order to identify your Master, Presence is a prerequisite. Without your Presence, there can be no identification of anything, no identification whatsoever. Therefore, forget about the gods and goddesses. Forget about Rama and Krishna. Identify yourself! Identify that Unidentified Identity that is your True Identity. Your Presence is Invaluable Presence. Identify your Presence. I am talking about that Presence, that Invisible Presence within you.

This practice is free. There is no charge. The only cost is your devotion. I am asking for your devotion, devotion to your Selfless Self. At least, spend two or three hours out of twenty-four regularly. You are doing it for you. I am not asking you to meditate for me. This is for your benefit. If you don’t get rid of your concepts, and wake up to your Reality, there is the possibility of seeing another dream, like this one. Therefore, be serious! Casual spirituality will not cut it.

The Mantra is composed of ancient, sacred words. Through these words you are hammering yourself with this basic knowledge, that is universally known – “I am Brahman”.

But, even though it may be universally known, that knowledge needs to turn into Realization. The Mantra will assist in bringing this about spontaneously, but only, if your earnestness and sincere devotion is driving you forward.

I take on the role of Master for the purpose of teaching. But “Master”, is just a name that has been ascribed, like “disciple” or “devotee”. There is no difference between us. Our bodies differ, that is all. Identify this knowledge. Digest it! Convince yourself! Read the book Selfless Self. It addresses the questions, difficulties and problems that are concerning you.

These days, my health is not permitting me to talk with you. I have already told you everything, again and again. Now you have to absorb it. You have the basic knowledge, the complete knowledge. So, try and identify yourself. Apart from the daily, two hour concentrated meditation, recite the Mantra at all times. Whenever you remember to recite it, whether you are working, cleaning, bathing, cooking, just recite it. In time, you will no longer have to recite it, as this will just happen by itself, spontaneously.

97. I cannot come to India to receive the Naam Mantra...

If you cannot come to India, then use the Mantra Aham Brahmasmi, or, “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”. It is not compulsory for you to receive the Naam Mantra. Have strong faith in the Master’s words: “Except for Selfless Self, there is no Brahman, Atman, Paramatman”. If you have full faith in the Master who is teaching you, then a Mantra is not necessary. The Mantra is only a medium that creates a conducive atmosphere. It is not only about reciting the Mantra, there is to be a spontaneous awakening of: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. Only then, will your originality emerge, with the result that, when it is time for you to leave the body, there will not be any more dreams.

98. A casual approach to meditation is futile

If you do not have the Naam Mantra, recite Aham Brahmasmi, with full confidence and concentration. You may sit for half an hour, or one or two hours, or divide your time accordingly. But don’t waste your time. In the beginning, devote as much time as you can!

When the illusory concepts disappear, then, the reflection of Ultimate Truth appears upon your Presence. This, in turn, leads to Conviction.

What is needed is regular churning, regular reciting, and regular hammering. You are to act forcefully, and deliberately, in the beginning. This intellectual act will lead to a practical experience, whereby all these concepts dissolve slowly, silently and permanently. Then, you will feel spontaneous blissfulness inside because your Invisible Presence is the Ultimate Truth, the central point of this whole world.

The world does not have its own identity. It is reflected from your Presence. The entire world is projected out of your Presence. If there is no Presence within the body, there is no world. Simple fact! When the Spirit clicks with the body, the world is projected. When you leave the body, the world disappears. Your Invisible Anonymous Presence is Ultimate Truth, through which the entire world is projected. We know the basics intellectually, but to absorb this knowledge, to digest this knowledge, to digest this Reality, you must be courageous and patient. Meditate, contemplate, take it seriously.

Time after time, what happens is that seekers come here and take the Mantra, but afterwards, they do not do any meditation practice. They don’t want to put in any effort. Instead, they expect some changes to take place miraculously. And then, they complain: “Oh, Maharaj, I am not finding that happiness you spoke of, or that blissfulness. There’s too many thoughts going round and round. It is hopeless. I’m depressed”. This casual approach does not work. These spiritual travellers are just roaming here and there, looking for one spiritual massage, after another.

How many times do I have to tell you, that without your involvement, without your earnestness, devotion, sincerity and longing to find out who you are, you will remain in the illusory ditch, crying over a dream. This process is not a one-way process, where the Master does the work for you. No! It will not happen like that. The Master is giving you a hundred percent guarantee, but only if you fulfil your side of the bargain, and devote some time for Selfless Self.

If you are sincere with your meditation, ultimately, all the concepts will be cleared out, and in its place, there will be exceptional happiness and peace. But this will not happen without your effort. Meditation is a must. It is indispensable because there is no other way, of absorbing the knowledge, and removing illusion.

In the beginning, as you recite the Mantra, you may experience a degree of monotony, laziness, and reluctance. Ignore these feelings! Don’t neglect your meditation because this human body, has presented you with a golden opportunity, to wake up from this long dream, and to ensure that it is your last dream. The Master says, “this is your last dream”, therefore, it is your last dream!

While attending to your responsibilities, and caring for your family, you have a duty to find out the secrets of this world. The secret of this world is that it is an illusory world. The entire world is an illusory world. The entire “seen”, is reflected out of the Seer that is Ultimate Truth. This means you are Final Truth, for whom there is no birth and death, no past, no future, no deed, no doer, no experience, no experiencer, no witness, etc. The open secret is that, except for your Selfless Self, there is nothing. Everything is within you. Nothing is outside of you. But to absorb this knowledge, and to live like the Master that you are, you must undergo disciplined meditation, and continuous hammering.

In the beginning, when we give the Soham Sadhana, make an effort to recite the Mantra non-stop. This is commando training, with a no-nonsense strategy. It is a no-nonsense assault on your illusory body-based knowledge. Be serious! There is work to be done, to remove the layers of illusion that have accumulated over a lifetime.

Beware of any tricks played by the mind, say, any unpleasant thoughts and feelings. Don’t be dissuaded! Tell yourself, “I have to do this practice. I have to continue. If I don’t, I will never be free!” And then, after continuous hammering and churning, it will become easier.

You are like a big computer that has caught some kind of virus. That virus has to be removed, so that the computer can be restored to its pristine state. Meditation is the base, the foundation, the antivirus software that will solve this problem. When you install this programme, then all the files that have been corrupted by the virus will be erased. The virus is body-based knowledge. Layers of this knowledge are obscuring your Pure Presence, your Invaluable Presence.

This practical approach of reciting the Naam Mantra, will clear the battlefield of conflicting problems, that you think you have, with illusory others, and imaginary enemies. It will bring your struggles to an end. You will realize the fact that there are no others, and there are no enemies. And there is no battlefield! You are like the space or the sky. All your battles have been imaginary ones. You have not been fighting with anyone. You have been fighting with the air.

Again, I must emphasize, that meditation is the only effective medium for Conviction. Theoretical knowledge will not do, neither will visiting Masters. Why not? Because the Master is within you. You must know yourself directly, and not indirectly, through words. Don’t depend on the Master. The Master will guide you, but he will guide you, to stand on your own two feet. You are wholly independent.

How long are you going to remain a disciple for? Nisargadatta said: “I am not making you disciples, but Masters”. So, even if you visited a thousand Masters, it would still not help you because the Master is within you, and you are ignoring your Inner Master. You are still under some delusion that the Master is separate from you. There is no separation. This misunderstanding comes from your identification with the body-form.

You are formless. You are within every being. The bodies are different, but the Spirit is one. Meditation is the medium through which you can identify yourself in a real sense. It is not possible otherwise.

Your approach is casual because you have no loyalty. Your wavering mind is taking you on a joyride. “Stop Following the Mind. Let the Mind Follow You.” Be loyal to yourself, and be loyal to your Master. If you don’t have faith in any Master, then place your faith in a material idol, or in a symbol made of stone, or whatever. Somehow, and somewhere in you, there has to be loyalty – faith in yourself. You must have faith in something, a focus, trust in something, like in the famous story of Eklavya from the Mahabharata.

The Master Dronacharya, refused to teach Eklavya the art of archery. But Eklavya did not give up. With the help of his Inner Master, he learned, and perfected the art of archery. Dronacharya was astounded by his skill, and immediately, accepted Eklavya as his Master. This illustrates the strength of the Inner Master. Your Inner Master is the central focus, the central point of the universe. Discover your Inner Master, and let your Inner Master teach you.

The Outer Master is there to indicate your Identity. However, in practice, the Inner Master and the Outer Master. are just concepts. Don’t ignore your Inner Master! The Listener within your body is the Inner Master. That is Ultimate Truth. Therefore, have faith in yourself, and stay loyal to your own Master.

Here, I am sharing practical knowledge. You have a lot of theoretical knowledge, but it is only practical knowledge, that will lead to Conviction. Be determined, and self-disciplined! Every moment in your life is very precious. Don’t waste your time. Life is very short. Continuous hammering, continuous churning, continuous concentration are all needed.

You don’t need to spend a single penny for any of this. The only cost is your time, and your devotion, in the pursuit of your Reality.

You have it easy these days. I am asking for one, two or three hours maximum. In Bhausaheb Maharaj’s day, he used to sit in meditation for ten or twelve hours! Nowadays, this is no longer possible. Surely, you can still find two hours or so! And at other times, throughout the day, you can recite the Mantra, too. I have already given you a guarantee, but you need to do the practice. Then, everything in your life will change. Any negative feelings of depression and anxiety, will vanish after Spontaneous Conviction. So, don’t worry about anything, and continue the meditation with firm determination.

Be serious! Concentrate seriously on your true nature, your Ultimate Reality. Try to understand the secret of this world, and the secret of your Selfless Self. In short, be realized, and make others realized! Be enlightened, and make others enlightened. When you stop counting yourself as the body-form, enlightenment is not very far from you.

If there is sickness in the body, you will find the courage to cope with it. Spirituality teaches you, how not to be touched, by illness or disease. When you know that you are not the body, you are no longer so concerned about your physical illnesses, because you know that you have nothing to do with the body. Prepare yourself for the time when your body expires. Make it fearless and beautiful! When you know that there is no death for you, that you are immortal, and that knowledge has been absorbed in you, your last moments will be full of peace.

Suppose that, today your body was going to expire. Your attitude would be something like this, “Okay then, forget it! You will accept your fate because you know that the body-form is not your identity at all. The body may come, and the body may go. You are not bothered. You are not interested, because you know, that you are not going anywhere. Your Presence is just like the sky.

Always take maximum care of your body, and seek medical help when it is needed. This body is a five-elemental body. It is always out of balance. Anything can go wrong with it, at any time. Look after it! However, if the body is no longer co-operating, then, it is time to say bye bye!

Not so long ago, I met a lady. She was not a spiritual lady, but she wanted to tell me about a decision she had made. She said, “I wrote in my will, that if it so happened, that I needed to be kept alive with a ventilator, it was to be removed at once. I do not want to live with a ventilator”. She showed such courage!

Sometimes, it becomes evident, that the time has come to close the curtains. You have seen, what you were supposed to see, in the world. What more do you want to see? It is just more of the same thing, again and again. If the body is not co-operating, why choose to continue with life artificially, depending on machines to keep you alive? Forget it!

You will see this kind of courage manifesting. Understand that this is not suicide! If something happens to the body, that is beyond your control, “Fine!” That lady expressed her wishes to the doctor. It happens, and when it does, it demonstrates bravery and integrity. We are all going to leave the body at some point. Start preparing, now! Be strong, and have courage.

99. How do I practise the Mantra, and how does it work?

Reciting the Mantra is a proven, scientific method. The Mantra creates some vibrations. Breathe in as you recite the first part of the Mantra, then breathe out, as you recite the second part of it. With your eyes half-closed, focus on the tip of your nose. Concentrate on the Mantra, for around three to six months. Then, the reciting will continue by itself, spontaneously. It is like when you first learn the alphabet, and you are writing the letters, a, b, c. But then, after a time, this exercise is no longer needed, because you have mastered the language. But, in the beginning, you need to act accordingly, until the knowledge is established, until it is formed. The Mantra’s vibrations address your Selfless Self.

Everything you have ever heard, and listened to, has been recorded. It has left a trail of impressions. You are like a computer that has created some wrong files. When we entered this body-form, you accepted it. You blindly signed on the dotted line, “I am the body”, even though it was not your identity. And after that, you accepted all the other concepts that were engraved in you, by parents, teachers, church, employers, etc. We recite the Mantra in order to undo everything that we have accepted as our identity.

Basically, we are formless nobodies, but the body-form creates the illusion that we are somebodies. Your body-form may be very handsome now, as a young man, but when you reach old age, all your pretty looks will be gone. What is Reality? Whose Reality? Your Inner Spirit is neither young, nor old.

If you sit alone for five minutes, you will quickly start to feel bored. And so, you will read a newspaper, watch a movie, or turn on the TV, and choose from a long list of entertainment programmes on offer. Presence likes to remain engaged. It doesn’t enjoy boredom, and so, needs a lot of distractions. All our needs are for the body-form. We behave like children who quickly tire of doing the same thing again and again, and who are always complaining: “Oh! I am bored. I don’t want to do this anymore”, etc. You have to keep your child busy doing various things. In a similar way, Presence likes to engage through the body. If it remains idle, disturbing concepts may start to flow.

You will have spiritual courage after identifying yourself. If you fall ill, you will know that whatever illness you have is the body’s illness, and not yours. We have some devotees who are seriously suffering from cancer, of one form or another. But, they are happy because they don’t accept it, or buy into it.

They know that nothing happens to Presence. Nothing can touch Presence. Whatever happens, happens to the body. They are not that. When you know the Reality, you become the Master of the mind. This means that the wrong concepts will not enter your mind.

Suppose someone says that you are a very bad person. You will just let this comment wash over you, because you know that “bad” and “good” are concepts. Nisargadatta Maharaj said, if someone told me, “you are a very, good saint”, it would not give me any pleasure. If he said, “you are a very, bad saint”, it would not depress me. When Reality is established within you, whatever is thrown at you, will not touch you. The world cannot touch you. You will continue to live as before, but without any ego, and without a sense of “I am doing this, and that”.

After absorption, knowledge will start to flow. You will have the spontaneous feeling that you are everywhere in the world, and in every being.

You used to consider yourself in the world. After Realization, you will see that the world is within you. The body, and the entire world, are projected from you. You are not concerned with the body, and not concerned with the world.

100. So, we recite the Mantra “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”?

The meaning of the Mantra is “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”. It is the Final Truth that you are, which cannot be described, or seen, by the naked eye. We can be aware of it, and sense it.

You may feel a little depressed, or nervous when you start reciting the Mantra. Dismiss these waves! It is a good thing. It means that the cleaning process is in operation. Suppose your house was full of dust. When you start to wipe the dust away, you may smell an odour, but only for a brief moment. The smell goes after the dust has been removed.

During this cleansing process, the smell takes the form of disturbing feelings, or thoughts. Put up with it! It is a small price to pay for the removal of concepts. And then, life, will live life, perfectly! When you know that you are not the body-form, life will unfold beautifully with abundant happiness.

101. Do I recite the Mantra aloud, or silently in my mind?

Recite the Mantra in your mind only. Meditation is done through the mind only. Recite the Mantra, along with your breathing, to make it more effective in the beginning. The Mantra creates exceptional vibrations, which make you forget your body-identity. It will help you to identify yourself, and live a happy life, with the knowledge that you are Ultimate Truth. And then you will talk spontaneously, just like I am talking now. Your Self-knowledge will begin to open up.

You are young at the moment. But after some years, you will become old like me! Our bodies grow old, but our Spirit is changeless, ageless. You can be young or old, but the Spirit within that form is neither of these. Reality is there, you just have to grasp it. Be serious. I am talking to everybody. Don’t take it lightly, because this is an illusory world. Whatever you plan, is, in fact, meaningless. Unless you identify yourself in a real sense, you cannot live happily. Without proper identification, your life will be meaningless.

102. When I recite the Mantra, do I have to pay attention to the meaning of the Mantra?

It is not necessary. Just do it. You know the meaning, so you need not concentrate on it. The Mantra acts spontaneously.

When you take a drop of poison, do you start thinking about what is going to happen? No! The result is death. When you take this drop of nectar, the result is immortality. So, there is no need to concentrate on the meaning of the Mantra. The Mantra will act spontaneously within you. The vibrations will take effect. And, you will identify yourself in a real sense.

This is direct knowledge. “You are the Principle. You are the Central Point. Your Spontaneous Identity is the Central Point of this world.” All that you think, consider, and see, is the Seer’s reflection. As soon as consciousness arose, you immediately started thinking. That ego, intellect and mind started influencing you, and created endless thoughts, which made you accept this world as true. This world is not true, in the same way that the world of dreams is not true.

Prior to beingness, nothing was there. There was no dream world, and no illusory world. Your Presence is behind everything. You are the Central Point. If there is no Seer in this body, there is no one to think about any of these things?

Get some practical knowledge! Do some practice! It is most important, and desperately needed. So don’t waste your time! Try to identify yourself. My Master, Nisargadatta Maharaj, says: “Except for your Selfless Self there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman. What more do you want?

It is only because you consider yourself to be the body-form, that many, many questions keep arising. There are no questions. All the questions are illusory! The Questioner does not know that, “I am the Questioner”. But you have imposed some form on the Questioner, such as a man or a woman. Suppose that just for a moment, there was no Presence, what will happen to your questions? Where is the dream? Is the dream there? Is this illusory world there?

If there were no Presence in your body-form just for a moment, you would be certified dead, and your body taken away to be burned or buried. You follow? Any questions?

103. Does meditation mean repeating the Naam Mantra, or sitting in one place and meditating?

I will instruct you. You are to repeat the Naam Mantra, and recite it all the time. When you are sitting for meditation, sit in a lotus position, with a straight back. If that is not comfortable for you, then sit on a chair. If you try to stay in an uncomfortable position that is putting a strain on your body, it will distract you from your meditation. Be relaxed!

In the beginning, you are to allocate a minimum of two hours for meditation. This period is to be given to complete concentration, with your full involvement. During this meditation practice, sit in one place, and do nothing but meditation. You can either meditate for two hours continuously, or for two one-hour slots, or even four half-hour slots. Find out what suits you best, and what fits into your daily routine.

Throughout the day, repeat the Naam Mantra as often as possible. Get into the habit of chanting it, remembering to make it part of your daily routine. You can recite it while you are carrying out any activity, working, shopping, cooking, walking, bathing. Recite the Mantra, at every available opportunity, and then it will become for you, as natural as breathing. Do it, and do it sincerely! In time, the Mantra will recite by itself spontaneously. It will be humming in the background 24/7. You will go to sleep with the Naam, and wake up with the Naam. But, to begin with, you must make a determined effort to recite it.

You are to meditate until you recover from your amnesia, and regain your memory. This means, until you have Conviction, until the knowledge that you are Ultimate Truth has been absorbed. Many seekers say, “Oh, I am realized, I have the knowledge!” Literal knowledge, and bookish knowledge, only offer you temporary relief, not permanent.

You may have different experiences during meditation. You may feel that you have lost your body-based-knowledge.

This is a good experience, but it, too, needs to be dissolved because whatever spiritual experiences occur, are also only layers on your Presence. It is an appearance upon your Presence. And, at the Ultimate stage, there is no experiencer or experience.

All experiences are body-related, and therefore, illusion, including those experiences of “I am Brahman”. There were no experiences prior to beingness. There will not be any experiences after you leave the body. Therefore, whatever experiences you may have, and however blissful they may be, keep going beyond them, keep going deeper and deeper, until both the experiencer and the experiences have dissolved. That is the Ultimate Stage.

104. I have been reciting the Mantra for a few months. Should I continue?

Of course, you must continue! You have been reciting your concepts for years! Continue reciting the Mantra. You need to be more patient. You have had a lifetime of living with concepts, so, it will take a little time to remove everything which you have accepted as reality. Also, it takes some time to absorb the knowledge. I have told you, that you need to put in a determined effort in the beginning. You say you have been reciting the Mantra for a few months now, and you already want to stop. Who is counting the months? Who is counting? You have this amazing opportunity to find out who you are, and it is like, you cannot even be bothered! I am only asking that you devote two hours per day for yourself.

You must be serious about the practice. Recite the Mantra for as long as it is needed. This will vary according to one’s involvement. Your casual approach is not helping you. So, don’t be half-hearted! The rewards that will come your way are unimaginable. Therefore, be strong, and with renewed vigour and determination, continue reciting the Mantra!

The original consciousness will create an atmosphere, after a period of reciting the Mantra. This atmosphere is stateless, thoughtless. It is your natural state, the way you were prior to beingness, without any qualities. When this happens, your bodily identity will be completely forgotten.

When the Spirit clicked with the body, you experienced “I”. The consciousness came across with the mind, ego, and intellect, and then the body started functioning. Understand this process! Prior to beingness, there was no experiencer and no experiences. There was nothing. When the beingness took form, and the consciousness touched with the mind, ego and intellect, everything started functioning. And, instantly, you accepted your bodily identity, and adopted the pose of a human being.

The mind manufactures thousands of thoughts per minute. And we accepted all these thoughts, because we did not know ourselves. But now, you are approaching the Ultimate Stage. The veils are being removed slowly, silently and permanently. So, carry on reciting the Mantra. Don’t be impatient. It will take some time to undo the years of conditioning. I am giving you 100% guarantee that if you follow my instructions, a peaceful, happy, fearless, tension-free life is already yours.

105. Nisargadatta Maharaj said: “the purpose of the Mantra is to surrender the seen to Brahman”. How is this done?

Yes! Because when the Spirit touched with the body, the concept of “I am somebody” emerged. The consciousness accepted “I am somebody”. And, so, Nisargadatta Maharaj said that the Mantra acts in a way that will remedy this mistaken notion.

The Mantra, “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”, is meant as the Final Truth. The Mantra is hammering you with your Reality spontaneously. You forgot about your Identity, therefore, the Invisible Meditator within you, reminds you: “I am Brahman”. Brahman is the Ultimate Truth, your Final Truth.

All the saints say exactly the same thing: “Try to identify yourself”. You are identifying yourself in the body-form, and that is illusion! Therefore, concentrate on the Concentrator within you, until the Concentrator disappears!

Surrender the seen! You are not the body! Surrender your body-based-knowledge! Identify your Selfless Self. How were you prior to consciousness? How will you be after leaving consciousness? Through this consciousness, you are observing this world, watching this world. Is existence true or false? Identify that! Identify!

106. What is the minimum time for meditation?

There is no hard and fast rule. It all depends on the extent to which you can devote your time. Sometimes people meditate for one, two, three, or four hours, and others, for only ten minutes. In the beginning, give the maximum time possible to meditation. Whatever time you can afford, make sure that you are able to give your full concentration to reciting the Mantra. Concentration is most important, so that you can hammer yourself relentlessly with, “I am Ultimate Truth. Ultimate Truth I am”. We need to recite the Mantra, for as long as we are under the illusion that we are the body-form.

Spiritual knowledge is needed to correct wrong knowledge. Spiritual knowledge is needed, so that we can identity ourselves. Spirituality is needed to dissolve this illusory identity. Once it has served its purpose, it has no further use.

You have forgotten your Original Identity. Your Identity is vast, like the space or the sky, and it is way, way beyond that. But we have reduced ourselves to the status of the human, body-form, to mere, limited mortals. Be serious! Try to find the answer to, “Who am I?” You should be deeply involved in your quest. It should be earnest, passionate, a matter of life or death. Why? Because it is such a waste of a life, to take the dream for reality, and to sleepwalk through life, never knowing the secret of your existence. Make it a priority to know yourself. Follow the Mantra at every available moment. We have to keep on hammering ourselves, to rid us forever of all that is false.

Knowledge basically means identifying yourself, or knowing yourself in a real sense. When you convince the meditator that you are Ultimate Truth, you are dissolving the strongly-held, fixed illusion, that you are separate from Ultimate Truth. Body-based knowledge disturbs and confuses us all, therefore it is to be completely discarded and ignored. Meditation, concentration, and reading books are all theoretical knowledge. This theoretical knowledge then becomes practical knowledge.

What is practical knowledge? Practical knowledge means living as Brahman. You live without concern for the body, because you know that you are formless. You no longer have any cares because you know that you are unborn, and that there was nothing prior to beingness, nor will there be, after beingness. Therefore, when the Spontaneous Conviction arises, your foundations will be rock solid. You will live spontaneously, and nothing will have any power whatsoever, to touch you, or unsettle you.

Before meeting the Master, and pre-initiation, we were under the enormous pressure of thousands of concepts. With all these concepts that were tightly wrapped around us, we were struggling to live peacefully and happily. It was an impossibility! Be enthusiastic and eager to remove the concepts that have crippled you! Don’t ask what is the minimum time! Give meditation your maximum time. You are showing a lack of interest and involvement.

107. Will meditation make me spiritually strong?

It depends on how serious you are about it, and how involved you are. Meditation is the best foundation, the only foundation. Spiritual discussion will not help you. We could go on talking for hours together, but this exercise would be a meaningless exercise!

I am trying to make you stand on your own feet. You are independent. There is no need for you to depend on anyone else. You can do it! All you need is the courage to accept Reality. I am encouraging you. Encourage yourself! Build some extraordinary confidence in yourself! It is already there. Tell yourself: “Nothing is impossible, I can do it!”

All these saintly people have the same Spirit that you have. The Spirit within this body, and the Spirit in all these other bodies, is not different. But you have doubts, and are always underestimating yourself, wondering, “How can it happen?” All that the Master says, is it really true?”

We depend upon others. We depend upon some spiritual power, some godly power. This is illusion. It is coming from your insecurities and fearfulness. The fact is that you are completely independent. You are free from all burdens. There are no burdens. You are worrying about what is going to happen. Nothing has happened. Nothing is happening, and nothing is going to happen. Be strong! Meditation shows you your inner strength, and then, you will start roaring like a lion!

When you wake up from a dream, it is very quickly forgotten. You can have many problems in dreams, all sorts of worrying problems that cause you stress. For example, say in a dream, your business lost lakhs of rupees. And then, when you wake up, you realize that you did not suffer any loss. It was just a dream! Nothing happened after all. It is the same in this long dream of life, nothing has ever happened. Mould yourself in this way!

108. Does meditation mean that I have to sit for four hours?

See, there are no hard and fast rules. If you meditate for four hours, the effect will be greater. If you have sufficient time, without neglecting your duties, you can spend half an hour, one, two, three or four hours, etc, it depends on your circumstances. Don’t neglect your family responsibilities: “Oh sorry father! I have no time. I cannot take care of you because I have to go and meditate”. This is not real. This is not pragmatic spirituality. Whatever time you spend, do it willingly, earnestly, and not with any ill-will.

It is very simple. Everything is within you. Just have some faith, and try to identify yourself. You don’t have to spend any money. You don’t have to, go here and there. There should not be a dual mind: “Oh, I will go to this Master, then that Master”. I am not criticizing anyone, but nowadays, there are thousands of Masters, saying, “do this, do that!”, extracting money from the vulnerable, naive, undiscerning seekers. Be aware! Everything starts from you, and everything ends with you. You are the principle of spirituality! You are the principle of this world. Be loyal, and stay loyal, in this way: “Yes, I have that perfection. I can do it! Ultimate Truth is not separate from me!”

109. Some days I cannot even recite the Mantra for half an hour. What then?

Forget about how long you can meditate for! Don’t count the length of time. Sitting down to meditate is not compulsory. “You Are to Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator Within You.” You Are to Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator, “I Am Brahman”, hammering yourself at all times. After you have reached the Ultimate Truth, the meditation happens spontaneously, 24/7, even in deep sleep.

You are a man named Ravi. You do not have to remind yourself of this while you are asleep, that, “I am Ravi”? That name “Ravi” is one with your Spirit. Likewise, the Master says your name is Brahman. Brahman means Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. So, though you are holding the body, you are still Ultimate Truth. You remain as that “State”. Now the ball is in your court. The way you handle it is up to you. You are there, and there alone, whatever the circumstances that are maybe going on around you.

110. Do I just close my eyes for a few minutes?

That’s okay. It’s very good. Meditation is most important. Give it your full concentration. Early morning meditation, say at 4am or 5am is an excellent time. Close your eyes, and sit calmly, and quietly. Take a look! Observe! See what’s there within you. You will experience the vibrations, and some feelings of tremendous happiness, and peacefulness. That happiness and peacefulness are not separate from you. The happiness that is in you, is your nature. The peacefulness that is in you, is your nature.

Meditation will clear out all the body-based garbage. When everything has been removed, emptiness will remain. And that emptiness will be filled with happiness. Happiness and peace will flow, gushing out, and overflowing. There is no end to this outpouring, as it is coming from Source, from the bottomless bottom of Reality, the eternal fount of Reality.

This pure joy, this expansion that feels like it is not able to contain the ecstasy, cannot be imagined. It is incomparable, unparalleled, priceless! This will happen, spontaneously, with meditation.

111. When I recite the Mantra, should I concentrate on the words, the sound, the breath, the Master, or just Selfless Self?

Try to concentrate on Selfless Self! As you know, the Master is formless, but in the beginning, the mind will not easily let you concentrate directly on Selfless Self. If this is the case, when you see the Master in the body-form, you can concentrate on the Master. See the Master in the body-form, and then you will feel some vibrations and rays inside. As a matter of fact, there is no difference between the Master and yourself, but in spite of this, the mind stubbornly refuses to accept this Reality. To encourage the mind to accept this Reality, you have to concentrate on the Master, or on Selfless Self. Concentration on the Master as the form, will help you in the beginning. It will be easier for you to concentrate in this way.

There is no difference between the Master and the disciple. There may appear to be different forms, but there is only One Spirit in all these forms. In all the bodies, Spirit is One, just like within all the buildings, space is One. Similarly, there are lakhs of beings. Every being has the same Spirit called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God or Master. But, directly or indirectly, we consider ourselves as the body-form. Concentration is needed to loosen all our attachments.

We have an egoistic “I”. Dissolve that egoistic “I”! “I” is to be a humble “I”! Again, don’t take these words literally! What is needed is really very simple. Try to identify yourself. This “I” does not know that it is an independent identity. It is vast, it is everywhere – omnipresent.

The Master is not separate from you. Stop playing with the words, “Master, God, Ultimate Truth, maya, Brahman”. Through narration and explanations, the Master is trying to convince, the Invisible Listener within you of your Ultimate Truth. There is only one principle: “Selfless Self is the Ultimate Truth That You Are”.

Why do you need the Naam Mantra and the Master? Because you have forgotten your Identity, and consequently, treat this dream as true. Each and every day, there is a different dream. Dreams are not true. This is a long dream! You need to meditate because you are treating this dream as reality. Meditation is the only medium, through which you can discard all the illusory concepts.

112. While we are going through this meditation process, can we read books?

Yes, you can read books, as long as you don’t analyze the words. You can read books, and approach the Masters, but bear in mind, that it is what they wish to convey that is of paramount importance. Don’t depend on the words! You are not supposed to analyze the Master’s words or sentences: “Why did Ramana Maharshi say this? What did that Master really mean when he said…?” No! This is not the way! What are they trying to convey from their statements and expressions? What is the gist, or the central point of your Reality? It is: “Except your Selfless Self there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman”. Meditation is needed to enable you to accept this Reality.

The strong force of your mind, ego and intellect is upon you. Directly, or indirectly, you have become a victim of your own mind and concepts. The subtle ego is warring with your mind. When you go to a friend’s house, the subtle ego has expectations: “Oh, she has not offered me any tea? She should offer me something”. If your expectations are not fulfilled, you feel depressed. All your expectations must dissolve.

You have expectations from your children. You have expectations, about how to be a good father and parent. You have expectations from the Masters, too. You want a miracle or two: “Oh, if I go to that Master, something miraculous will happen”. Nothing will happen. The Master does not perform miracles. You are the miracle worker, who makes miracles happen! This body is a miracle box, a magic box, that contains everything. But you are unaware of your box of tricks. The Spontaneous Existence in your body is the Ultimate Truth, the Final Truth.

113. Can you say something about devotion?

Yes, it is a very good question. Devotion means that you are a devotee. [“seeker” is synonymous with “devotee”] If you are a devotee, your devotion has already begun.

You are a Deity, that manifested as a devotee. Through devotion, you will find out that you are, in fact, a Deity. “Devotee, Devotion and Deity are intertwined”. These are just words!

At the initial stage, you are a devotee. At the last stage, you are a Deity. Devotee and Deity, Devotee and Deity, there is no separation. “There is No Separation Between the Devotee and the Deity. The Deity Knows Through the Devotee. The Deity Lies Within the Devotee.”

You are a devotee. You are a Deity. You are everything. Basically, you are not the body. “Devotee” and “Deity”, are body-related concepts. “Master” and “disciple” are also concepts that came along with the body. There were no concepts of “devotee”, “deity” and “devotion” prior to beingness.

You need to go through the preliminary stages until Spontaneous Conviction arises. I am, therefore, insisting on the Naam Mantra. Thereafter, no further practice will be necessary: no meditation or devotion because you are already a Deity. This means that “You Are Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. That You Are! Be With You all the Time”.

114. Should we keep the sadhana going till our last breath, or only until Spontaneous Conviction is reached?

You can do your sadhana anywhere in the world. Sometimes it is not possible to come to India due to physical weakness, mental or emotional problems, age, financial limitations, or other problems. You don’t have to come to this ashram all the time. Wherever you are, make yourself believe that except for Selfless Self, there is nothing. Convince yourself! Accept all that you are listening to, and reading. Sadhana is needed for the Conviction of your Reality.

You are considering yourself in the human form, and as you know, that is not your identity at all. Sadhana is essential to remind yourself, to hammer yourself, and demolish the ingrained concept of being a man or a woman. You are Ultimate Truth. “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. These words serve to make you forget about your body-identity.

Even if you understand that the body is not your identity at all, one day you will leave the body. And, when that day dawns, you must be thoroughly prepared. Die to your body, before the body expires. This way, you will ensure that there will not be any more dreams. This is the final terminus.

Again and again, I am placing before you the same thing. Sadhana is necessary because it is difficult to accept the Reality. The Master is required, the Mantra is required, unless of course, you have full confidence, strong confidence, just like in the case of Eklavya. Here, nothing else was needed. But if you have full confidence, strong confidence, nothing is required, just like in the case of Eklavya. In the absence of an external Master, he invited his Inner Master. His skill and achievements were beyond any, that a Master could ever have taught him!

This can happen. Your Inner Master is a very strong Master. Don’t neglect your Inner Master. Try to invite the attention of the Inner Master. Do your sadhana and concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator, that you are Brahman. When you hammer yourself with the Mantra, the body-form consciousness, turns towards Ultimate Truth.

You are formless and changeless. The changes you appear to see are illusory. You have to mould yourself, and put in some effort. The questioner is within you, so, question yourself calmly and quietly. The answers will come from within. Make your Inner Master dialogue with you. This seems like duality, however, it is not. It is only an apparent duality.

The Master is not separate from you. You are wasting your time if you approach more than one Master, while neglecting your own Master. You are underestimating yourself. You are not valuing yourself.

When you ask questions, make them practical questions. Avoid asking theoretical, or confused questions, which have no value, and will be of no help to you.

Sadhana, meditation, etc, are all illusion. Throw out your knowledge as well! After reaching the destination, you no longer need the address, the directions which you followed. Everything can be thrown out when the Knowledge and you, are One.

115. Would you say, that meditation is letting go of our attachment to thoughts?

Yes, of course! You are letting go of your attachment to everything. Through meditation, you are hammering yourself. These sacred words have tremendous power. The Spirit or Presence is highly sensitive, and therefore, it will absorb and accept the hammering. It accepts the Truth: “Yes! I Am That!”, without your knowledge. That knowledge is already within you, but you are unaware of it.

Reality is already within you, but directly or indirectly you are posing as a male or female, and expecting to have this knowledge, this Reality, with your body-based-knowledge. You are the architect of your own life. What to do, or not to do, is up to you. You need not go anywhere to find a Master, because there is no Master except for your Selfless Self.

116. What do you think of other kinds of meditation, like Buddhist meditation?

When did you come across Buddhist meditation? All these concepts came after, with the body-form. If your Presence were not there, would you know of any Buddha? And, will you know of any Buddha, Brahma, or Shiva when the body expires? You say, “This is Shiva, this is Brahma, and this is Vishnu”. When did you come across these? All these concepts began when the Spirit clicked with the body. “Brahman, Atman, Dattatreya, this thing, that thing. This is Krishna, and that is...”, and so on, and so forth.

You did not know anything prior to beingness, and you will not know anything after beingness. You are to come out of the illusory circle of concepts. Come out of it completely.

You have read so many books. You have so much bookish knowledge. Is it going to help you, when it is your time to leave the body? You know the Vedas, you may even be a Master of the Vedas, and/or a Master of many philosophical and spiritual books. What use is that kind of Master? How will that knowledge help you when it is your time to exit the body? Question yourself! All this knowledge indicates Truth. It points to the Truth, but it is not the Truth because the Truth can only be found in You!

We have the Vedas, Buddhas and Buddhists texts, etc. We also have many different spiritual traditions, and many, many spiritual concepts. These have all been created as signposts, attempts to: “Identify the Invisible Listener Within You”. I am not criticizing any of it, but, this man-made knowledge is not your Reality. It is not an end in itself. This kind of knowledge, is only a means through which, you can try to identify, The Invisible Reader Within You, That You Are Ultimate Truth. So, recognize that all this knowledge is body-based knowledge. Try and identify yourself!

117. What does concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator mean?

We always say: “Concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator within you”. The Invisible Concentrator can be felt as “I Am”, but you cannot see how it is, but it is a feeling that has been called glimpses of “I”, which is subtler than the space or sky. However, there is no comparison to the space or sky because the sky is visible to us. But, the Invisible Experiencer within this body is not visible.

You feel it, but at the same time, because you are caught up in body-based-knowledge, you are lacking in Conviction. We know that we are Brahman, but still, the Conviction is not there. To have that Conviction, or, to make that Conviction appear spontaneously, you are to concentrate on the Concentrator within you.

The concentration is a deliberate act. After some intense practice, and reaching a certain level, that concentration and the concentrator, will disappear. Nothing will remain! This is a trance-like state, or samadhi, Afterwards, Reality will open within you. And you will be filled with incredible, spontaneous peacefulness, and spontaneous happiness.

118. When I recite the Naam Mantra, do I need to fight the illusory world?

Why fight it? Ignore it! Your inner power will fight the external forces. You have inbuilt power and energy, which you are not aware of. If anything tries to attack you, or destabilise you, you will be protected by that inbuilt power. This will happen spontaneously, without your knowledge. You will be given direct guidance: “don’t go there, and don’t do that”. This stage is called the last devotion, Atma Nivedanam Bhakti.

At this ultimate stage, make a habit of having a dialogue with Selfless Self. This is Self-dialogue, Self-talking. It is really miraculous. You will receive knowledge that is beyond your imagination. When that Self-dialogue starts, knowledge will flow within you. There will be total transparency. Knowledge means just to identify oneself in a real sense. So, some deliberate efforts are required in the beginning.

Calamities, different circumstances, and unpleasant atmospheres will come your way. When they do, don’t give them too much importance. These are temporary storms. Yes, storms will come and go, but you are not going anywhere. You are there, and there only. Be firm, “Let the storms come!” Nothing will happen to you, because you are totally firm, solid, and established in Ultimate Reality. Don’t become a victim of your mind, ego, intellect, or of anybody’s concepts.

4 THE PROGNOSIS

“After Conviction, you will be able to face any challenge that comes your way. There will be exceptional happiness and peace: a subtle, subtle light. You can’t describe it in words, but it is an exceptional experience, beyond your wildest imagination.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

119. What are the results of meditation?

You will not get immediate results. I received the Naam Mantra on the 31st October 1962. In the beginning, it was not possible for me to understand what Maharaj was saying. Each evening, I used to go to Maharaj’s house, to listen to his lectures. At that time, I had very little understanding. It felt as if it was really beyond my capacity.

But Maharaj used to say, “Listen to me! Listen to me!” What he meant by this, was that the Invisible Listener was listening to his Talk. And, indirectly, everything was being engraved. Intellectually, you may not be able to understand the teaching, but the “Invisible Presence is Engraving That Reality Permanently”.

You will not see quick results, so you need to be patient. You may feel frustrated, “I can’t understand. This is way beyond my capabilities!” But your Presence is absorbing the Master’s words.

My Master used to encourage us, by giving us some very useful tips. He would say: “What exactly is in the body? Nothing but glimpses of ‘I’.” After a number of years, everything opened up, and flowered. How did this happen? Because after strong meditation, deep involvement, and faith in the Master, your Inner Master opens up the Secret of Spirituality.

The Inner Master is not separate from the Outer Master. “Inner Master” and “Outer Master” are only concepts. That Power that is within you, and behind everything, underlying everything, suddenly opens! This happened to me. It can also happen to you. My Master also used to say: “Listen, Your Presence Is Everywhere. Every being has Presence”. And then, it happened, spontaneously inside. What my Master said was happening. I started to see myself in every being. It was such a wonderful surprise!

At that time, I sometimes had very, very bad thoughts. I felt guilty, and I also felt some hatred and jealousy. I had some terrible dreams, too. All this made me feel very confused. Thereafter, after some time passed, there was a change, a turning, an opening. “Why should I feel guilty?” I asked myself. “This is the nature of the mind, the flow of thoughts. I am not going to give these thoughts any attention. I refuse to accept any more thoughts. And now I know that I am not guilty of anything”.

When Reality begins to open, it is like there is an inner voice, that is explaining everything so clearly. You feel that you are drawing closer and closer. Any sense of separation, that might have been there before, dissolves. “The Merging Process is Marching Towards Oneness”. “You Become One With That.”

Everything will start to flow. You will receive spontaneous instructions, as well as answers to all your questions. It is very funny, a miracle really, that there is a dialogue taking place within you. This happened to me. I had some unresolved questions, so I placed them before my Inner Master, and miraculously, and to my great amusement, they were answered immediately.

The physical Master does not exist. It is your Inner Master, your inner Power that is answering the questions. You will be absolutely amazed when this happens, wondering: “How is it all possible?” These answers appear instantly because your Inner Master is pleased with you. That illusory feeling, that you were somehow separate from your Inner Master, is no longer there. Nisargadatta Maharaj often said, “I am not making you a disciple, I am making you a Master”, because that Masterly Essence is already within you.

The Invisible Listener has no shape. When the Invisible Listener absorbs the knowledge, everything will suddenly fall into place and become crystal clear. You will have no further need of any Master. However, until then, you must follow the instructions from your external Master. This will draw you closer and closer to your inner Master. The outer Master guides you to the door of your inner Master, and shows you how to gain entry. If the outer Master says, “You Are Brahman”, accept it.

All these uneducated and illiterate saints and devotees, accepted what the Masters said without question, without having any doubts. You, however, are not accepting the Truth so easily. You, are in the way, with the rational mind’s habit of questioning everything: “Why this? How is that?” There is no “Why?” or “How?” There should not be any kind of analysis of the Master’s statements’ taking place. It is simple: “My Master says, I am Brahman, therefore I am Brahman”. You are to accept your Reality in this way. Keep it simple.

We have a tendency to complicate everything. Spiritual knowledge develops the spiritual intellect, which, in turn, brings the subtle ego into play again. There are various mental pressures around, so that, even though we know Reality, there is still some confusion around.

You will develop a commanding nature, and know how to act, or react, under different circumstances. That Reality will emerge from you. That inner voice will guide you. All your previous doubts will dissolve. You will no longer let the mind dictate to you. The mind will be your slave!

120. What are the changes that will take place after Conviction?

After a period of continuous meditation, after Conviction, you will be aware of some changes taking place.

Before Conviction, even though you already had spiritual knowledge, when something unexpected happened to a family member, or if an incident took place, if there were any problems or difficulties, you would react, and become irritated at that particular situation. That irritation is no longer there, after Conviction, because you know that “I am not the body”. Nothing can touch you! As Nisargadatta Maharaj used to say: “If someone says that I am a very good saint, or a very bad saint, there is no reaction, because I am neither good nor bad”. That reality will be absorbed within you, so that if anyone praises you or abuses you, it is like, “water off a duck’s back”. You have nothing to do with that, and so, you remain untouched.

This change happens because after Conviction, body-based-knowledge does not, and cannot touch you. Up until now, you maybe accepted that you were Brahman, but this knowledge was only theoretical knowledge. You did not have practical knowledge because of the influence of the five elements, the ego, the intellect and the mind. As your central point of reference was body-based, you absorbed all the concepts. Whereas, after Conviction, after reaching Ultimate Truth, after the Ultimate Stage, all these concepts dissolve because you know that you are not the body-form at all. Now you know that you are the “central point of the universe”.

If you wish to gauge the changes that are taking place, and see whether the knowledge has been absorbed, there are various, obvious signs of Realization: Forgive and forget, about those who have wronged you. Tolerance is important, too. There will be exceptional tolerance and patience, which was not there before, so that, if you heard something unpleasant, or if something happened in your family, you would not be upset or disturbed. You know that there are no enemies. You know that there is nothing.

Supposing that a close friend, or a relative dies, there may be some grief or sadness there for a moment, but then you remind yourself: “Okay this is going to happen to me also. Today this man’s body has expired, and tomorrow my body will expire”. When there is that Conviction, you will not be affected.

Having a deep longing and desire, to know the Reality is another sign. You have the ability and discernment to know Reality, calmly and quietly.

All your attachments, and concerns will be discarded. You will have no desire for sex, money, or fame. Your view of the world will change completely with Conviction. You will no longer be attracted to the material things in life, or to material happiness and peacefulness. Happiness and peacefulness will now appear spontaneously within you.

This spontaneous happiness and peace will deepen your devotion. You will find within you, all the qualities that you were previously seeking from the world. As this happiness and peace arises, and permeates your being, you will realize that you no longer need any material cause to bring you happiness and peace, because happiness and peace are your very nature.

All this will happen spontaneously. Whatever is needed is already within you. When everything the Master said would happen, happens, this will deepen your trust, both in your Master and yourself. “Yes! this is the Ultimate Truth!” These changes will take place. They are the signs of Realization, or Enlightenment. Everything will happen spontaneously. If meditation is needed, it will happen spontaneously. You will not need to go and sit down to meditate. It will simply happen by itself, and continue throughout deep sleep, as well.

So, though you are holding the body, and using the body, you will remain unconcerned and detached from it. After these changes have taken place, your lifestyle will be totally transformed. But until these changes happen, you need to continue with the meditation practice. Because sometimes after some kind of miraculous experience, you may get carried away, thinking, “Oh! I have the knowledge. I am Realized! Why bother going for meditation?” This is a kind of mental sting, that is trying to distract you from Reality. The mind, ego and intellect are always trying to trick you, trap you, or pave the way for your downfall! Be alert! There are always external forces in the form of half-knowledge, that will try to impress their old concepts on you.

After Conviction, there will be no need for you to visit another Master. Why would you? You know, who or what, you are! You are here to identify yourself, not to identify Brahman. You are to identify the Invisible Identifier within you. It is not subject to birth or death. It is shapeless, like the space or sky.

For that Conviction to appear, you need to make the necessary inner changes.

When you are faced with any kind of problem, you will learn to keep quiet, and not to feed the problem with your attention. That is the first stage. The ego will not allow us to stay completely unconcerned and detached. So, with meditation, you can learn to control your mind, ego and intellect, so that they act according to your wishes, and not, the other way round. You used to be their slave. Not any longer! This is the effect of meditation.

The first lesson in spirituality is strict meditation. It will take some time for the changes to take place. In some cases, they will happen within one month or two, and in other cases, it may take six to ten years. It all depends on whether your involvement is serious or not, and on the strength of your faith. Strong faith is most important here, as there should not be a dull mind, or a wavering mind. Don’t go to more than one Master. And better still, approach your own Master. The Master does not show you anything except your Selfless Self.

Changing Masters is meaningless, but because we have some kind of dual mind, we keep on roaming and changing Masters. You will not get anything from another new Master. “Everything Starts From You, and Everything Ends Within You. That is the Ultimate Truth, the Final Truth.”

We are trying to bring about change, to stop you being led by the mind, the ego and the intellect. Meditation is the only way.

121. After tasting the nectar, how is it reflected?

In yesterday’s lecture, the question was raised, “after tasting the amrut (nectar), how is it reflected in our spiritual body?” Here, nectar means receiving knowledge through the Spiritual Master, and absorbing it. Through the Masters, you gain the knowledge that you are Ultimate Truth. You become one with the Ultimate. There is no separation. Though you are holding the body, you are one with yourself. “Self” is a word. It has no special identity. It is called swarup, which means Selfless Self. It is One and indivisible. There is no separation. It is just like the sky which is everywhere. The sky is not divided into parts like an Indian, or Chinese sky. The sky is everywhere, and Presence is like that, too. It is everywhere. It does not depend upon the body.

Accept what the Master has told you. The Master has told you that, except your Selfless Self there is no God. It is your Reality. So why are you still looking for Brahman? It is not difficult to find Brahman or God. Brahman is not some material thing. Brahman is Formless, Ultimate Truth which you are holding, which is within you. There is no Ultimate Truth, except for Formless You. That Conviction is to appear in you. That is the purpose of spirituality.

Yes? Okay! So, Be With You. This is the purpose, this is direct knowledge: there is nothing to be done because you are not a doer, and there is no deed. How were you prior to beingness? Do you know anything about your past birth, or future birth? Nothing! And, in between? No!

In order to know nothing, you are to do something. Do something, to know nothing. And that something, is meditation. You will realize through meditation, that the source of spirituality is in you. The entire source of this world starts from you. Now the ball is in your court. Hmm! How to live, and how to act, is entirely up to you.

122. How do I know if Brahman is absorbed in me?

There are six signs, called “sharguna”. Sharguna meaning six – the six signs, or six symptoms. After absorbing the knowledge, you can look out for the following:

1. Shama means forgiveness. Forgive and forget. I often give the example of Jesus Christ when he was nailed to the cross. At that moment, he said, “Oh God, forgive them, for they know not what they do”. You are to forgive and forget!

2. Dama means tolerance. If anything unpleasant happens to you, you don’t get irritated. You try to understand, and remain peaceful. Suppose, for example, someone shouted at you, or bumped into you, you would not get irritated.

3. And then there is Titiksha which means that you are anxious to know the Reality.

4. Uparati means discarding all the concepts, and worldly attractions. Even if lakhs or crores of dollars are given to you, you will not be interested. You will say, “Why? I don’t want it!” And then, even if a beautiful lady appears in front of you, there will not be any attraction. It happens. Your body-based knowledge, will be totally discarded. You will look at the beautiful lady, and say: “What is that? It is a dead body”.

5. Bhakti means total devotion.

6. Sharda means complete faith.

If there is some irritation, and if you do not have a forgiving nature, or, if there is still some attraction for material powers, this means that something is wrong! The knowledge has not been absorbed within you.

These qualities will appear with meditation. And when they do, you will live life in the world, yet remain untouched by it. You will be in the world, but not of the world.

123. You say, that I am the architect of my life?

Yes, you are the architect of your own life. It is up to you, to accept or refuse, what comes your way. If you don’t want something, don’t take it. If someone wishes to give you something, and you don’t wish to accept it, then, don’t. It is up to you to take what you need, and reject what you don’t need. There are so many thoughts flowing in the mind. Accept the useful thoughts only. That is why I say, that you are the architect of your own life. Everyone tries to impress you with their own concepts. Meditation will teach you, how to act and react. You will be instructed because you are a mastermind!

“You Are the Central Point of the World.” You are not this illusion. The body-form is not your identity. You are nobody, and you are everybody. Your Presence is everywhere, just like the sky is everywhere. The sky that you see here, is the same sky that is everywhere. You are beyond the sky. Have that Conviction! Try to absorb this knowledge. Try to digest this knowledge, which is your Reality, the Listener’s Reality. Reality is not separate from your Identity, therefore, I define it as “Unidentified, Invisible, Anonymous Identity”.

Everything starts from you, and everything ends within you. You are not separate from Ultimate Truth. But because of your conditioning, and the influences you were under, since childhood, you don’t have the courage to dissolve the body-based knowledge. You accept everything, and sign on the dotted line, without even knowing what you are signing: Everywhere, and all the time, you are signing, “Yes! Yes! Yes”. Though you are not guilty, you live with a guilty conscience. You are not guilty. You are not anything at all, because there is no doer, and there is no deed.

124. If we compare a realized person to a non-realized person...?

There is no such thing. There is no difference between a realized person, and a non-realized person. You are formless, like the sky. Is the Indian sky realized, and the American sky not realized? Again, you are using your intellect: “This person is realized, and that person is not realized”. This question comes from considering yourself to be somebody, and taking the world to be true. All these concepts are based on the mistaken notion that “the body is my identity”.

You don’t need to recite the Mantra after Spontaneous Conviction, because you have reached the destination. It is like when you were looking for “Nashik Road Ashram”. When you set out, you asked for directions: “Where is Nashik Road Ashram?” You were looking, and searching. You were asking everybody. Finally, when you arrived at the address, you knew where the ashram was. Likewise, after Conviction, you don’t have to read one more single book. You don’t have to go anywhere, because you have reached your destination.

When you were learning a language, you needed to learn the alphabet and grammar. But once you had acquired these language skills, you no longer needed, to put in any effort to know the alphabet and the grammar. So, after Conviction, you don’t need the “abcd’s”, i.e. the Mantra. Meditation is illusion. There was no meditation prior to beingness, and there will not be any meditation after beingness. You lost your memory; you went missing. So, you needed a process, through which you could identify yourself. Now that you know who you are, the process has become redundant.

125. What do you mean when you say, “the body touch dissolves”?

When we wear clothes, we are not aware that we are wearing them. We don’t really feel them on us, as we go about our daily business. You don’t feel their touch. Similarly, when you know that you are not the body, you are not concerned about it. You feel very light and weightless. There won’t be any type of burden. The body is not a burden to you. You will feel completely free. Meditation dissolves the body sense. It detaches you from the body, so that you do not take its touch.

There is nothing for you to do, except to know that the body is not your identity at all. It is simple. If you try to extract spiritual knowledge, with the strength of body-based knowledge, there will still be duality there. Meditation is essential for seekers of any age, who wish to identify themselves. You have a good background, and spiritual foundation, now all that is needed, is for you to hammer yourself. “You Are to Hammer Yourself.” You are to be totally free from the bondage of the body-form.

That body touch will dissolve with meditation, and you will experience exceptional, internal happiness, and peacefulness. Though you are holding the body, you will remain untouched by it. The body is like an external cloth, and, even though you are holding this external, body cloth, it will not concern you. The body will appear as a kind of subtle, subtle, subtle light. It cannot be described in words, but it is an exceptional experience.

When Bhausaheb Maharaj was in the process of planning and organizing the “Inchegeri Sampradaya Lineage”, he had great foresight. He clearly perceived, that the only way, to combat body-based knowledge, to reach the Ultimate Truth, was for devotees to be immersed in a spiritual atmosphere all the time, at every available moment. To keep them absorbed in the spiritual zone, he prescribed early morning Bhajan, meditation, afternoon Bhajan, and evening Bhajan. This daily schedule kept the devotees’ minds’ busy, while, at the same time, giving them practical knowledge.

While you are attending to your responsibilities, and looking after your body, at the same time, you should be fully involved with Selfless Self, to keep in touch with Selfless Self at all times. This was the idea behind Sri Bhausaheb’s busy, daily programme.

There is no doubt, that Bhausaheb Maharaj knew that the Bhajans and meditation, were all illusion, but, at the same time, absolutely necessary for Conviction, for the Spontaneous Conviction of Your Ultimate Truth, your Ultimate Identity.

The process is very simple, but also very difficult, because you must have strong faith in your Master. There are so many layers upon your Presence, that in order to remove, or burn all these layers, you are to undergo strict meditation, and follow the Master’s every instruction.

126. If this is a dream, can we do anything we want?

This does not mean that there should be total freedom, “Oh, it is all a dream, so I can do whatever I want”. No! Absolutely not! Some limitations are needed, boundaries are essential because anything taken to excess is poisonous. Control yourself! Self-control is most important. After knowing the Reality, you are to exercise self-control. Otherwise, you will say, “My Master has given me total freedom, so that I can do whatever I want”. It should not be like that. This is a reckless attitude that will create further problems.

The human body is very important because through it, you can identify yourself in a real sense. If there is no identification, you will continue seeing dreams – another dream, and another dream, and maybe another dream. How long do you wish to keep seeing dreams for? This is called rebirth, but as you know, “rebirth” is only a concept. This should be the last dream. There should not be any more dreams. You must convince yourself of that. Make this your last dream!

“After Conviction, Be Calm and Quiet, Be Humble, Be Normal, Be Simple.” There is nothing to do. There are no restrictions, no orders, no bondage, or any conditions.

“There is Nothing to Know.” No knowledge is knowledge. Knowledge is also an illusion. Brahman is also illusion, the entire thing is illusion. Try to identify yourself. “You Are Ultimate Truth.” I am saying the same thing, over and over again, to “Impress The Reality on You. You Are Reality. You Are Ultimate Truth.”

127. Why is devotion needed after Realization?

Because there are always external forces around that are ready to disturb you. Also, the mind, the ego and the intellect, may try to distract you from Reality. In spiritual language, this is called maya. [there is no maya] There are so many concepts around. Publicity or fame, money, sex and other desires. After Realization, you still need to remain alert to these dangers, and that is where devotion comes in. If you meditate, recite the Mantra, and remember the words of the Masters, no one will attack you, or be able to distract you from Reality.

128. Nisargadatta Maharaj used to pray after Realization. Why?

Of course! We are also praying. Continuity is required because there are so many concepts pressurizing us without our knowledge. We pray every day. Prayer creates certain vibrations, that keep us in a devotional, humble and elevated state. Continuity is essential, as the human body has so many problems. There is no harm.

5 EXHORTATIONS AND WARNINGS

“I am giving you a hundred percent guarantee! No one is willing to give you a guarantee, but I am – a hundred percent! All you are to do is sacrifice, and devote some time for you. And then you will see the results. I am not performing any miracles. The miracles happen within you. But you are to be very serious regarding meditation.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

129. Be brave, and live like a lion!

Be brave! Live like a lion! Don’t be a coward, always anxious, “Oh dear! What’s going to happen?” Nothing has happened, at all. There is no deed, and there is no doer. But we are always under the pressure of fear, and therefore, lacking in courage. Be humble! Be normal! There is no great or small, and no good or bad. Don’t make comparisons such as: “oh, this is a good man, and that is a bad man”. Nothing is good, and nothing is bad. These are your own concepts.

It is the purpose of spirituality, to transform you from a beggar into a multi-millionaire! “You Are Not a Beggar.” But you are acting like one, when you say, “Oh, do something, give me what I need. Bless me, bless me”. Why? You are not a beggar! “You Are a Multi-Millionaire!” There is absolutely nothing to fear. “You Are the Father of This World, the Mother of This World” – one and the same! This is not an egoistic statement. “You Are Final Truth. You Are Ultimate Truth. There is Nothing Except for Selfless Self.”

130. You must have the courage to accept the Reality

Courage is needed to accept Reality, and, that is what we seem to lack. That courage, power and energy will come with meditation. Meditation means hammering yourself at all times: “You Are Brahman, You Are Atman, You Are Paramatman”. This appears as duality, but out of that duality, your individuality disappears. In the beginning, you say, “When I am sitting in meditation”, or, “I am somebody who is meditating”. This is duality. But we need to take the help of this illusion, to remove another illusion.

All your concepts and fears need to dissolve. The fire is there, but it is covered with ash. Through the meditation, you are removing the ash, removing all the body-based concepts. Then you will be strong and courageous.

It is not difficult or impossible! Don’t stress yourself, or struggle with anything. Go deep, and deep and deep, within your Selfless Self. Then forget all about this world. There should not be any concepts left: No “I am”, no “you are”, “There is Nothing There.” There is no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman. All concepts! Discard them all!

“God” is also a concept. It is a fact because we have given birth to God. This is not an intellectual statement. It is the truth. But to accept this truth with Conviction, we need to meditate. It may feel like a monotonous practice in the beginning: “Oh not meditation again!” But there is no other way. You have to devote some time for yourself, because you are travelling around this unbalanced, illusory world.

We don’t expect there to be another illusory world after this one. This is the Final, Final Dance! This is the Ultimate Truth. Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. Playing with spiritual words, and literal knowledge, is meaningless. You are to go deep within. Go deep, and deep, within you. And then, your so-called existence will disappear. There won’t be any experience, experiencer, or witness. You will be completely aloof from the world, and then your attachment to the body-form will loosen, and gradually lessen, more and more.

Though you will continue to use the body for your work, and for performing some duties, you will not be touched by body-based knowledge. The mind, the ego, and the intellect may be there, but you will use them sparingly, as and when, required. Then, you will forget about them.

In this way, there will be no confusion or temptation. After knowing the Reality, you will not feel drawn to go anywhere. If an attraction arises, this means that you do not know your own importance. You still do not know yourself. You have tremendous power, and great importance. Don’t underestimate yourself. Don’t measure yourself in the body-form. You are beyond that! “You Are The Terminus.”

131. Spirituality gives you courage

The importance of spirituality, is that it gives you the courage to face life’s many challenges. They may only be spiritual words, but nevertheless, they will give you the courage to live a happy life.

Nisargadatta Maharaj became a disciple of Sidharameshwar Maharaj. Some time later, his problems began! He felt the need to absorb himself in spirituality full-time, to experience and absorb the teachings, and to gain practical knowledge. So, spontaneously, he abandoned everything, left home, and headed for the Himalayas.

When he returned, his business had all but collapsed. One shop out of ten remained! Then his mother died, followed by his daughter, his father, and his wife. He had to face so many calamities! But, in spite of all these devastating blows, he did not abandon his spirituality. He found the courage, to confront these extremely difficult circumstances.

Spiritual knowledge teaches you how to live successfully, and peacefully, in spite of so many challenges, difficulties and depression. That is the purpose behind it. You have the power to overcome all the difficulties that come your way. Use that power! Understanding and Conviction are most important. They will come from meditation and knowledge.

It is a fact that this world is an illusory world. There is no “I”, “you”, “he”, “she”, “it” – there’s nothing. There is no Master, there is no disciple, there is no God, there is no seeker or devotee. This is fact! But, there will be concepts around, for as long as we are holding the body. When the body disappears, there will not be any concepts. Nothing will remain. Who is God? What is God? What is Brahman? What is Atman, Paramatman, Master? Everything came out of nothing, and everything will dissolve within nothing. It is a fact!

Accept your Reality! Spirituality teaches you how to stand on your own feet. It gives you the strength to be independent. Don’t depend on anyone, including the Masters. Encourage your Own Master! Approach your Own Master. Your Master is a Powerful Master. Outgrow your old habits, “Please help me, and give me this, and give me that! Bless me! Give me your blessing”, etc. Why are you asking someone to bless you? “Put your hand on your head, and bless yourself.”

132. You say we need courage, but I don’t feel that I am a very courageous person…

You need courage because you consider yourself to be the body-form. It is spontaneous courage. Even when difficulties appear, you will not be disturbed or depressed. If some unpleasant incidents happen in your life, you will find the courage to deal with them. You will find the strength, to stay aloof from any problems, that come your way. In the past, if there was an upset, we responded with fear and depression. We were disturbed. But after Conviction, there will not be any fear or disturbance when unpleasant incidents occur because you will be as solid as a rock, established in Ultimate Reality, and therefore, invincible.

If something happens, let it happen! Whatever calamities may come your way, spontaneous courage will arise from within you, so that you float through these particular challenges. Your attitude should be like this: “Bring it on! Let whatever is going to happen, happen. It is not my concern”. If you face the difficulties head-on, the black clouds will disperse quickly. If you are fearful, they will gather momentum.

The clouds are coming, and the clouds are going. But you are not coming and going. “You Are There, And There Only.” After concentrated meditation, you will feel some spontaneous changes happening within you. Slowly, silently, and permanently, all your body-based concepts are dissolving.

Forget about all that is happening in the world! Just forget it! You are not the body, and you have nothing to do with the world. You are formless!

Yesterday, I told this lady who was visiting the ashram, about a young boy who used to come here. He was very innocent. He did not know the “a,b,c’s” of philosophy or spirituality, but then a miracle happened.

He had taken the Mantra. When he sat down for meditation, he immediately fell into a trance, forgetting everything. Then, one day, while he was putting some towels away in a cupboard, he fell from the third floor. Luckily, his fall was cushioned to some extent, by a small bush on which he landed. He attributed this to the miracle of the Naam Mantra!

The specialist doctor, gave him a life expectancy of no more than twenty-odd years. Wrong! He is now married, has a child, and is working as a ward porter, at the hospital where he was treated. He was supposed to receive blood transfusions every three or four months. That stopped, along with all his medication. And so, though he fell from the third floor, nothing really happened! It is a fact! When he was admitted to the hospital, he thought he was going to die! “Oh! A miracle happened”, he said. “My Master saved me!”

This kind of thing happens. Miracles are not Ultimate Truth, but, nevertheless, you have tremendous power. When you become One With You, anything can happen.

I will tell you about an American named “Whittaker” He was a mountaineer. He was not involved in spirituality. Here, I am talking about the power, the spiritual power, that inbuilt power in us all. After a car accident, they had to cut his right leg off, from here, [Maharaj points to his lower legs] In spite of this huge handicap, he wanted to climb Mount Everest. He failed on his first two attempts. But in spite of this, he did not give up. He attempted the climb again, wearing an artificial limb. He almost reached the peak, but then, the screws loosened, and his artificial limb fell off.

In spite of that, with inbuilt courage, he reached the mountain peak. This is a fact! How did it happen? It was a miracle. This story of unimaginable determination, and strength and courage, demonstrates that we all have immense power, miraculous power. I am encouraging that power, through which you can identify yourself. You are still doubtful, unbelieving, saying, “No! How can this be possible?” It is possible, and it can happen. It can happen to you. This kind of remarkable phenomenon cannot be grasped by the intellect. Something happened that is beyond the intellect, and beyond our imagination.

You will have the strength, courage and determination to face anything. Courage is inbuilt in you. It is spontaneous courage. This knowledge is priceless. But you must give of your time, that is all. Sit down for meditation, and recite the Mantra. Here there are no spiritual rules and restrictions, regarding your diet or daily actions. Yesterday, one boy asked a question about food: “I eat fish and mutton. Is that okay?” There is no problem. The body is a food-body, so give it what it needs, in moderation.

Another time, a middle-age man came to me, saying, “Every day, I drink beer, can I still take the Naam Mantra?” It is not a problem. You can drink beer, you can consume what your body requires, but never take anything to excess. What I want to say, is that diet and food etc, is not the concern of spirituality. Concentrate on remaining detached from body-based knowledge, and staying aloof, and untouched by body-based concepts. That is the concern of spirituality, and should be your one and only concern. Don’t mix food-body issues with spirituality. They are unrelated! Okay?

133. “Bless me! Bless me! I need a blessing!” Why are you begging?

Don’t expect anything from anyone: “Oh! Please do something for me”. “You Can Stand On Your Own Feet.” Don’t depend on anyone. Bow down to you, mmh! That is Reality. How can you bow to yourself? By taking what is given to you. By accepting that you are the Source, the only Source. By accepting that you are All! Value your invaluable Presence. Respect yourself, and respect everyone! I am not saying that you are not to respect the saintly people, the Masters, mothers, etc. You can respect them all, but, at the same time, you must try to identify yourself.

The Holder of the body is Ultimate Truth. Don’t allow the growth of any sense of ego, because human beings have a subtle, subtle ego. If something happens, that goes against your mind, you get annoyed. There should not be any annoyance in you.

A well-known example of how we ignore our power, and underestimate ourselves, is portrayed in the popular story of the “Beggar Boy”. A boy is living on the street as a beggar. Then, one day a man approaches him, saying: “Why are you begging? Your parents left you a lot of money”. The boy responds: “You are making fun of me”. “No I am not”, replies the man. To prove to the boy that he is in fact rich, he takes him to the bank, where he shows him all the documents to verify his status. Seeing the evidence in front of him, with his own eyes gives him the conviction: “Wow! I am not a beggar after all. I am a multimillionaire”. He was under the illusion that he was a beggar, but when he was given the knowledge, his ignorance dissolved.

He was already a multimillionaire when he was begging, but he did not know the facts, and, therefore, he was begging. It is the very same thing with us. We are begging, “Oh God, bless me”. Don’t beg! You are not a beggar, but a multimillionaire.

Why are you begging for blessings from somebody? Give yourself your own blessings. Bless yourself! I am trying to convince the devotees in this way. Devotees also ask how they can realize – when they are already realized – but, put simply, they do not know that they are. “How will I realize?” You are realized! That Realization is unknown to you. Here, you are not learning anything new, we are just refreshing your memory, and removing some unwanted things that don’t belong to you. It is a process of subtraction, not addition. You must have strong faith during this process. The bottom line is that you are a Master. You need a physical Master to assist you with identifying yourself. “Identify the Hidden Master Within You.”

You receive Diksha (initiation), to convince the Invisible Listener That, “Except Your Selfless Self There is Nothing”. You have to be sincere, and always recite the Mantra. Remember the Master’s words, and meditate. One way, or another. you will Self-Realize: “Oh! I am finding so much. What am I finding? I am finding the Finder! Aha! The Finder is itself Ultimate Truth! I am Ultimate Truth”. That Spontaneous Realization will appear within you. This is not an egoistic statement.

Exceptional happiness, without any material cause, will come with that Realization. You were looking for happiness from material sources. You were looking for fame, money and sex. These are not needed to make you happy. Nothing is needed because the happiness that will arise is spontaneous happiness, causeless happiness.

134. Why do we search for a Master?

Because you do not know your direction Home. You do not know the address, or how to get there. The Master knows all the details, because he was once a disciple, too.

When you are in the Presence of the Master, don’t analyze the words. Instead, try and identify what they are saying, what they wish to convey. Be selective! Be careful which Master you decide to settle with, as the Master who has uncovered his Perfect and Exceptional Identity, is a very rare Master indeed. Many Masters just pile heaps of knowledge onto the seekers. They are not able to take seekers beyond knowledge, because they have not gone beyond knowledge themselves. The Master who shows you God in you, is as rare as a flower in the desert.

There are many so-called Masters, who talk about the kundalini and the chakras. It is all meaningless. There is no kundalini. There are no chakras. This illusory circle of kundalinis and chakras is a vicious circle. Don’t enter it! [Maharaj chuckles]

All the secret assets, invisible assets, the invisible property, the entire assets, everything is within you. So, why go elsewhere, to find your innate and rightful property? This is the principle of spirituality.

With the help of the Master, you can identify yourself, and finally know who you are. After identifying that Master within you, you can attend to your duties, work or career smoothly, and without any difficulty. By this time, you will be able to do anything, because your foundations will be solid. You will have exceptional peacefulness, and exceptional happiness within you. Happiness and peacefulness are not separate from you. You Are That!

135. Why do we need to listen to a Master?

Why do the Masters talk? Because you are not able to hear your own, Inner Master talking to you. The Master is trying to invite the attention of the Invisible Listener, that, “You Are Brahman”. What is here? [Maharaj points to his body] It is the same thing. The Presence within this body, and the Presence within your body is one and the same. This Reality is to be established.

Have respect for your Master. Why? It is only because of your Master, that you know your true identity. If it were not for your Master, you would still be lost in the world, identifying with the body-form. The Master and the disciple do not have separate identities. After Conviction, there will be eternal happiness. It cannot be described in words. There will be exceptional peacefulness. Even if, say, violence erupted all around you, inside of you, there will still be total and complete silence.

Though we may have theoretical knowledge, we have still not met ourselves in a real sense. For that, you need regular meditation, sincere meditation. Beyond that, there is nothing.

This knowledge is the rarest of knowledge. It is priceless knowledge. But because it is free, it is seldom valued. At first, when visitors come to the ashram, they are very interested. However, their enthusiasm does not last. They get distracted, lose interest, and then decide: “No, no, this is not it”. They listen to the mind, and reject Reality. Concentrate sincerely! This is an opportunity. To avoid the next concept of birth and death, you have to try and identify yourself today, not tomorrow. “Every Moment is Valuable For You.” Give prime importance to your Selfless Self.

Some visitors who may have developed a physical problem and are feeling somewhat helpless, go to see a Master. They will say: “bless me, bless me, bless me, do something, please, do something to help me”. This will not help you. The Master is not here to solve your physical problems.

After Conviction, if something goes wrong with your body, you will have the courage to face that problem. There will be a complete change of perspective. The human body is very unstable. Anything can happen to it, at any time. There may be sickness, depression, impediments, or all sorts of difficult circumstances there, but, you will always be firm, because you are established in Ultimate Truth.

We all feel handicapped to some extent, as if we are incomplete, not whole, lacking. So, we look to others for help: “Do something, do something”. We are desperately running, here and there. With strong devotion, you will never have to go running to anyone else again, because the cure is within you. You can cure anything. It happens.

No one is performing any miracles. When a Master says: “Oh, I will do a miracle for you. When I put my hand on your head, I will transfer some power”. This is a story. It is meaningless. Don’t believe it! No one can give you any power.

136. How can anyone transfer power to you?

You already have power, exceptional power. Don’t neglect your own power. No one can transfer power to you because all the Power is with you, and in you. “You Are the Principle of This World. The Entire World is Projected Out of Your Invisible Presence.” That Invisible Master, that Invisible Power or Energy, is already within you. You are the backbone, the foundation of Reality.

137. Why go here and there?

I am not restricting your movements, however, after reaching the destination, don’t go looking elsewhere in search of something. Don’t go with the intention of finding something, like: “If I go to that Master, or that place, I will get some kind of realization”. You will not get anything. You will be misguided, misguided, misguided, because there is no Brahman that is separate from you. There is no Brahman apart from you. So, why go after unnecessary distractions, when you are Reality. “Be With You All The Time.” Don’t mix with the wrong company, and get entangled in body-based, and commercial knowledge. There are so many spiritual shops these days, selling commercial spirituality. Spirituality has become a business, unfortunately. I am not criticizing it, just pointing out a fact. Don’t be attracted to that spiritual business.

Here, the Masters are not withholding any secrets. We are placing before you, your Ultimate Truth, the whole truth! There is no more. So that, if you go elsewhere seeking something else, all you will find is illusory, body-based knowledge. And, you will be back on the hamster wheel once more!

We are pointing out, to the Invisible Listener within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. There are no miracles. There is nothing else. No miracles, nothing is there. Be strong! Tap into your power. “Encourage Your Power. Entice Your Power. Use Your Power.” Avoid going to other teachers, or Masters who say: “Oh, yes, Brahman! I have Brahman knowledge. I will show it to you”. Nobody can show you Brahman. It cannot be shown.

How do you show the sky to anyone in India? How do you show anyone the American sky? No one can! This kind of talk is nonsense, misleading. It is a misrepresentation. The sky is everywhere. Brahman is the name given to that principle that is everywhere, in every being -not only in humans, but in every being. This world is full of Presence, full of Brahman, but we do not know that Reality. Therefore, we meditate to know the Reality.

Some visitors tell me that they have been at a certain ashram for years, sitting crossed-legged in meditation, and fasting for long periods of time. Don’t waste your life unnecessarily. Do your job, do your duties, but don’t sit with your legs crossed 24/7!

I always tell those who come to me for guidance about their marriage and family life, the same thing: “Marry, and have a family, if you wish. There is no problem”. Some of them say, “Oh, I am a spiritual person, how can I get married?” Of course you can marry! There is no problem! The body is a food-body with bodily needs. It has bodily requirements. These kind of thoughts are arising and flowing, but you are trying to restrict them. And because you are trying to suppress them, they blow up again, and explode with double the force. Don’t accept these impressions and concepts, but at the same time, be your own judge. Be normal, and be humble!

In brief, “Except For Your Selfless Self There is No God, No Brahman, No Atman, No Paramatman, No Master”. It is very simple. Reality is placed before you. You may accept it, or you may reject it. It is up to you. Listen to me! “This Is the Final Truth, the Final Ultimate Truth.” There is nothing beyond, and there is nowhere else to go.

You may visit any place you wish, but not for spiritual knowledge. Spiritual knowledge is always within you. Don’t underestimate yourself. You do not know your own greatness. Greatness is always with you. We have created language. We use it to convince you of your True Identity. Ignore the language because it is of secondary importance. Try to identify, and understand what the Master is conveying, the meaning behind the words. Instead of analyzing the words, try to understand what the Master is conveying.

138. Why are we running after a mirage of spirituality?

Because we are deceiving ourselves that it can give us something. Spirituality is a mirage, an illusion. There is nothing there. Everything is within you, but you are not identifying yourself. You don’t know yourself. This is the basic idea. To identify yourself, we are presenting you with Reality, your Reality, not the Reality of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. These words indicate, that except your Selfless Self, there is nothing. Everyone is struggling to reach that Conviction. Every being is struggling. Even though we know that we are Ultimate Truth in the literal sense, happiness is still not there, and peace is not to be found.

139. What does spirituality mean? Touching the Master’s feet, clapping, garlands?

This is not spirituality. When I was a boy, my Master, Nisargadatta Maharaj, said, “Earn lakhs of rupees, and then throw them away! Stand on your own feet. Educate yourself. Don’t come to me. Lead a practical life”. He asked me: “Why aren’t you in college? Enrol at the college! Don’t come to me! If you have any spare time, then you can come! You are welcome”.

Don’t leave your job, and don’t abandon your duties. You are a doctor, so you must pay attention to your patients. And after that, come to me during your free time. What is spirituality? It just means, “To Identify Yourself In A Real Sense”.

140. We are not doing any miracles

All sorts of spiritual books are out there. The principle behind them is to identify oneself in a real sense. See, we are not doing any miracles. There are some concepts around, whereby people say, “after going to see Maharaj, after going to the Master, a miracle will happen. My family life and my personal life will improve”. I tell them that I am not performing any miracles. I am placing before them their Identity. We are asking you, to discard all the concepts, that have been engraved in you, from childhood till today. These concepts, like birth and death, future and past and present, last birth, future birth, all of them are to be discarded because you are unborn. There is no birth and death. You are Ultimate Truth.

141. Why does Nisargadatta, say this, and Ramana Maharshi, say that?

You must have read so many books by Ramana Maharshi, Nisargadatta Maharaj, Krishnamurti and others. Don’t analyze their words. It is the nature of the mind, to analyze and dissect everything, and make comparisons. “Why did Nisargadatta, say this, and Ramana Maharshi, say that?” We are analyzing their words, and their statements, all the time, and missing the most important thing, which is grasping [apperceiving] what they are trying to convey.

All the authentic Masters are right. Everything that they say is correct. They are all communicating “Perfection”. But what do we do? Immediately, we start analyzing their words, and complain that one Master’s statement, contradicts another Master’s statement. That analysis should not take place. All the Masters wish to convey is one principle, the same principle, and that is: “Except your Selfless Self there is no God, no Brahman”. You are to accept this conclusion. Don’t analyze it. This is not a debating society!

142. “Oh, I am a spiritual man, how can I spend time with my wife, my father, my parents?”

This kind of talk is nonsense talk! Our spirituality is practical spirituality. Do your duties, whatever they may be. Be normal! You have family responsibilities. Look after your loved ones! Visit your parents. Family life has nothing to do with spiritual life, but at the same time, you are to be humble, normal and practical.

If you are hungry, you need to eat something. You can’t avoid it by saying, “Oh! I am a spiritual man, I cannot eat”. That is theoretical nonsense, and illusory talk! Be practical! Ask yourself, “What exactly do I want?” The answer is, “I want to identify myself”. It is a fact that the body is not your identity at all, so you need to discover, and find out what your identity is. Remove all the layers that are stopping you from knowing yourself.

143. What is the use of this knowledge?

What is the use of this knowledge? Suppose you were to read thousands of books. This activity may well make you a Master of words, of spiritual words, but it will not make you a Master of your Selfless Self. You are to be a Master of your Selfless Self, in this way: “I am not a man, or a woman, I am totally formless. Since I am formless, there is no death and birth, no future, no past, no destiny”. It is a fact. “Your Presence is Just Like the Space, or the Sky.” The sky does not know anything. Likewise, “Your Invisible Presence is Just Like the Sky or Space”.

Dissolve all your concepts! This is the principle of spirituality. Be firm! Visit Yourself! Don’t keep travelling, and going here, today and there, tomorrow, looking for knowledge. By all means, visit different places, but without the expectation, of finding happiness or peace. You won’t find happiness anywhere else, except within you. Happiness and peace are already within you, but you are unaware. We have become victims of our mind, ego and intellect. Use them appropriately, but don’t become their victim.

144. Some people want to become sannyasins

What is a sannyasin? It is someone dressed in colourful robes, wearing lots of necklaces, and neglecting his responsibilities. This is not a sannyasin. Throw out all your concepts! Instead of decorating the body, decorate your Inner Master. Try to find your Real Self. It is not difficult at all. But, we are not giving ourselves enough attention. This is the problem. We still have some mind, ego and intellect influencing us. The mind is very tricky, manufacturing so many thoughts.

Stop swimming with the thoughts, and going along with them indiscriminately. Okay, having thoughts is the nature of the body because the body belongs to the five elements, but your Identity is an Exceptional Identity, through which the entire world is projected. It is not limited to the body.

Taking on a new identity, any new identity, whether it is a new spiritual name, or becoming a sannyasin is meaningless. Find your true identity! We are trying to remove the layers of clothing, not put new ones on! Try to identify yourself in a real sense.

145. Is your Master realized, or not?

People often ask the question, “Is your Master realized or not?” What concern is it of yours? The mind asks unnecessary questions. Instead, find out whether you are realized or not, and how to realize. Instead of talking about others, talk about your Selfless Self.

Try to identify yourself, and see whether you are realized, or not. Ask the question, “Am I realized, or not?” Presence has no duality. Presence is everywhere. Sky is sky. Teach yourself, and then become your own Master.

Instead of wasting your time trying to find out if so and so, is, or is not, realized, make yourself powerful and indomitable! Find the answers from within. Let the answers reveal themselves to you. You are perfect. You are the central point of this world. Don’t ignore that. I am placing before you the facts.

146. Reading books and dry discussion will not serve your purpose

When you read various spiritual books, and approach the Masters, or travel to various sacred places, all these activities are meaningless, unless they lead to identification. These are physical activities, and, therefore, will not help you. “Try to Identify the Invisible Listener Within You.” The Invisible Listener in You is your Reality. This is what I call the principle of spirituality. You do not know yourself.

Approach your Selfless Self. The Master, Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, etc, are not separate from you. Because you are measuring yourself as the body-form, you are under the false impression, that Reality is to be found outside of you. It is only within you. Meditation alone, will enable you to identify yourself in a real sense. Reading books, and dry, spiritual discussions, are all unnecessary exercises. It is more important to find out, who is reading the books? And, who is discussing spirituality?

What is the use of all these books? “Have You Ever Read the Invisible Reader Within You?” Mmh? You are travelling all over the place, looking for answers, and hoping to find them, from various teachers and Masters. Question yourself! The answers are within you! It is only you, and you alone, who can answer your questions because the Invisible Questioner is the Answer.

There must be a conclusion! Don’t just keep reading, reading, reading ad infinitum. Reading books in this way is nothing but an intellectual exercise. Spiritual books are only indicators. They point to your Ultimate Reality, your Ultimate Truth, but they are not your Ultimate Reality, your Ultimate Truth. Ultimate Truth is not to be found in books, or Masters, or in sacred sites. Why? Because “You Are Ultimate Truth.”

What have you achieved from all your reading? You must know, otherwise, it has all been a waste of time, a meaningless exercise. Question yourself: “Where do I stand?” “What is my position?” When you read books, and listen to various Masters, what you are doing is accepting second-hand knowledge, someone else’s concepts. This will not help you. It will not serve your purpose. It will not lead you to Self-Identification. Question yourself! Self-enquiry leads to Self-Knowledge, and Self-Knowledge leads to Self-Realization. You must know yourself directly – not through words.

Ask yourself: “What exactly do I want?” You are no different from anyone else. The human body-form looks for a peaceful, happy, fearless and stress-free life.

We all carry with us a fear of death because we identify with the body. When we come to know that we are not the body, that fear simply dissolves, along with all the other concepts.

Carry out an investigation! Find out what is the value of the body? Does it have any value? Try to find the “Holder” of this body, the Power, the Life Force that sustains the body. Without Presence, your body is a dead body! Identify yourself! Read the Reader! You must find out “Who am I?”, by diving deep within your Selfless Self, through meditation. The principle of spirituality states: “Except Your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, No Master”, because You Are A Master, You Are Paramatman, You Are God Almighty!

The purpose of spirituality is to help you identify yourself in a real sense. You are identifying everybody, and everything, in the world, except your Selfless Self. Identify your Selfless Self! Because the body is not your identity, and was not your identity, and will not remain your identity, therefore, whatever is accepted through the medium of the body, is illusion. Please try to know yourself. Try to identify yourself. That is the base, your foundation, which can only be established with meditation. Meditation is the medium through which you can identify yourself.

147. What is the point of counting beads?

Counting beads is meaningless! Reciting “Ram, Ram, Ram”, or “Hanuman, Jai Hanuman”, “Jai Ram, Jai Ram”, is a waste of time. Prior to beingness, do you think there was any “Jai Ram, Jai Ram, Jai Ram chants”? The Spirit is tempted to count the beads and chant, “Ram Ram, Ram”, but “I Am Inviting the Attention of That Spirit Within You That is Itself Ram!” Ram is not separate from you. When you use these beads, you are not doing anything but exercising your fingers!

Religion teaches that Brahma, the Creator God, gave birth. Then, Vishnu came as the Protector, to supply food, and take care of the bodies. And then, Shiva came along as the Destroyer. So, we have the God of death, the Shiva-God, the caretaker, Vishnu, and the birth-giving Brahma. The important question here is: “Who gave birth to Brahma? Who is Brahma’s Father? Vishnu is taking care of you, but who is taking care of Vishnu? And then, what happens to the “God of death, Shiva? Who takes his soul, when his time ends after death?

These are the concepts developed by religion. It is a purely imaginary story. In a similar way, we develop imaginary concepts that influence, and pressure us. You are to discard all these concepts. There is no reasoning or logic to all these stories, rituals, pastimes. “Ram Ram, Vishnu, Vishnu”, etc, all these are concepts – a total waste of time. Find out where you stand. Reach a conclusion, and bring an end to your drifting.

148. Nisargadatta Maharaj said, “Don’t mix with such elements which will distract you from Reality”. What did he mean?

Nisargadatta Maharaj was referring to keeping bad company. If you mix with the wrong sort, there will be confusion. I have told you that you are Ultimate Truth. Then, after leaving here, you meet other teachers, or Masters or seekers, who say, “No no, you are not Ultimate Truth. Brahman is separate from you”. They are trying to confuse you.

You need to convince yourself, and be convinced by your Master: “Yes! My Master says that I am Brahman, therefore I am Brahman! I am Ultimate Truth!” There is nothing more. If you listen to anyone else, everything will be undone, and you will enter once more, into the confusion field.

You must have strong willpower, and a sacrificing nature, so that you will resolutely accept: “Yes, my Master says I am Brahman, I am Brahman”. It is your Unidentified Invisible Anonymous Identity. Simple! Prior to beingness, did you know anything? Nothing! When you leave the body, will you know anything? Nothing! What is the purpose, and use of all this knowledge?

Think seriously, even intellectually, and try to convince yourself. Your Self-Conviction is most important. The Master has given you various clues. You are to accept what He says. You are to think seriously. It is a fact that you are not the body. It is a fact.

“Don’t be distracted by the elements” means don’t accept the illusory thoughts that are flowing, inside and outside. Be there, and there only.

You have been told the Truth. “You are Brahman, Ultimate Truth, You are Brahman, Ultimate Truth”. You have seen the Ultimate Truth, you have recognized the Ultimate Truth: “Except for Selfless Self there is no Brahman, no God, nothing! What more do you want?

Whether the body-identity is there or not, “You Are There, And There Only”. Prior to this bodily identification, nothing was known. The unknown only becomes known through the body. The unknown disappears along with the body. And, the body is not your identity.

A small child becomes a young man, then an old man. And one day, he is destined to leave the body. Therefore, the body is not your permanent identity. There is no death, no birth. You are unborn. The building may collapse, but the sky remains. You are subtler than the sky or space. So, have the courage to accept your Identity, your Reality. If you have strong courage to accept the Reality, nothing will disturb you.

Sometimes, friends try to put people off from listening to the Master. Ignore them! Don’t listen to them. Don’t give any cognizance to such types of atmosphere. Forget it! Forget and forgive, just like Jesus says, “Oh God, forgive them, for they know not what they do”.

Any doubts? There should not be any doubts because all the doubts, and all the questions, are related to body-based-knowledge. It is a very simple thing, an open fact that: “The Body is Not Your Identity. The Body was Not Your Identity. The Body is Not Going to Remain Your Identity”. So, all this knowledge of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, maya, and all these concepts, have created a background, but you are totally separate from all that. “The Presence Within This Body is Subtler Than Space or Sky.” But because that “Presence Touched with the Body”, you started saying “I”. That form is taking place. Prior to the touch with the body, there was no form. Basically, “Prior to Beingness, You Are Totally Formless.” It is an open fact, even if you think about it intellectually. After leaving this body, you will be formless.

When you are formless, there is no thinking, and no thoughts. There is no knowledge, no words like Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. All these man-made words came along with the body only. There is no desire, there are no demands, there is no anything! “There was Nothing Prior to Beingness. Nothing was There!” Everything came along with the body. All your desires, needs, requirements, happiness, peacefulness, etc, all these words came along with the body.

All these concepts did not exist prior to beingness. Even that “I” concept was not there. After leaving the body, that “I” concept will dissolve. All your precious knowledge will disappear, along with the body.

Where is the question of death and birth? Where is the question of rebirth? These questions are there because we have been brought up with various concepts, and are influenced by them. Come out of this circle of concepts! Discard everything, and don’t be distracted again!

6 TROUBLESHOOTING

“Behind painfulness, there is blissfulness. Behind the dark, there is light. You are always thinking about darkness. Why don’t you think about brightness? It is very interesting, if you go deep and deep, you will find exceptional happiness, “Oh! It is spiritual intoxication”. It is just spontaneous happiness. You can enjoy it! ‘My Master says I am Brahman, therefore, I am Brahman!’ Accept it! There is nothing else. Grow in confidence! Let things unfold! Let the calamities happen!”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

149. I don’t understand the second part of the Mantra. Are the syllables of the second part, the reverse of the first part?

Yes, correct. It is: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. “I am Brahman”, and the reverse, “Brahman I am”. It is very easy, very simple. Both parts are influencing the Invisible Listener, the Meditator within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. But don’t analyze the Mantra. Don’t apply the so-called intellect to the practice. Just do it very easily, and simply. Be simple, be normal, and be humble!

150. When I recite the Mantra, my mind is always trying to hold onto something

If you find it difficult to concentrate, then you can picture the form of the Master. This may help you to focus better and recite the Mantra. Don’t try too hard! Don’t put in so much effort! Keep the use of the intellect, the mind and the ego to a minimum.

The Spirit is sensitive, and it will absorb what is impressed upon it, with great ease. You can identify yourself through the Naam Mantra. We are identifying ourselves in the human form, when basically, you are formless. There is no form, and therefore, no death, or birth. Just recite the Mantra, and after a while, you will feel the effects, some vibrations. After continuous recitation of the Mantra, after concentrating on the Invisible Concentrator, your existing appearance will disappear. Reality will open up within you.

151. I already have a mantra. If I take your Mantra, does this mean that, I am starting all over again from the beginning?

If you wish to change your mantra, then there is no problem. Om Namah Shivaya, or other mantras are not wasted. Through that knowledge, through that sacrifice or devotion, you came to me. So, it is not wasted. You are not starting all over again.

Nowadays, direct knowledge is quite rare. Teachers will take you round and round in circles. This a direct approach, without any expectation. I am not expecting anything from anyone else. Be realized, and make others realized. Be enlightened, make others enlightened. This is straight knowledge.

Normally, in our lineage, we do not give the Naam Mantra immediately. But I am very liberal. Some of you have travelled long distances to be here, so, with sympathy, I am trying to give the Naam Mantra. But I have found, that many people who come here, then go elsewhere, to see another Master, and to possibly receive another mantra. They are spoiling their spiritual career.

152. In the first two or three months, after receiving the Mantra, I couldn’t concentrate on the meditation, there was a lot of confusion and depression

In the beginning, the mind will rebel against you. There will be some laziness, depression, or nervousness. But don’t abandon the meditation because of all this. It is actually a good sign. It means that the meditation is working. The medicine that has been given to you is having an effect. Those things that are not needed or wanted, are beginning to leave, just like when you get rid of the tenants from your house, when you no longer want them there. As they are leaving the house, they may hurl abuse in your direction, because they have been long-standing tenants. They are attached to their homes, and don’t wish to leave.

In a similar way, there are so many wrong, and illusory concepts in the body, that, they will rebel against you, as they depart! The mind used to control you. Soon, you will be a Master of the mind! Follow the meditation. It is very simple. You are to devote some time for yourself. In the beginning, we ask for one, two, or three hours. The more you do, the greater the benefits. And then, after some time, it will be spontaneous meditation. Even when you are in deep sleep, the meditation will continue.

This body is called a “man”. I am not thinking, “I am a man, I am a man, I am a man”. This body has been given some name, “Ramakant”. In deep sleep, I don’t keep thinking, “Oh, I am Ramakant”. The point is that, that word, “Ramakant” is very, very close, and has become one with this body. Similarly, the word, “Brahman” is supposed to resonate very close, with your Selfless Self. When that Oneness occurs, you will forget everything. Keep reciting the Naam Mantra until this happens.

The Naam Mantra is to be repeated, until you reach the level of Spontaneous Conviction, “I am Brahman”. I will say this again, Naam Mantra meditation is necessary till the Spontaneous Conviction arises that, “I am Brahman”, without any experience. At this time, you will find that even “I am Brahman” is also a concept. This is direct knowledge. It has become complicated by layers. This is a direct approach. Therefore, the summation of spirituality is: except your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master. You are to accept That Reality, that Ultimate Truth. Keep hammering with the Naam Mantra, “I am Brahman. Brahman I am”. Keep impressing! Keep hammering! “Yes! I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. And see the humorous side of it all! That Reality will open within you. Enjoy!

153. I took the Mantra, and it has no effect

It is not like that! Suppose you were watering a row of plants. You pour water at the side of the plants. It absorbs the water and begins to flow towards the rest. The water does not flow immediately. With the Mantra, it is the same. You cannot expect instant results. It all depends on your involvement, and how serious you are taking it all. Don’t take it casually. The Mantra will remove all the layers that have appeared upon your Presence. There are so many layers there, that they are not all visible. They are not so easy to detect.

It is a little like a fire that is covered with ashes. After removing these ashes, you will see that there is a fire burning underneath. Your energy, your fire, is covered with so many concepts. The Mantra works to clean, and remove these concepts. The Mantra will purify everything. It has tremendous power! The role of the Mantra is to remove all these things. It is like a spiritual broom. It is like a spiritual duster that makes everything vanish. But you must have some patience. Don’t consider yourself as handicapped in any way, and doubting whether anything will happen. Remember that nothing is impossible!

The human body is not your identity at all. Accept that reality, your reality! It is a fact. You are not accepting it because of the impressions from body-based knowledge. Dissolve those impressions!

154. That Conviction is not happening to me

That Spontaneous Conviction is within you. The Conviction is already there, but “You are missing”! You are already there, but you do not know that you are. There is already Enlightenment. There is already Realization, but you do not know, because you are layered with so many concepts. You have become a victim of so many body-based concepts.

155. I face so many difficulties, how can I concentrate, and just be the witness?

Everyone has some degree of tension, even small children. Problems are bound to be there because you are holding the body. Meditation will help you. There are so many difficulties, when you are holding the human body. There are concepts, impressions, doubts, tension, fear, depression, etc. Spirituality will help you overcome these difficulties. Meditation will make you less concerned about problems and difficulties. It will gradually melt away all your illusory problems.

Conviction leads to Realization. Spontaneous Conviction leads to Realization, enlightenment. When this happens, you will remain unconcerned with the body-form and its difficulties. The body-form causes lots of problems. Even saintly people have their share of problems, but they do not give so much importance to them.

Spirituality helps you to be unconcerned about the body. After Conviction, you will have strength, full strength and power. That power will be there, and will help you. That energy, that invisible energy will help you. Don’t worry, your problems will all be negligible ones, after Conviction.

156. Every time I feel closer to Selfless Self, it is, as if something comes in the way

This happens because you are holding the human body, and under the pressure of a lot of concepts. Keep the practice going, and ignore any interruptions. Melt all these concepts!

Dissolve them! Then, you will be totally separate, and independent from them. Have Conviction: “I am nothing to do with body-based-knowledge because I am formless”. That Conviction will appear spontaneously from within. At that stage, you will not be concerned with the world, the body-knowledge or the spiritual knowledge. You will not be concerned with Brahman, Atman, God, Paramatman, Master, either.

Spiritual knowledge is important while you are holding the body. When the body disappears, spirituality disappears, Brahman disappears. So, when the time comes to leave the body, there should not be any fear around. There should not be any concept around of, “I am somebody”. That has to be melted.

The impressions and impacts on the human body are so strong that, in spite of your knowing everything, you are not able to accept it. In order to accept your Reality spontaneously, you need to recite the Mantra and meditate. Give the maximum time you can to meditation.

Now concentrate on your Mantra, and on your meditation, which will help you. You have to stand on your own feet, and not depend on your Master. Stimulate your own Master within you. The Master is not separate from you. The Masterly Essence is within you. Therefore, Nisargadatta Maharaj says, “I am not making you a disciple, I am making you a Master”.

You are already a Master. “Disciple” is the name given to the identity that does not know itself. When the real identity is known, you are a Master.

157. I have the feeling that I am coming closer and closer to my Selfless Self, but then I fall…

Don’t feel it! It is spontaneous action. Why feel? Are you feeling, “I am a man, I am a man, I am a man”? Just concentrate on the meditation to discard all this confusion, and all these illusory concepts. Meditation is the only medicine for you. It is the only treatment for your malaise.

The mind, ego and intellect are there, and can easily cause problems. So, use them sparingly, not more than is necessary. All your questions and difficulties come from a weakness of your mind, and a lack of confidence and courage.

To regain your memory, your strength, your power, and your energy, you are to undergo strict meditation. Meditate until you get Spontaneous Conviction. The mind may not accept it initially, but if you persevere with it, that will bring an end to the mind, the ego and the intellect.

Don’t become a victim of anyone’s thoughts. What is Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, maya, etc? Everything is maya. Nothing is true. Nothing has ever happened. Prior to beingness, you are Brahman. At present, you are Brahman. When you leave the body, you are also Brahman.

The sky is in this temple. Prior to its construction, there was the sky. After demolishing this building, the sky will be there. The sky has never changed.

You need to transform your body-based knowledge. You are not accepting this Reality. The mind continues to catch you off-guard, and distract you from Reality. Don’t become a victim of anyone’s concepts, anyone’s thinking. Make your own decisions: “Yes I know!”.

If you want to ask questions, you can ask any question. You must be clear. Make everything clear for yourself. Nothing is impossible. The entire world is an illusory world. Shankaracharya repeatedly says, “To say “I” is illusion, to say “you” is illusion, to say Brahman is illusion, the entire world is illusion”. In an illusory world, God is also an illusion, as well as the Master and the disciple. Everything came out of nothing, everything dissolves in nothing. All our needs, requirements and desires came afterwards. Have some Self-confidence: “Yes I can do it!” It appears as an egoistic statement, but it is necessary in the beginning.

The saints have the same Spirit which you already have. The only difference is that they recognized their importance, while we are not recognizing our importance. Place your hand on your own head, mmh? Self-blessing is required – No God-blessing is required! You are to please yourself. You are to take the favours and boons from yourself. Behind painfulness, there is blissfulness. Behind the dark, there is light.

158. I am far too attracted to women…

Presence is neither male nor female. These bodies are human bodies. Where is the happiness in these bodies? Can this body have any appearance without Presence? No! The body cannot appear without Presence. Supposing for a moment, that you saw a beautiful lady standing next to you. Without Presence, there cannot be a beautiful lady there at all! There is only a dead body!

As long as we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, and considering ourselves to be men or women, we will have that attraction to other men and women. What is a man? What is a woman? Dead bodies! There are male and female bodies, but the Holder of the body, is neither male nor female. As long as you are under the illusion of, “I am a man”, this attraction will continue. It will distract you from your Reality.

You are neither a man nor a woman, “You Are Brahman”. When that Conviction appears, that attraction will dissolve. We feel attracted to other body-forms, because all the time, we are accepting that, “the body-form is our identity”.

So, unless that body-identity dissolves, you will not be able to know yourself, and happiness will elude you.

What is happiness? Where does it come from? Does sex give you happiness? Or, money? Or publicity? These are temporary things. You know that any happiness gained from these material sources is only fleeting. Sex, money, and fame are all temporary sources of happiness, They will give you pleasure for a few moments, that is all.

When it is your time to leave the body, will these material, pleasure-giving sources be available to you? Not at all! “Know Your Greatness!” All the happiness that you have experienced is of a temporary nature because it is sourced from the illusory world. Many, many different material causes, have given you moments of happiness, but never anything lasting.

Fidel Castro of Cuba was known for his womanising nature. He had forty thousand ladies! He had a big appetite! A lot of sexual attraction! What kind of happiness did he get? And what happened to that happiness, after he left the body? Think about it! We are not really thinking! Many people have a lot of money. Are they happy? No! Many people are very famous. Are they happy? No! These are not the causes of happiness.

Who wants happiness? Does the body want happiness? If there is no Presence, can the dead body experience any enjoyment? Can a dead, male body enjoy a dead, female body? Can a dead body enjoy money, or publicity? Think about it! You are not thinking about these things. You are simply going through the motions like an automaton, in search of one pleasure after another. What is True Happiness? Where is this True Happiness? All the answers are within you. All the questions, and their answers, are within you, and within you alone.

True happiness is your nature. It is permanent, and causeless. When you identify yourself in a real sense, and have the Conviction that you are not the body-form, then, you will stop looking for happiness from material sources. Your attractions and attachments will begin to lessen, and then, dissolve completely. “You are the Source of Happiness.”

When the concepts have dissolved, and all the garbage has been removed, there will be a feeling of expansion, formlessness, and vastness. And with that opening, there will arise exceptional happiness, lasting happiness. This happiness is your nature. It is permanent, eternal, and causeless.

Think about what I have told you just now! Read the books of the lineage Masters. Read Selfless Self. After reading all these books, establish your position. Reach a conclusion! Know and accept that: “Except for your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master”. This is the principle of spirituality.

159. We feel very good when we hear these talks. Why does this not last?

Because the illusion is stinging you again. The mind is pricking you from the backside. What do I mean by saying this? See, this body is called a man, or a woman. Do you forget that you are a man or a woman? No! You have accepted that your body is called a man, and, therefore, you live as a man. In dreams, you also appear as a man. Likewise, the Master says, “You are neither a man, nor a woman. You are Brahman”. Why not accept that? Try and absorb these Talks. Remember the teachings! Keep them close to your heart. And meditate! You cannot identify yourself without meditation. You cannot absorb this knowledge without meditation. You are wavering because you have not accepted your identity, and therefore, you keep getting pulled back into illusion.

160. If some illusion or dream arises, should I try to stop it with the Mantra?

Don’t do anything deliberately. “I will stop it. I will do it”. No! Don’t think like that! All your actions are supposed to be spontaneous actions, not deliberate ones. When the knowledge begins to flow, and you listen to your Inner Master, you will receive spontaneous instructions that will guide you in your actions, in all circumstances.

At present, you are employing the mind, the ego, and the intellect to guide you in your thinking processes. After Conviction, you will receive the answers to your questions from within, spontaneously, without the mind, intellect and ego. Your difficulties will be resolved spontaneously, without any deliberate effort on your part.

Your question at the moment, “should I record these thoughts, should I do that?”, demonstrates that you are back in the ego. You are taking on ego, and over-using the intellect. You are trying to do something, with the help of the mind. That is duality!

“Don’t Think Anything. Don’t Plan Anything. Don’t Do Anything.” Just wait and watch. Watch and wait! And you will see, that when you have a big question, a pressing question, some problem that needs a quick resolution, you will get your answer instantly!

“This is Called the Last Devotion, Atma Nivedanam Bhatki.” You are interacting with your Selfless Self. “There is No Body, No Mind, No Ego, No Intellect.” Without these subtle organs, some spontaneous feelings will appear upon your Presence, and you will receive a reply to your questions. You will receive the guidance you need, to manage each and every circumstance.

So, don’t do anything deliberately. There is no question of duality because “Your Presence IS, Without Thinking”. Your Presence is a Spontaneous Presence. It is only because that Presence touched with the body, that “I” appeared. If that touch of Presence and the body did not occur, there would not be an “I” a “you”, “he”, “she”, “it”. And, no Brahman, No Atman, No Master because nothing is there. There is nothing!

At the moment when Presence or Spirit touched, or clicked with the body, you started to say, “I”. Then, instantly, when you felt “I”, a glimpse of “I”, the world was projected. And then, when you leave the body, that projection of the world will dissolve. So, as I have repeatedly told you: “Everything Came Out of Nothing, Everything Dissolves Within Nothing”.

Don’t act deliberately. Don’t think deliberately. “Remain As It Is.” The saints say, “Without any thinking, “Be As It Is”. Without any thought, or any thinking, instructions for you will come from within. So, “Be As It Is Without Thinking”.

Prior to beingness, were you planning anything? “I will do this thing, or that thing?” And after beingness, after you leave the body, will you be planning anything? You are to establish yourself, without any identification whatsoever. When you are not identifying yourself, this is the way you were prior to beingness. And That is your position. It is your place of origin. Your Original Place! This is the Stateless State. “That Position is Supposed to be Established.” Be as it is! Everything will unfold and happen spontaneously, so, don’t try to do anything. Don’t think, and don’t plan anything. Nothing needs to be done with your deliberate action. This kind of spontaneous living will come with practice. Meditation, reciting the Mantra, absorbing the knowledge, staying with Selfless Self at all times, all this is most important. You have a lot of theory, but the practice is weak. Start today, with determination and courage!

161. When I meditate, a lot of thoughts are coming up. How do I make the mind still?

Don’t stress your mind! Don’t give so much importance to the thoughts. No stress!

Listen to me! In the beginning, I will take care of you. Do not worry about it. Since you have come here, I will make you perfect. Nisargadatta Maharaj says: “I am not making you a disciple. I am making you a Master”. You have come here as a seeker, or devotee, and you will leave here as a Master.

Convince yourself: “Yes, I am a Master. My Master says that I am a Master”. Live like a Master. You are the owner of this world. Okay?

The mind is a constant flow of thoughts. As these thoughts arise, you recognize what’s going on. You identify some thoughts as “good”, and others, as “bad”. You discriminate between them. Let the thoughts come! Accept those that may be useful to you, and reject the rest.

Forget about the mind! You are a Master, therefore you are in charge. Forget about the world because it is illusion. It is projected out of your Invisible Presence. Be brave! Nothing is impossible. Meditation practice is most important because it will give you a lot of courage and energy. Mantra Meditation is not just about a few simple words. Behind these words there is a lot of power, that creates inner vibrations. It creates a spiritual energy within you, that enables you to accept Reality more easily.

162. When there are challenges, can I still stay with the sense that my real identity is Selfless Self?

Yes, correct! Autumn comes, then winter. These are the seasons. They come, and then, they go. You do not come and go. You are there, and there only. Be solid, be very firm, so that no one will dare try to attack, or influence you, in any way. I am telling you: nothing will attack you! You will be strong enough to deal with anything that happens to come your way.

If you are mentally weak, physically weak, or spiritually weak, you will be vulnerable and susceptible to influences. Anything can take possession of your body, if your mind is wavering. Don’t let the mind, the ego, and the intellect control you! You are no longer their slave. You know that you are the Source of everything. Now you know, that without your energy, the mind cannot function. You lack spiritual courage, this is the only problem. You have doubts. Why? What are these doubts? Where were these doubts prior to beingness? And where will they be, after you leave the body?

163. I feel trapped in the body, in maya

There is no maya. Maya is illusion. There is no Brahman either. Brahman is also illusion. You have nothing to do with maya. It is just a concept. You have nothing to do with Brahman, too, because these are only words, the names assigned for “illusion” and “Ultimate Truth”.

Where was this maya prior to beingness? Where was this Brahman prior to beingness? Where will Brahman be after leaving the body? Don’t let the words trap you. There is nothing in existence. Absolutely nothing is there. So, why struggle with all these illusory words like maya, Atman, God, Master? Okay, there is nothing wrong with these words. They are needed to communicate spiritual knowledge, to indicate your Ultimate Truth, etc. But, remember that you are subtler than the space or the sky. There are no restrictions, and no limitations. You are not trapped, you are a free bird. You can fly without wings. Forget about the past, forget about the future. Forget about the present. Forget about everything!

164. What are the things that are blocking us, Maharaj?

Nothing is blocking you. Your own imagination is blocking you. Nothing is there. Where are these things that are in the way? Where were these concepts prior to beingness? Was there anyone, or anything, blocking you, prior to beingness? And where will these obstacles be, when you leave the body? Your own concepts are attacking you, and causing confusion.

No-body is blocking you. No-thing is blocking you because there is nothing except Selfless Self. You are formless. Again, you are considering yourself as the body-form, and accepting the seen. Stay with the Seer, and not with the seen! You are just like the space or the sky. Does the sky have any identity? No! So, directly or indirectly, you are measuring yourself in the body-form, and not accepting the Reality.

Nisargadatta Maharaj gave us a good example: As a small child, you were given a few small copper coins to play with. You grew attached to them. When you grow up, if someone wants to give you a few golden coins, you will not accept them, because the copper coins are more precious to you. They have become invaluable to you because of your attachment to them over the years. If someone says, “Take this golden coin in exchange for your copper coin”, you will likely say, “No, no, no, I want to keep these ones!”

In a similar vein, you accepted so many wrong concepts in the beginning, that now, when Reality is presented to you, you cannot accept it because of your attachment to the world – exactly like the behaviour with the copper coins.

There needs to be a change in you, a shift, a change in your perception, so that you can surrender the old concepts and attachments, and accept Reality. Give yourself advice and guidance, because you are the central point of this world. There is nothing blocking you. You are subtler than the sky or space.

The entire world is projected out of your Invisible Anonymous Presence. Identify yourself!

165. When I came two years ago, this knowledge was being absorbed very easily, but not anymore

Don’t think like that! This is nothing but a play of your mind. The divinity, your divine essence is already within you. You are a Deity. That divinity is not separate from you. Knowledge is your Reality, your Ultimate Truth. Knowledge does not come or go. It is there. It is! It is a fact that you are Brahman. It is a fact that you are Ultimate Truth. Knowledge means just to identify yourself in a real sense. By now, you should know better, that the body is not your identity, and not be fooled by concepts again.

Meditate more! Concentrate more fully! Sometimes the so-called mind goes quiet for a while. But, then, suddenly, it erupts, as it tries to distract you from the Reality, and your practice. Be alert at all times! And don’t give so much importance to your mind, to the flow of thoughts.

Self-enquire! Who feels like that? Who is saying, “Last time that happened, and this time this is not happening”? This is a game of your mind. Don’t listen to these stories. Don’t give them attention, or any importance. Don’t worry about anything. I am giving you a hundred percent guarantee. I am not just giving you a warranty, but a guarantee! [Maharaj chuckles].

These days, guarantees are in short supply. You can easily get a warranty, but not a guarantee! But, I am giving you a hundred percent guarantee. Just follow me! Sri Siddharameshwar Maharaj, used to say: “If you take the first step, I will take the next step for you”. Don’t be anxious! Deposit all your worries here in the Ashram. Empty yourself, and leave everything here. Leave here with nothing. Leave as a blank slate.

166. Why is Realization so hard?

Hard? There is no hard! What is Realization? Realization just means to know yourself in a real sense. It is just Spontaneous Conviction. As long as you are measuring yourself in the body-form, there can be no Realization. Realization means Spontaneous Conviction of the Invisible Presence. It is your lack of Conviction that is creating the problems.

167. I just have this desire for closure of this whole spiritual search, rather than continuing to meditate, do Self-enquiry and listen to teachers

You are to undertake all these exercises until Conviction. Meditation, knowledge, reading books, and spiritual exercises are all the tools that will help you. They have their own limitations, but they are necessary to remind you of your forgotten Identity. Why are these practices required? Prior to beingness, we did not do any practices. And, after we leave the body, we will not be doing any either.

When Presence or Spirit clicked with the body, you forgot your Identity. To regain that Identity, to have Conviction of that Identity, all this spiritual knowledge, meditation, reading books and Masters are there. Knowledge has its limitations because “Knowledge is No Knowledge”. Prior to beingness, there was no knowledge. After beingness, there will not be any knowledge. Therefore, knowledge has its limitations, and is only used as a medium, or tool, until the concept of the food-body dissolves. This is a food-body [Maharaj points to his body] It has a beginning, a middle – when it grows and develops – and then it has an end.

Keep up the practice, until Spontaneous Conviction. Be patient! It will happen.

168. I have problems with my family. Why is my son not studying?

Spirituality is not concerned with family matters. Why is your son not studying? Why is your husband not more spiritual like you? How can I help you with that? I can’t help you! If your problems are family-related, then I cannot help you. You have come to the wrong place!

You see, the foundation, or core, of spirituality, is that you are not the body at all. This knowledge gives you the courage to live happily and peacefully. Since you are holding the body, you started to believe in the body, and then acted accordingly. Sometimes, there is depression, sadness, and problems like these family problems.

Some people, particularly the ladies, often complain that their husbands are not doing meditation, or not interested in spirituality. “Why is my husband like this? Why is my son like that? Why is he not learning? Why…?” What to do? What to do? [chuckling] I can’t take care of your family life.

Even after listening to these dialogues, and reading the spiritual books, that body-based concept is still stinging you. You are stumbling because you have not accepted your Reality. You do not have Spontaneous Conviction.

You may be reading the books, but the Conviction is absent. There are still some body-based concepts that have not yet dissolved. Conviction will not be possible, without a complete melting of all your concepts.

Even the intellectuals state that the body is not our identity. Where were all these bodies prior to beingness? Nothing was there. “My husband, my father, my sister, my guru” – all these concepts came along with the body. When you leave the body, where will they be? Nowhere! Nothing will remain! It is an open fact! Forget about spirituality for a moment, and think rationally and logically, about the body. The evidence is conclusive: it is a temporary phenomenon.

And further, if Presence were not there, this body would have no value. Without Presence, it is nothing but a dead body. After knowing the facts of your existence, you will have Conviction: “Why should I worry about birth and death? There is no birth, and there is no death”. What is inside this body? What’s there? Just glimpses of “I”. It is space, that is like a veil, a subtle veil, through which we feel “I”. If there is no veil, how can you feel “I”? We are directly experiencing that “I”. Spirit only knows itself through the body. It is its nature to want to continue with this life forever. Of course, that is not possible.

7 MISCELLANEOUS

Don’t underestimate yourself! You are not a little, insignificant thing. You are Great! That Greatness is already within you. Stop ignoring it! The human body is a golden opportunity for you to finally know who you really are. So, please don’t waste any more time!

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

169. If there is no Realization, what happens?

Nothing! Nothing is going to happen. You will remain as a man, or a woman, and continue with all these concepts: “I am born”, “I am going to die”, “past birth”, “future birth”, “suffering” etc. You will take another form. There will be another dream.

170. As long as I recite the Mantra, I will be able to accept whatever comes my way. Is that right?

Don’t struggle with the mind. Don’t struggle with society. You are a Master! Make your own decisions. Take decisions on your own. Take this human life lightly. Don’t give it so much attention. Ignore what is to be ignored! Respond where needed! Accept what is useful, and reject the rest. This routine, daily life is illusory. The world is illusory! Don’t take it so seriously, or take it for real.

In the illusory world, everything is illusion, including myself, and yourself. It is a fact. I am placing before you the facts. What I am talking about now is illusory. What you are listening to, is also illusion. Think about it! Prior to beingness, there was no such thing as advice or guidance. These are concepts. Spiritual knowledge is also a concept.

For Perfect Identification and Perfect Conviction, we need to use a secondary thorn. This will remove the primary thorn. [A secondary concept removes the primary concept] You have mistaken your identity to be the body-form. You have been given “wrong” knowledge since childhood. You listened to “wrong” knowledge. Now you are listening to “right” knowledge.

I am placing before you the facts of your existence. I am not claiming to be a great Master because there is no difference between you and I. You do not know yourself, and therefore, the Master is guiding you to find your true identity.

Try to see Reality, the Reality within you. You are ignoring Reality. You need to sacrifice all of your concepts, before you can know yourself in a real sense. You are the Master of this world, without form! Birth-less and Death-less! There are no concepts of birth and death, or past lives and future lives. I am trying to hammer you with your Reality: “There is Nothing Except for Selfless Self”. We need to use words such as “you” and “I” to communicate, for teaching purposes. Just remember, that this “I” and “you”, are illusory. Brahman is also an illusion. Everything is illusion. Don’t cling to any concepts! Don’t hold onto any words. We are only using language as a medium to convey knowledge. Once this task has been completed, discard everything!

You are fighting with the concepts. You are fighting with yourself, because you consider yourself to be somebody: “I am a man”, or, “I am a woman”. This mistaken notion, this mistaken identity creates so much unnecessary confusion. There is no need for any confusion. There was no confusion prior to beingness. There will not be any confusion after beingness. What will happen to the body? Nothing is known! Nothing can be known!

“Nothingness” is projected into “somethingness”. The unknown became known when you became aware. When you started to know, you took the illusion for reality: “Oh, this something is reality”. This is very simple knowledge. A lack of confidence and willpower, is preventing you from accepting your Identity. It is stopping you from realizing, “Yes! I Am That”, without any ego. Then there will be spontaneous peacefulness.

I am placing before you, the Reality, your Reality, the Listener’s Reality, because the Invisible Listener within you is the Ultimate Truth, the Final Truth. So, instead of analyzing the words, try to convince yourself. Therefore, don’t analyze the words. See language for what it is, a means, and not an end in itself. Don’t struggle with the words. Try to identify, and understand what I am conveying to you.

All the gods and the goddesses are illusion. There is no such thing as a Great Power, that is in charge of everything. There is no other Greatness, but your Greatness. “You Are Great!” Because without your Presence, there is nothing! How can you identify the gods and goddesses, the Master and disciple, without your power, without the Power of Presence? Just imagine it for a moment, without Presence, you cannot view the world.

How was this life of yours prior to beingness? And how will this life of yours be, after beingness? This is just like a long dream. Every day, you see yourself, and then you see the world. The world is a projection of your Spontaneous Presence.

171. You say, there is nothing, but I think there is something else, there is a sense of beingness...

Don’t think! Why are you thinking about it? This is the Reality. When you think, you are taking a position, “I am a man, or a woman. I am male or female”. Who is experiencing the sense of beingness? What is that sense? Where is that sense, prior to beingness? And where will that sense be, after beingness?

What you are talking about is just imagination. You are formless. All the answers are within you. Prior to beingness, you are formless, at present you are formless, after leaving the body you are formless. There are no questions to be asked, such as: “How Am I?” It is just like space or sky. The sky does not know, “I am the sky or space.” Similarly the Presence within you does not know itself as “I am Presence”. It is Invisible, Anonymous, Unidentified, it cannot be defined.

Discard all your concepts, that is the purpose behind spirituality. You should take something from this Ashram. We do not want anything. We do not expect anything from you. But, you should learn something, earn something! Be That

Which You Are Already! You have an opportunity to know your Selfless Self, to identify your Selfless Self, to identify yourself.

This wonderful opportunity which you have to finally know who you are, does not cost anything. Grasp this opportunity with enthusiasm. This body is an instrument, through which you can identify yourself. “Reality Starts From You, and Ends With You.” You must have strong faith within you, to know yourself in a real sense. You know everything, but you still do not know yourself!

172. How can it be said that the waking life is no different from a dream?

Q: It is said that there is no difference between the waking life and dreams, yet in the waking life, things are very solid. For example, if I leave something on the table, it stays there, until I, or someone else moves it. These are the laws of physics, mathematics, biology, etc. There is no such continuity in dreams: all is chaos, and it is rare to find any sort of continuity from one dream to the next. When I awaken from a dream, I return to the same life and situations of my present life. So, how can you say that the waking life is no different from a dream?

Maharaj: How were you prior to beingness? Were there any dreams? And, after beingness, will there be any dreams? Where were the laws of physics, mathematics, biology? Where was this life that you speak of, prior to beingness?

When consciousness touched with the body, this kind of logical questioning began. There is no logic. Prior to beingness there was no logic, and no knowledge. Prior to beingness, you are unknown! You do not know yourself.

During deep sleep, while you are dreaming, there are many appearances. Who, or what, is manufacturing all these images? It is your Presence! Your Presence manifests your dream life, and your Presence manifests your waking life. Your Presence activates both the dream state and the waking state. The Experiencer of both, is one and the same. This Invisible Experiencer is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master.

The entire world is projected out of your Presence. Both the dream world, and this world, are projected out of your Invisible Presence. You are the Principle behind everything. In your dreams, your Presence is there. In this world also, your Presence is there. If there is no Presence, you cannot see yourself. There is nothing there.

The Sciences, Mathematics, Logic, Metaphysics, Philosophy etc, are all related to body-based knowledge. They came into existence with the consciousness. Therefore, avoid trying to explain your Reality, with these man-made disciplines! You are wasting your time.

What were you experiencing a hundred years ago? Nothing! Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing. You have all these concepts because you are posing yourself as the body-form. To get rid of all these concepts, we prescribe a potent medicine, a cocktail of meditation, reciting the Mantra, bhajans and knowledge.

Identify yourself. How were you prior to beingness? Formless, Stateless, Thoughtless. No knowledge, no experiencer, no nothing! That identification, that spontaneous identification, must be there. Only then, will all these questions finally dissolve completely.

173. If I do this sadhana, will I make progress?

Q: Normally a person expects something, and that is why, if these expectations are not met, there is depression. We think that if we do a certain sadhana, we will get something back. If this does not happen, then we will change Masters.

Maharaj: What progress is required? Who wants progress? There is no “I” no “you”, “he”, “she”, “it”. Prior to beingness, did you expect progress? And when you leave the body, will you be looking for progress? You have consumed a lot of spiritual knowledge from various Masters. Will that knowledge help you, when it is your time to leave the body?

You have met spiritual Masters, and you have read many books. You are a master of spiritual knowledge. Question yourself! Self-enquire! “Will all this knowledge help me on my deathbed?” The answer is there: No! Whatever spiritual knowledge you have, will not be useful to you when you leave the body. Has this knowledge, given you the spiritual courage to face each and every problem? If you do not apply your spiritual knowledge, and make it pragmatic, it is not going to serve you.

The fact is that you are unborn, but you are posing as a separate entity, who thinks, “I am born, my personality is like this, and I am going to die”. There are lots of other concepts swimming around. Find the courage to dissolve them. And find the courage to accept the Reality because Reality is not something that is separate from you. You are Reality.

Q: You said that after death, spiritual knowledge is useless?

Maharaj: You see, death and birth are also concepts. No one has had an experience of death and birth. In a dream, you may witness someone’s death. But then, when you wake up, you say, “it was a dream, a bad dream”.

Q: People who follow a spiritual practice...

Maharaj: Why are you thinking about the people? Think about yourself! What you see, is the Seer’s reflection, the Seer’s projection. If there were no Seer, how can you see the people?

Q: You cannot.

Maharaj: If there is no Presence in your body, how can you see the people? This means that the entire world is projected out of your Presence. If there is no Presence there, for even just a moment, who is going to talk about the people? Who will talk about God, the Master, and everything else? Dissolve that concept! You are thinking of these people, and whether they are realized people, or non-realized people. Why?

Think about yourself. It is the habit of your mind, to take the touch, of each and everything in the world. The world itself is illusion. Shankara says, “To say “I”, is illusion, to say “you”, is illusion, to say Brahman is illusion, the entire world is illusion”. Where are the people? Where is God? Where are the Masters? This is plain knowledge. Again, I will repeat the same thing, that the only way to absorb this Reality is through meditation. Dry discussions, and reading thousands of books, are totally meaningless. These activities will only give you some sort of temporary intoxication, like painkillers. “Everything Starts From You and Everything Ends Within You.”

174. Should I eat vegetarian food, or not?

Don’t be concerned with that. If your body likes something, you can take it. But don’t have too much of anything. The body is a food-body. Look after the body, and nourish it well. Here, there are no rules, about being a vegetarian, or a non-vegetarian. The food-body is separate from you. Were you a vegetarian or non-vegetarian, prior to beingness? Of course, not! Eat what is good for you, and what agrees with you. Keep it simple, and don’t feel guilty about eating non-vegetarian food, if you are a vegetarian. Don’t be too serious about it all!

Don’t be concerned with what you are doing, or not doing. “Who Is Speaking From This Body? Who Is Listening From This Body? It is an Unidentified Identity. There Is No Shape, No Form.”

Even though you know that you are not the body, you still want the body to survive forever! Try to know yourself!

Try to convince yourself! It is easy to convince others, but, it is most important that you convince your Selfless Self.

Maya is distracting you from Reality. Keep up the meditation practice. It is the only way you will dissolve these illusory concepts.

175. What comes first, the Absolute, or food?

Q: Basically, what I understood is that the consciousness is the quality of the food. And because of the consciousness, the Absolute is able to understand its Presence. And, for the Absolute to have consciousness, food is essential. But when we say the “Absolute” and the “food”, then there is a duality. So, which one comes first, the Absolute or the food?

Maharaj: There is no “first”. Nothing comes first. When did you first come across food? Was there food prior to beingness? When did you first come across the “Absolute”? Was there an Absolute, prior to beingness?

Q: No!

Maharaj: Will there be any food after beingness?

Q: No!

Maharaj: Is there any Absolute prior to, or, after beingness?

Q: The Absolute is...

Maharaj: Now you are thinking intellectually, “the Absolute, and then, something else. You are the Absolute. You are Ultimate Truth. Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. This is a food-body. When the Spirit clicked with the body, you said, “I”. Your Presence is needed to say “I”. If there is no Presence, who will talk about this “I”?

You say, “the Absolute is there, or food is there”. This is an intellectual game. You are just amusing yourself, playing with the words. There is no Absolute, no intellect, and there is no food either. All these concepts came along with the body. What is the Absolute? You are the Absolute!

Because you are thinking from a body-base, you discriminate and separate everything from the whole, saying, “this must be the “Absolute”, and that will be “Ultimate Truth”, and this will be the “food-body”. There is no discrimination. The words are used solely for us to communicate and understand. The Absolute is not separate from you. It is because the Absolute is there, that the food-body is there.

The Absolute is Invisible. It cannot be imagined. You cannot guess what it is like. It is Spontaneous Existence. Because you are holding the body, you are trying to guess how that Spirit, that Absolute is, through the mind, ego and intellect. Prior to beingness, did you know about the “Absolute”? Did you know about the “I am”? Of course not! There was nothing there.

These are only the words that we use to identify ourselves. Spiritual language contains so many words: Absolute, Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, consciousness, awareness, and thousands upon thousands of words are there, thousands of words are there. Instead of defining the words, instead of playing with the words, try to identify what they are trying to convey. Or, after reading the books, this Ultimate Truth, Selfless Self, I Am That, Ramana Maharshi, etc, instead of defining their words, and analyzing the sentences, pay attention to the meaning behind the words. What do they wish to convey? Language is of secondary importance. That which the Masters wish to convey is of paramount importance.

The message is that “Except Your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master”. All these names have been ascribed to your Spontaneous Existence, your Presence. That You Are! The Absolute is not separate from you. Ultimate Truth is not separate from you. Because you are measuring yourself in the body-from, through the intellect and the ego, you feel something, and then you say, “this is the Absolute, and this is the food-body, and this is something else”. There is no discrimination. That Reality is supposed to be absorbed. And for this to happen, meditation is essential. It is the first lesson, the foundation. Dry knowledge will not help you. We could carry on talking about this spiritual knowledge, but it would be meaningless – just more spiritual entertainment, like a spiritual massage, or a spiritual sauna.

176. What is the significance of Hari Narayana?

Q: Maharaj, today I was reading the Bhajans, and everywhere it says Hari Narayana, Hari Narayana. Any significance?

Maharaj: These names are not so significant. There are many names. Basically, you need to concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator within you. Rama, Krishna, Narayana and Vitthala, are the names given to the Almighty Supernatural Power, which is already within you. There were no names, such as these names, prior to beingness. And there will not be any names, after beingness either. All these names appeared upon your Presence. Prior to that, we did not know anything about Rama, Krishna, Narayana and Vitthala.

So, beingness is a temporary concept. It has a time limit. It is the span between the so-called birth and death. Birth means awakening, just to say “I”. Death means the disappearance of existence. Death and birth are concerned with this body only, and you are not the body at all.

177. Every question is answered in your books, so I can’t make up any questions

Maharaj: This is practical knowledge. It is your knowledge, the Listener’s knowledge, not the knowledge of Ramakant Maharaj, or of some other Maharaj. You also have this Reality of Maharaj. It is the same Reality. You are not separate from Maharaj. Our names are different, that is all. It is only because we consider ourselves to be the body-form, that we keep finding differences, where there are none. The bodies may be different, but the Spirit is one.

Recite the Mantra, and then concentrate on meditation. All your problems will be solved! Unless all your body-based concepts dissolve, you will not be able to identify yourself, and consequently, you will not find any peacefulness. You have been suffocated by concepts since childhood. Now you need to discard all these concepts, including the concept of God. God is the name given to the supernatural power which is already within you.

178. Can we say that Ultimate Truth uses the body to know Itself?

Maharaj: “Ultimate Truth is Not Separate From You.” There are many concepts swarming around Ultimate Truth, so one should not become their victim. I am referring to this whole background, because there is so much misunderstanding. People are asking, “Is there a last birth, a future birth? Is it okay to take “Rama Nama”? There is “Nama”, “Hanuman Chalisi”, and other similar concepts. They are not bad concepts, and they can be helpful, in the beginning. But, they are not useful for that moment when you exit from the body.

If you say, “Ram, Ram, Ram, Ram, Ram”, at the point of leaving the body, it will not help you. Ram is just a name given to a body-based concept. Energy is needed to say “Ram, Ram”, or “Shiva, Shiva”. “I Am Inviting the Attention of That Energy Through Which You Are Talking”, through which you are watching the world, through which you are watching your dreams, and everything else. That energy is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. That You are!

After Spontaneous Conviction, all your actions and reactions will be illusory ones, because you will know that there is no birth or death. Conviction will come with meditation. Through the meditation, you are hammering yourself “I am Brahman, Brahman I am, I am Brahman, I am Brahman”. This is called “Soham Sadhana”. It is the base of this spiritual knowledge. This practice will eliminate all the concepts, including religious concepts.

The Bhagavad Gita, tells us to discard all religions, and bow down to that invisible “I”, through which you identify all religions. Forget about all illusory religions. They are created to establish a happy and peaceful society. Religion is meant to bring happiness and peacefulness to society.

Since you are Ultimate Truth, the Invisible Presence appears in you. The purpose of “Except Your Selfless Self There Is No God, No Brahman, No Atman, No Paramatman. Rama, Krishna” is to convey that many different names have been given to that Ultimate Truth, but it is not any of those names. These names are used to help you identify your Reality.

Ultimate Truth has been called by so many names, but it is none of these names. It is not Ram, Krishna, or anything. Therefore, Saint Tukaram said, “All these gods are imaginary gods, and they will dissolve along with the imagination”. You are separate from all of that. So, stick up for the Real. Stick with Reality. It is the Reality called Ultimate Truth That You Are. This is the principle of spirituality.

179. It is said in spiritual science, that your last desire takes you to another dream

Maharaj: If your last desire is very strong when you are leaving the body, then it will take birth. That is the concept of spiritual science. It is not true, but it may happen. To avoid all this, you need to have the Conviction that, “I am nothing to do with this world. I am the Seer, the Invisible Seer, I am Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master”. It is a good concept, which will dissolve all your attachments to the body.

When the Spontaneous Conviction arises, you return to the way you were prior to beingness, “I am nothing to do with the body, and nothing to do with the world”. You will attend to your responsibilities as before, and find the courage to meet any challenges that come your way. The difference is that you will be fully aware that you are just role-playing.

180. You are talking about the new world. What about the old world?

Maharaj: There is no new world, and there is no old world. The world is created, or projected, from your Presence. Where is this old world, and new world? Nothing is there. What happens is that we accumulate knowledge from many different sources: books, teachers, reading, listening, and absorbing everything around us. You are to forget everything, dissolve all this illusory, body-based knowledge.

It is just like when you fill up your new smartphone with new applications. And then, we remove the old, unnecessary apps. The human body is a big computer, the biggest computer. It has been filled with concepts, engraved with concepts for the last thirty, fifty, or seventy years. Meditation will remove all your body-based knowledge.

181. Is that also another thought … that which wants peace?

Maharaj: No thought, no thought, it is a thoughtless state. There is no thought there. Thoughts and concepts came along with the body-form. Where were the thoughts prior to beingness, and after beingness?

Who wants peacefulness? Who wants happiness? Who is afraid? And what are you afraid of? You are still considering yourself as the body-form, even though you know that it is not your identity. Remove all the concepts. Be completely blank. Identify yourself!

182. Is meditation and Self-enquiry the same thing?

Maharaj: There is Self-enquiry in the beginning. Self-enquiry means investigating “Who am I? What is Brahman?” You Self-enquire because you have forgotten your Identity. Then meditation gives you some clues or landmarks. Through meditation, you are able to identify yourself. Through meditation, through that Mantra that will be given to you, you are hammering yourself, “Yes! I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. So, I will give you the Mantra today. Recite it with full confidence. Devote quality time for yourself. The human body is a wonderful opportunity for you, as identification can only happen through the human body.

Don’t confuse yourself. Forget all that you have read, and listened to, so far. Forget it! “The Listener within you is the Ultimate Truth. The Invisible Reader within you is the Ultimate Truth. The Invisible Experiencer is the Ultimate Truth.” The entire world is projected out of your Invisible Presence. God did not create this world. This is another myth!

There is no God who created this world. The world is the Seer’s reflection. When the Spirit clicks with the body, you see the world. To regain your identity, meditation is recommended. The Naam Mantra is given, and we are also asking you to sing bhajans, to create an atmosphere that is conducive to aiding Conviction.

183. How important is Self-enquiry? And, is there an end to it?

Maharaj: Self-enquiry is required because Ultimate Truth is missing, Selfless Self is missing. In the beginning, Self-enquiry is essential. “Who Am I?” is the most important question in life. The Questioner itself is the Ultimate Truth, but because we are holding the body, we wrongly consider the body-form to be our identity. Therefore, Self-enquiry is required because you don’t have the address that can take you home. You do not know your own address.

We know everyone else’s address, but we do not know our own! Who am I? Find out! Self-enquiry leads to Self-knowledge. Self-knowledge leads to Self-Realization. These are the three stages in the spiritual life. Why Self-enquiry? Because we do not know ourselves. There is much confusion about Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, confusion about spiritual knowledge, confusion about ourselves. While you are undergoing spiritual enquiry, you will come to know Brahman – That You Are.

184. What is enquiry?

We are talking about the nature, and the fate of the unborn child. Self-enquiry is okay in the beginning, because we do not know ourselves. We are told many things: that there is a God!

And that God is great! Find out what is true, and what is false. Knowledge is within you alone. It is not separate from you. Your “Spontaneous Invisible Existence” is itself a sign of knowledge, Reality, Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. There are many different names for your Reality, your Ultimate Truth.

I will repeat it again: You are Almighty God! God is not separate from you. So stop measuring yourself in the body-form. It is an open fact that you were not the body. You are not the body. And, you are not going to remain the body. But you have identified with the body-form. You have accepted it as your true identity. So, Self-enquiry is helpful at the early stage, to investigate what you are not.

Self-enquiry will lead you to the central question: “if I am not the body, then who am I?” You say: Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. How is that Brahman? It cannot be imagined, and, it is beyond inference, because it is a Spontaneous Existence without any identity – where there is no experience, experiencer, or witness. It is described as “Nothingness”. “Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing.”

185. Where does the body and the Spirit come from?

Take dreams as an example! In a dream, you can see the whole world. You see various people and places. How did this dream come into existence? In the dream, you are acting as a real person. Who has created this dream world? Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence! The world is also projected out of your Spontaneous Invisible Presence.

There is no reason behind it all. But, because we are holding the body, we have become very attached to it. Further, we have been gifted with the intellect, and so, we ask intellectual questions.

Your existence is an anonymous, invisible, unidentified existence. You are trying to use reason and logic because you are holding the body. You think “I am somebody”. There is no reason for a particular dream. Each day, you see a different dream. You see yourself, different people, places, circumstances, and happenings.

This information is short and sweet, because lengthy talk is meaningless. Now the ball is in your court. You have to undergo strict meditation, with the words that have been given to you. If you do not have the Naam Mantra, you may say: Aham Brahmasmi, Brahmasmi Aham. These are only words, but through these words, you are trying to hammer the body-based knowledge.

It is very important to recite the Mantra all the time. After continuous hammering, this illusory body-knowledge will be discarded, and all the concepts will be erased. That is the purpose of the practice. You will be totally free. You are basically free now, but you don’t know that you are, because of the various pressures that make you feel that you are in bondage, and unfree. Meditation will dissolve all your mistaken concepts.

I do not see you as a disciple, I see the Master within you. Nisargadatta says, “I am not making you a disciple, I am making you a Master”, because the Master is already within you! You are covered in ash, the ash of illusory concepts. The Master removes the ash.

186. What is Self-knowledge? Is it a direct sense of the primary “I”?

Maharaj: No, no, no! Self-knowledge means Conviction. At present, you know yourself as a man, or as a woman. You are neither a man nor a woman, you are Brahman! When the Spirit touched with the body, we started knowing ourselves as human beings. Who is acting within the human body? Who is listening? Who is reading? Who is enjoying the food? Who is watching the entire world? This is called Self-enquiry.

When you approach a Master, you are asking the question, “Who am I?” That is Self-enquiry. The Master reveals your true Identity, and tells you that you are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. You respond with disbelief: “How can I be Brahman? How can I be a Master?”

The Master explains that the body is not your identity at all. The body is subject to death and birth. You are not, because you are the Holder of the body. You are subtler than the sky, or space. How are you prior to beingness? You reply with, “I don’t know”. How will you be after leaving the body? You reply with “I don’t know”. This means the responder who says, “I don’t know”, is saying, “I am not in any form”. You are formless.

So, we need to Self-enquire because we do not know who we are. “You are Missing Yourself. You are Missing Your Ultimate Truth.” Self-enquiry corrects our wrong identification, our mistaken identification. Self-enquiry leads to Self-knowledge: Perfect Identification. The Invisible Identifier within you is Ultimate Truth. Your Identity is Unidentified, Invisible, Anonymous Identity.

Practice Self-enquiry! If you perceive yourself as a separate entity, an individual, a mere body-form, then Self-enquiry is needed. The Enquirer Itself is the Ultimate Truth. Self-knowledge is the recognition that “I am Brahman, Ultimate Truth”. Self-knowledge leads to Self-Realization, that Self-Conviction, which enables you to live detached from the body and the world. You are holding the body, but you are not concerned with the body or with the world. You are established in your Ultimate Truth. Nothing can touch you.

187. Spontaneous waves of light occasionally appear. Do these experiences enable Self-enquiry, or are they just mind-body-knowledge to be discounted?

Maharaj: There is no experience, and no experiencer. At the ultimate stage there is no experience, no experiencer. These are only statements, words, to try and convince the Invisible Listener within you. At that stage, there is no experience or experiencer remaining. How were you prior to beingness? There was nothing there, then. There were no questions, no knowledge. It is the same, after you leave the body. There will not be any questions or knowledge. This means that everything comes out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing. Out of nothing, something is seen. Whatever is seen is illusion. Avoid playing with the words, and analyzing the words. Instead, it is most important that you try to identify the Invisible Listener within you. And keep in mind that, “Except for your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master”.

188. Once, when I was on holiday in Tokyo, I went to a Buddhist temple. It was very peaceful. Is that okay Maharaj?

Maharaj: You can go anywhere you wish. I am not imposing any restrictions on you. Visit temples if you wish. There are no rules. Visit any country in the world, any temple, church, ashram or place of worship of your choosing, with self-confidence. At the same time, remember that everything is within you. “Visit the Visitor!” “Wherever You Are, There is Your Ashram.”

189. Maharaj, the body feels like it is vibrating. Is this good?

Maharaj: Good! It is a good sign. It means that the body-based concepts are vanishing. The process you are going through is a cleaning process, a purification process. The unwanted tenants are leaving. While leaving your body, they are abusing you. Since childhood till today, so many tenants have resided within you, so many concepts are there. Your experience shows that the cleaning process is effective.

190. When do I get liberation, mukti?

Maharaj: It is already there! Who wants mukti, liberation? You are already free. These concepts keep appearing because you still consider yourself as the body-form, these concepts keep appearing: “I want liberation, freedom, salvation, mukti or something else”. There is already liberation. You are free, but you do not know that you are, because you take yourself to be the body-form.

Yesterday, someone said, “some of the statements made by Maharaj are contradictory”. Don’t analyze the Master’s words! What is the point of analyzing the words? What are you hoping for? Nothing! Reality is not up for debate. This is not a spiritual discussion that is open for argument, and counter argument. There are many saints like Ramana Maharshi, Nisargadatta Maharaj, Siddharameshwar Maharaj, Ranjit Maharaj and so on. What is of supreme importance, is what they tried to convey.

Don’t try to analyze, or define the words. How many times have I told you, that language was created by us to communicate, and exchange thoughts with one another! Language is not ultimate, because we have given the meanings to our vocabulary. And, therefore, the meaning is not ultimate. It is a conventional meaning, solely to convey a message. Don’t struggle with the words, it is an unnecessary waste of time. Try to identify yourself!

You are roaming within a vicious circle, “I am a man”, or, “I am a woman”. Because of this vicious circle, we cannot find happiness or peace. We are always stressed. And, in the background, there is always that fear of death. Why all this unpleasant atmosphere? Simply because our identification is a wrong identification.

Though the Invisible Listener within you is Ultimate Truth, Final Truth, you are measuring, counting yourself in the body-form, as the body-form. You are trying to know yourself through the body-form.

Be clear! The body is an external cover. It is not Ultimate Truth. The Holder of the body, the Invisible Presence within the body, is the Ultimate Truth, the Final Truth, for whom there is no death or birth. Prior to the body-form, prior to this body-knowledge, we had no knowledge of ourselves because there was no physical existence.

Just now, there is consciousness, but there is consciousness with confusion, consciousness wrapped up in various concepts. So, spiritual knowledge teaches you how to act and react, in this illusory world. This is an illusory world, just like a dream world. We are all watching the dreams. However, you cannot watch any dream, without your spontaneous existence. Likewise, you cannot see the world without your spontaneous existence. Therefore, the entire world is projected out of your Spontaneous Invisible Presence.

Know, that you are already free from all these concepts, but directly or indirectly, you have become a victim of your own concepts, which were engraved, in you since childhood days. It is essential to discard all the concepts, otherwise, Ultimate Truth will not emerge.

The Ultimate Truth is there, the Invisible Presence is there, energy is there, power is there. And, just like electricity, this power is an unknown power, an unknown energy.

Existence is there, but it is not experienced or witnessed. That You Are: Ultimate Truth, Final Truth, Brahman, Atman, God, Master. Except your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman. What will the results be, after knowing the Reality? You will have complete freedom from all the concepts. Because you were bound to your own concepts, you felt unfree. Now that these concepts have been unwrapped, there is no longer any bondage. You are free because you are formless. You must have a strong Conviction, and for this strong Conviction, for a strong foundation, you must meditate!

191. What will happen after my death?

We are under the pressure of “I am going to die. What will happen after my death?” You are not dying at all. Death and birth are mere, false allegations, that have been made against the Invisible Presence. There is no death or birth for you. When you know this, really know this deep in your core, all your illusory fears will collapse.

Death means deep sleep. Do you worry about deep sleep? No! When you are about to drift off into sleep, you do not want anyone to disturb you. On the contrary, you will say, “Oh! just leave me alone. I’m going to sleep!”

There is always peacefulness, but you are disturbing it, colouring it with body-based-knowledge which, in turn, brings illusory fear. Identify yourself, and then, you will have the courage, to meet any challenge. “Be With You Always, And You Will See That Nothing is Impossible!”

Follow everything that the Master says. Strictly follow every instruction. Continue with your routine life. Spirituality is not a hindrance or a hurdle. Enjoy! Be Realized! After Realization, make others realized.

Death is a concept, but a concept that has the power to frighten everyone, every single being. Nobody welcomes death. The Spirit is unaware of its perfection, its Perfect Identification. It only knows its identity through the body, as “I am somebody”. And so, it wishes to prolong its existence, and survive at all costs.

There is so much bodily attachment because of this mistaken identity. Your existence, your Spontaneous Existence is everywhere, just like the sky or space. You are subtler, subtler than the sky and space, but you are not accepting this. That is the problem. To accept the Reality, you have to hammer yourself, you have to teach yourself. Be your own teacher. You are your own Master. Discard all your body-based concepts.

It is incredible, unbelievable, that we continue to self-impose all these concepts. We have become victims of our own concepts. Why? Happiness and peacefulness are not separate from you. Spontaneous happiness is there. When all the concepts dissolve, there you are. See, there is only nothingness because everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing. That illusory something, that you take for real, must dissolve.

Again, I am not asking you to neglect your body. Take good care of it. And observe your duties and responsibilities as well. However, at the same time, there should be the Conviction that, “I am nothing to do with body-knowledge, because I am totally formless. I am unborn, with no past and no future”. Past and future are for a “something”. This something is illusory. You are nothing, and, at the same time, you are everything.

You are Almighty God. Almighty God is the supernatural power that you are. You have tremendous power. Therefore a firm Conviction is required, “Yes! I Am That!”

You have forgotten your address. The Master is showing it to you: “This is the address. This is your Perfect Address”.

192. After that continuous hammering, what happens to the personality, does it dissolve with the body?

Maharaj: There is no individuality, no personality at all. I have told you that you are just like the sky or space. Does the sky have any individuality? Is the sky in India different from the sky in China? These questions will keep coming, for as long as you are counting yourself as the body-form. Look at you! See within you! Just be calm and peaceful. What is there? Just glimpses of “I” are there, without any form – pure consciousness.

This is a big computer. You are holding a lot of memories, every single memory since childhood has been recorded within you. Say someone knocks on the door, and you hear a voice, immediately, you will say, “hey, my brother has come”, or, “my father has arrived”. You are recording each and every item of data, like a computer. All the voices are recorded, so that, even if a lengthy period of time has passed, say some fifteen years, you will instantly recognize the voice and exclaim, “Oh! this is my Master’s voice”. Everything is recorded. Dreams are recorded. Who is recording all this? Who is video-shooting this dream? That Invisible Presence Is! That You Are!

Identify yourself! “Who am I? Where do I stand?” How can spirituality help you? Because it shatters the illusion of who you think you are. When this illusion is pierced, you will know your true Identity. The implications of knowing yourself in a real sense are huge. All your fears will simply vanish, along with your suffering. There will be abundant peace, and happiness that is causeless and permanent. The Master promises you 100% guarantee. This promise will be fulfilled, if you follow the Master’s instructions.

193. Is there a God?

God does not have any independent identity. Listen carefully: “Except for Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master. This is the principle of spirituality. What is God? Have you seen God? Be frank, have you seen God? To say God, some Presence is required. If there is no Presence within the body, who is going to identify God? This means that you are the father of God, the mother of God!

The whole world is a dream-world. It is like when you are dreaming. According to science, a dream lasts for a maximum of ten to fifteen seconds, yet when you tell someone about your dream, it is as if it lasted for hours. Apply your intellect! This is not theoretical knowledge, it is practical knowledge. Understand the theory, and then, through that theoretical knowledge, try and identify yourself.

That Masterly essence is already within you, so why are you underestimating yourself? Be bold! Have some courage to accept the Reality. You are lacking in courage, questioning: “how can it happen to me?”, or, “God will punish me if I do something bad”. These are the concepts that need to be erased completely.

I am not asking you to have blind faith. Open your eyes, your spiritual eyes. Bow down to your Selfless Self. “Oh God, bless me! Oh God, bless me!” No! Give yourself a blessing because God is not separate from you. You may not believe it today, but that Conviction will come. It will come. Just be patient, and keep up the meditation.

When you are reading books, read them thoroughly, and very carefully. Don’t just have a superficial glance. Read Selfless Self, again and again. Then the Invisible Reader will awaken, “I Am That, this is my story!” There will be Self-recognition. If someone writes your biography, you will easily recognize yourself in the story and say: “Yes! This is my story”. When you are reading a spiritual book, it should be like this, “This is my story!”. All that is needed is Conviction and courage. You are afraid of everything because you are lacking courage. Be bold! Accept the Reality.

194. Sometimes in meditation, I am aware of the colour blue. I wonder if that is why Shiva, Rama and Krishna are depicted in blue?

These are the names, these are the games! Imagination! What is the colour blue? Did you know of any colour, whether blue or white or green or purple, prior to beingness? These are imaginary colours given to all the gods. A black Rama is there, a white Rama is there in Nashik. Gora Rama, Kala Rama. These colours have been dedicated to these gods by human beings.

There is no colour. Colour is a concept. Everything is colourless, (this is also a concept). Prior to beingness, did you know anything about colour? No! Therefore, instead of posing such questions, try to identify yourself. God does not have any specific colour. Does the sky have any colour? Black sky, white sky, yellow sky? They are imaginary colours given by people. There is no meaning to all that! It is meaningless. How will this knowledge help you? Where is the sense? You are wasting your energy!

Some people are worshipping the black Rama, the blue Rama, or the white Rama. There are all kinds of colourful Ramas in Nashik. There are many Hanumans here, too. They have no meaning. It is a meaningless question. When you know the Reality, why ask such a meaningless question? It is just like a question that has come from a baby! You are not a baby at all.

Read some books. Read I Am That, read Selfless Self, read Master of Self-Realization, read Ramana Maharshi. God does not have any colour. Rama, Krishna, Shankara, these are the gods and the goddesses, the supernatural powers. Where were those gods and goddesses prior to beingness? If there is no consciousness, who will be there to talk about Rama, Krishna, and all the rest?

This is a meaningless question. If you are still asking these silly questions, then you need to read more and digest more. When it is your time to leave the body, which coloured Rama are you going to accept? The blue Rama, white Rama or black Rama? What do you mean by Rama or Krishna? These are gods, supernatural powers. They are just names that have been given to the supernatural power, Rama, Krishna, and others.

Forget about all this, and concentrate on the matter at hand – how you are going to identify yourself. Ask questions on how you are going to emerge from all these difficulties! You must identify yourself!

195. I wonder if, when I die, when I leave this body, I will realize that Selfless Self?

Who says you are not realized? Realization means Spontaneous Conviction: “I am not the body. I was not the body. I am not going to remain the body”. These are the concepts that have been impressed upon your Presence. To have strong Conviction, at the initial stage, you have to undergo strict meditation, and recite the Mantra at all times.

Then reciting the Mantra will be Spontaneous, even in deep sleep you will recite the Mantra. You will find that the Mantra is going on inside. It is an invaluable Mantra, but you have to follow it strictly, and you have to follow it seriously. Taking the Mantra is not enough: you have to follow it to the letter.

When the doctor gives you some medicine for an illness, you must take it, from time to time. If you don’t follow the prescription, the medicine will not work. Similarly, the Master has prescribed medicine for you: Mantra meditation. You have to take this medicine regularly, so that it cleanses your body. It is a spiritual body, an illusory body.

You have to take the medicine if you want to discard all the illusory concepts. It is like you are installing an antivirus software into your computer, so that no bugs or viruses will be able to enter inside.

FINAL PLEA FROM SRI RAMAKANT MAHARAJ

“Please, Just Accept the Reality!”

My Dearest Devotees,

Yes, my dear friends, we will have a short discussion. There is one basic thing: as long as you are counting yourself as the body-form, it will be highly impossible for you to accept the Reality. It is an open fact, that this body is not your identity at all. I am shouting this out all the time, in different ways. Listen to me! I am talking about Presence. Keep your attention on Presence, and not on all the illusory layers, that have covered over your Presence, your Reality.

Now that you have the knowledge, listen to your own Master, that Invisible Presence within you. Self-Realization will only arise, if you discard all the dust with a spiritual broom. Are you ready to remove all the dust, that you have accumulated? All I am requesting from you is that you undergo the meditation. It is the only way, the only medium, through which you can remove all this dust, all the garbage of illusory concepts.

You are happy to accept quotations from the great teachers and Masters, and indulge in re-quoting their words, parrot-fashion: “So and so, says it like this, and so and so, says it like that!” The fact that you are happy with all these second-hand quotations is a dangerous thing. You are hooked on the words! As you know, words are not Ultimate Truth, they are only indicators or pointers. You say, “I read I Am That every day. I have read Ramana Maharshi a thousand times”. You are inflating the ego by making these claims. That ego is dangerous for your spiritual career. Please don’t do this! Because even if you have read so many books, and taken the Mantra from me, it is totally meaningless. You either accept the Reality, or you do not. There are no half-way measures. There should not be any duality. That is the drawback of the human being. Read the Reader!

Read books, but don’t become addicted to them. If you have read all these spiritual books, why are you coming here? It means that whatever knowledge you have, is only theoretical knowledge. It has not touched you. You have not yet identified yourself. Don’t become a Master of spirituality, become a Master of Selfless Self!

The body is not your identity at all. When it is your time to leave the body? There should not be any concept of “I am dying” around. Prepare now! The purpose behind spirituality is that you should be fearless. Be strong, and stand on your own feet! You are Ultimate Truth, but you are not willing to accept it.

You are to dissolve the concept of “body-attachment”. Start from you! Everything starts from you, and everything ends within you. You are the central point of this world. If that Invisible Presence within the body were not there, what value does the body have, and what is the value of all your relations? There is no value. There are no relations! Please just accept the Reality!

You have to teach your mind, teach your ego, and intellect. Become their Master! It is very simple. Always remain with your Selfless Self. Ignore the mind, and the thoughts. Don’t waste your energy, by giving these things attention. If you follow my instructions, and meditate sincerely, and recite the Naam Mantra, all the dust will be removed. And, you will be delightfully surprised at the transformation.

After knowing the Reality, forget about all the illusory concepts! Because they are all decorated notes, fake currency, that has no value in the market. Use this approach to throw everything out. You are not fake notes. You are Reality! You are Reality!

When I am sitting here, talking with you, there is a flow coming from my Master which I am sharing with you. This can happen to you also. It is not impossible, if you become one with your Master, and totally accept the Reality that the Master is conveying.

After Spontaneous Conviction, there will be permanent happiness and peace, fearlessness and a stress-free life. You will not need any material cause, to make you happy, or peaceful. Happiness is your nature. Peace is your nature.

Don’t underestimate yourself! You are not a little, insignificant thing. You are Great! That Greatness is already within you. Stop ignoring it! The human body is a golden opportunity for you to finally know who you really are. So, please don’t waste any more time!

Just please accept the Reality!

PART TWO Excerpts of Talks from U.S.A. October to November 2016

Introduction From Sri Ramakant Maharaj SEPTEMBER 14, 2016

Jai Guru,

As you know, I don’t wish to deliver discussions on spirituality. I strongly expect that all seekers should have practical Spiritual Conviction. As you are aware, meditation is a strong base which leads to Spontaneous Realization. Without any expectations, I would like to share Ultimate Truth amongst all the seekers. I strongly feel that everyone should have complete spiritual happiness, peacefulness, a tension-free life, and a fearless life.

To have the Spontaneous Spiritual Conviction, the seeker’s sincere and deep involvement is necessary. Approaching different Masters, reading endless spiritual books, or merely dry spiritual discussions, will not help you to have Spontaneous Conviction. In the light of the above, I would like to implant Ultimate Truth amidst the Spiritual Heart of all. For this, your devotional participation is strongly expected.

With regards and blessings to all. My affectionate spiritual feelings towards all seekers.

Jai Sadguru!

SEPTEMBER 12, 2016 SILVER SPRING, U.S.A.

“You are the worshipped. You are the worshipper. You are the worship.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

1. The Quest to Find the Jewel of “Who Am I?”

Q: I’ve recently started using the “I am Brahman, Brahman I am” Mantra, and it is interesting that it seems to dissolve the questions.

Maharaj: See, at the initial stage, it is necessary to recite, “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”, because through that Mantra, you are hammering your Selfless Self. To forget your body-identity, to dissolve all the concepts, you need to recite the Mantra, Aham Brahmasmi, or, “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”, like that. These are just words. We use language for the purpose of understanding. We have given words their meanings. Through language, we are trying to identify ourselves in a real sense.

Meditation is the anti-virus software. It cleans all the illusion so that you can uncover your knowledge. You have supernatural power. That power is unknown to you. Your Inner Master is very strong. The Invisible Listener within you is the internal Master, Ultimate Truth, God, Brahman, Paramatman.

Casual spirituality will not help you. Your total involvement is most important. “Oh, I have listened to a good lecture”, “that Master gives great Talks”. No! Who is listening to these lectures? Find out! Try to concentrate on the Invisible Concentrator within you. It is called Brahman, Atman. Therefore I have told you, apart from Selfless Self, there is no Brahman, no Atman. You have so many concepts: “last birth”, “future birth”, “last destiny”, “karma”, “dharma”. What is “karma”? Whose karma? Whose birth? There is no birth. You are unborn. Forget about your last birth. Can you even remember anything about your present birth? No! Dissolve all your concepts!

Be free! So many illusory concepts are wrapped around us. Be free! This human body is an opportunity for you to find out “Who am I?” Stop depending on theoretical, literal knowledge. Approach your own Master because you are Ultimate Truth. There is nothing else that is Ultimate, except for your Selfless Self.

Be serious! The quest to find the jewel of “Who am I?” is a full-time pursuit. It is not a casual, part-time endeavour, but demands a serious approach. You are embarking on the greatest adventure of your life. Your strong involvement is essential. Spirituality helps you to stand on your own feet.

We all share an intense fear of death. We live with tension and anxiety, in a fast-paced world. There is no peace and happiness because we are neglecting our own identity. Directly or indirectly, consciously or unconsciously, we are protecting our illusory concepts. Forget them all! Let them go!

The body-form is the medium through which you can identify yourself. Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves back into nothing. The main purpose of spirituality is so, that you can identify yourself in a real sense.

This identification leads to the Spontaneous Conviction that “I was not the body, I am not the body, and I am not going to remain the body”. Bow down to your Selfless Self. Everything is within you. We have been depending on an imaginary God who will help us, or a Master who will solve all our problems. “Oh God, do something,” or, “Oh Master, help me.” Why? A child depends on his parents, but you are no longer a child. You are a grown-up! You are a spiritual grown-up.

I am placing before you the facts of your existence, the facts of the Invisible Listener within you. It is free of charge. Presence is free of charge. You are unaware of your Presence. Presence does not know that, “I am Presence”, just like the sky does not know, “I am sky”. Your Presence is beyond that, but we are neglecting all this. The Master is inviting the attention of the Invisible Listener. The Master re-ignites the spark of your Inner Master. Be with You always!

Q: Over the past eight years, I have read so much, I have done so many practices that people have shown me, but I just feel more confused, and even more lost, than ever before. I am tired of it all, and just need everything to stop. I understand the teachings intellectually, a lot of it, but there is no conviction at all. It still seems like a fantasy, and basically, just a good idea. I just don’t know what to do anymore.

Maharaj: It is a fact, an open fact, that the body is not your identity. Forget about spirituality for a moment. You know that intellectually this body is not your identity at all. You were once a small child, and now you have become a young man. After that, you will become an old man, and then, willingly or unwillingly, you will have to leave this body. That means the body is not your identity. Fact! Forget about spirituality. Intellectually, you know that the body is transient.

The entire world is projected out of your Presence. If there were no Presence in this body, what value does this body have? The body is only important because of your Presence.

And therefore, I am inviting the attention of the Invisible Listener within you, that you are Ultimate Truth.

How can this knowledge be absorbed? It can only be absorbed with meditation. Just talking about spiritual knowledge is meaningless. Meditation is the only medium, because through it, you are inviting the attention of the Invisible Meditator within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. All the time, you are hammering: Aham Brahmasmi, “I am Brahman, I am Brahman”! You have accepted the body as your identity, either as a man, or a woman. With constant hammering, there will be acceptance of your true identity as Ultimate Reality, Ultimate Truth, as the Holder of the body.

2. You Have Forgotten Your Identity

Maharaj: Have you read Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj’s books? I Am That? Selfless Self? Ramana Maharshi and all these spiritual books?

Q: Yes, all the books.

Maharaj: So, you have a good background. Everyone has spiritual knowledge. Everyone knows about the Atman, Paramatman, etc, but only in a theoretical way. Practical knowledge is most important, because what has happened is that we have accepted the body-form as our identity. Prior to beingness, there was no body-form. There was no shape at all. But because of our long association with the body-form, we have accepted it as our identity. We have forgotten our identity, our Spontaneous, Invisible Presence which is our Reality.

We have accepted the body-form as our identity. The body-form has many needs. Everybody wants happiness, peacefulness, a tension-free life, a fearless life. These are the four things that are required in one’s life, so the purpose of spirituality is to identify oneself in a real sense. We are identifying ourselves in the body-form. As a matter of fact, you are shapeless, there is no birth, there is no body at all. Prior to beingness there was no body, and after leaving the body, nothing will remain.

So the purpose behind all of this, is just to identify yourself in a real sense. We are identifying ourselves in the body-form, and that is illusion. To dissolve these illusions, spirituality plays a very important part. What is spirituality? Just to identify oneself.

We are identifying ourselves in this form, and that is an illusion. The question is: “How were you prior to beingness, and how will you be, after leaving the body?” Let us find out!

3. Investigate Yourself

Q: Can you give some instruction by which meditation can be made incessant? Meaning, you can meditate for a few hours, and after that...

Maharaj: See, meditation doesn’t mean sitting like this [Maharaj poses with eyes closed]. Meditation means involvement, total involvement. I will give you a small example. If someone abuses you, using very bad language, you will usually want to get revenge. You will be thinking about that person 24/7. If someone says, “Forget about it”, you will not be able to. You are focussed, and one-pointed. This kind of concentration, is the quality that is needed for meditation. You are obsessed with trying to find Reality.

Q: Sometimes I get this feeling...and the voice becomes so strong. It says, “There is no value in anything you have done”. It feels like what I am doing is just a waste of time. And that feeling is very strong.

Maharaj: The thoughts will appear upon your Presence, until there is Conviction. Various thoughts are appearing upon your Presence. Good thoughts, bad thoughts, depressive thoughts are appearing. You are prior to all of that. And therefore, I am inviting the attention of the Invisible Presence. Concentrate! You are watching this, and you are witnessing, all that is happening inside. I am talking about the Invisible Witness in you.

Q: Yes, I can feel that.

Maharaj: You are to dissolve that “I”. To say “I” your Presence is needed. If there is no Presence, who will talk about the “I”?

Q: Again, the identity with the body comes back into play.

Maharaj: It does not come and go. Is the sky coming and going anywhere? These difficulties are not your fault. I am not blaming you. It happens because you consider yourself to be the body-form, and have accepted it as your identity, and that is why you have these difficulties. Meditation is needed to remedy the mistaken notion you have about yourself. Meditation is the foundation. It is the anti-virus software. You have to install this software, so that you are always hammering yourself, with “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”.

Take, for example, the way a criminal is interrogated by the police. They say, “You are a criminal. We have this evidence against you”. But the criminal at first, will deny it, and reply, “No, I am not a criminal.” But still they persist, “Yes, you are a criminal! We know you are guilty, we have evidence. You are lying! Admit it!” Under pressure, the police succeed in breaking down the criminal’s resistance. He finally admits to his crime.

You are to hammer yourself in this way: “You are Brahman! You are Brahman!”, breaking down the mind, crushing the ego, until there is acceptance. “Okay, then yes I am Brahman!”

Q: Now, can I have your darshan?

Maharaj: Darshan?

Q: Darshan, a personal blessing.

Maharaj: You already have blessings. You are not separate from me. It is only the bodies that are different. Put your own hand on your head, and bless yourself. Darshan is okay as a formality, or, as a sign of respect. However, blessing yourself is most important for you to recognize, that you are the only one, who can give, or receive blessings. Take your own darshan!

4. Who is Watching the Dream?

Maharaj: We have so many concepts. We have a lot of literal knowledge: “I am somebody. I am an individual. I am a separate, independent entity. I am a man. I am a woman. I am a personality, etc”.

We have some knowledge of karma, dharma, and many different concepts, various traditions, rituals and religions. We have wrapped all these concepts around us, and then we try to live our lives within the illusory circle of these concepts. Your Spontaneous, Invisible Presence is Ultimate Truth. However, you do not know that. Your Invisible Listener is a Master, but because we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, we have forgotten all about our Master.

Nothing is there except your Selfless Self. Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, these are the names that have been given to your Reality, your formless Reality. Therefore, I am inviting the attention of the Invisible Listener within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. We are not accepting this Truth so easily because of the impact and impressions of the body. It is a fact, even if you think about this intellectually, that prior to beingness there were no bodies, no concepts, and no “I am”, also. When Presence clicked with the body, you became aware of your existence, and announced, “I am somebody!”. You are nobody, and, at the same time, you are everybody. Your Presence is just like the space or the sky. You are everywhere.

Therefore, do not measure yourself in the body-form. Meditation will dissolve all your illusory concepts. This life of yours is illusory. It is nothing but a long dream! You are watching the dream.

What is the purpose of meditation? Through the meditation, you can identify yourself in a real sense. Through meditation you are inviting the attention of the Invisible Meditator within you that you are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God. Through meditation you are hammering yourself all the time. It is an open fact: We start as a small child, we grow up to become a young man, and finally we become an old man. These are the stages of the body. Who is acting within the body? Who is watching the dream? Identify yourself!

It is a fact that the entire world is projected out of your Presence. Your Presence is Invisible Presence, Anonymous Presence, Unidentified Presence. And therefore, the first thing I wish to say, is to stop considering yourself as the body-form. When you are measuring yourself in the body-form, you are seriously underestimating your Selfless Self.

5. Know That You Are the Central Point of the Universe

Maharaj: Do not underestimate yourself. Carry out your responsibilities, as if you are acting in a drama, or movie. In the illusory world, we have many relations. We are mothers, fathers, aunts, brothers, sisters, grandparents, etc. We play so many different roles. Act them well! All our relatives came with the body-form, and they will disappear with the body-form. Take care of your family, but at the same time, know that all your family members are a big illusion!

All our needs, and all our requirements came along with the body. We only need spiritual knowledge because we have forgotten our identity. There was no spiritual knowledge prior to beingness? We are not beggars, yet we behave like beggars, pleading: “Oh God, bless me. Do something for me. Help me!” Wherever you go, you are bowing down to someone else, something other. The Master says, “Why are you bowing to everyone else, but yourself? Bow down to yourself! Bow to Selfless Self!” You are the only Power.

After Conviction, you will not bow to anyone. This is not to say that you will disrespect anyone, but, you will know that you are the central point of the universe. Everything is within you. There is nothing else.

Q: You say it is not difficult to achieve this Ultimate Truth?

Maharaj: Of course it is not difficult!

Q: And yet, it takes time for most people.

Maharaj: Suppose it has been dark in a cave for five hundred years. If you enter with a light, will the darkness say, “I have been here for so many years, I cannot leave immediately. It will take some time?” Of course not. Enlightenment is instant. When the light of knowledge shines on the darkness of ignorance, the change is instantaneous.

6. You Are Your Own Master!

Maharaj: Literal knowledge will not help you. Bookish knowledge will not help you. Be practical. You have a lot of knowledge. The test is whether that knowledge will help you, when your time comes to leave the body. The answer is No! Theoretical or book knowledge cannot help you because it is material, second-hand knowledge. Will it help you at the time of leaving the body? The answer is “No!”

We may understand that we are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman or God, intellectually, but we have not accepted this as our Reality, our practical Reality. We do not have Spontaneous Conviction.

All the concepts that are related to the body-base are supposed to dissolve. It is a very simple process, that only requires your strong involvement. Self-involvement is most important. “I was not the body, I am not the body, and I am not going to remain the body.” The body was not my identity, and the body is not going to remain my identity at all. This is an open fact.

The Invisible Presence within you is Final Truth. It has strong Power, strong Energy. Therefore, stop viewing yourself as the body-form. Though you are holding the body, there should be the Spontaneous Conviction that “I am not the body, and I am not going to remain the body!” The mind, the ego, and the intellect came along with the body, and will dissolve along with the body. All your concepts, needs, and requirements came along with the body. Concepts like “God” and “Master”, are just that, concepts! For you, or anyone else, to say “God”, your Presence is required. To say “Master”, your Presence is required. You are your own Master! But because of your long association with the body, you have forgotten your identity. And so, to identify yourself in a real sense, meditation is needed.

There are always many questions regarding the Naam Mantra. The Naam Mantra is words! There are so many words – Aham Brahmasmi is a word, “I am Brahman”, Soham is a word. Mantra meditation is a medium. Through the meditation, you are inviting the attention of the Invisible Meditator, and reminding yourself that you are Brahman. You will forget your body-identity, and then, the Spontaneous Conviction will arise.

Everyone wants to know about death. What is death? There is no birth, and there is no death, because you are unborn. It is a fact! You may not accept it just now, but with meditation, Spontaneous Conviction will come, and then you will know!

We have a lot of attachment to the body-form, which has obscured our true identity. That is why, at the initial stage, you are to undergo the discipline of meditation. Why is meditation required? To develop Spontaneous Conviction.

SEPTEMBER 16, 2016, SILVER SPRING, U.S.A.

“Why the Naam Mantra? To keep the mind, ego, and the intellect busy. To remain thoughtless, and to erase all body-based memories.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

7. You Are Nobody, and You Are Everybody

Maharaj: Has everyone read the books, I Am That and Selfless Self? We are here to identity ourselves in a real sense. It can happen through this human body.

Body-based-knowledge is not tolerable. “I am somebody”, is not tolerable. So, once you have identified yourself perfectly, you will know, “I am not the body, I was not the body, and I am not going to remain the body”.

This is a golden opportunity. Your Presence is invaluable Presence. Presence does not know “I am Presence”. This Reality, your Reality has been given many different names, such as “Presence”, “Spirit”, God, or “Energy”, but you can call it anything you wish. It is just like the space. The space does not know that, “I am space”, and the sky does not know that, “I am sky”. Try to identify yourself in a real sense. This misidentification of “I am somebody”, is to be erased.

You are nobody, and you are everybody. You are beyond the sky. The sky is everywhere. If you go anywhere in the world, the sky will be there. But the sky is not conscious of it being the sky.

8. Do Not Underestimate Yourself

Q: What is devotion? How do you practice devotion?

Maharaj: Yes, good question.

Self-involvement is most important. We have been trying to identify ourselves using words. We have been using language, to try and identify ourselves. You cannot identify yourself using language. Through devotion, you can identify the Deity within you. Devote your time to Selfless Self. Get to know your Inner Master. Your Spontaneous Presence is a Deity, it is God, Ultimate Truth, Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. You are a Deity. The Deity is not separate from you. It happens because we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, thinking, “I am a man or woman”, etc. You are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. It is a fact, but you are not accepting the facts. There are so many questions appearing upon your Presence. All these body-based questions will be solved when you identify yourself in a real sense.

There is so much confusion around because we have read so many books, and countless concepts have been impressed upon us. We must break the vicious circle, of body-related concepts. Try to absorb the knowledge which you already have.

Q: Sri Ramakant, after reading Selfless Self, the spaces in my meditation where the “I” disappears have become longer.

Maharaj: “I” appeared upon your Presence. If there is no Presence, who says “I”? You are prior to “I”. “I” is a word. “I”, “you”, “he”, “she”. They are indications, identifications, physical identifications.

Q: But I have begun experiencing so much peace in that. Before my trip, I experienced so much resistance to get here, and it’s like I had to make myself come.

Maharaj: Your experience is okay. It is a good experience. But at the last stage, the Ultimate Stage, there is no experience and no experiencer, and no witness. Experience appeared upon your Presence. When you come, closer and closer, to your Selfless Self, some good experiences will appear, like exceptional peacefulness, and happiness. There will be spiritual intoxication, without any material cause.

You are already whole, self-sufficient, but you are always underestimating yourself, thinking there is something else that is greater than you, some supernatural power that is regulating this world. As I said, do not underestimate yourself. Your Selfless Self is very strong. There is no birth, and no death – these are the concepts.

No one knows that he was born, and no one knows that he has died. You are unborn. Does the sky have any birth or death? Does the sky know hell or heaven? Good deed, bad deed, bad energy, good energy. What is good or bad? We made a circle, and within that circle, we have been trying to live our lives. Break the circle with meditation. It is the only way.

9. All Questions Are Body-Based

Q: How do you practice Self-enquiry? What is the process?

Maharaj: Self-enquiry just means that we are unaware of our identity. Self-enquiry begins when we ask the question, “Who am I?” There are no questions at the advanced stage. Though our identity has been called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, “God”, we do not know what Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, or “God” is. The Questioner Itself, who asks “Who am I?” is Ultimate Truth. You have just forgotten your identity.

Q: I have gradually been feeling more bliss, than at other times, for some reason. It was stronger than ever, when I was sitting here waiting. I was wondering if I could share this with my mother? She is very old. Is there any way I could help her? I mean, I have told her about this stuff, and she has a little bit of interest.

Maharaj: All your relations, including your mother, came along with the body. You are not the body at all. If you wish to share this knowledge with your mother, then share it.

10. I Am Nothing to Do With the World

Q: What type of meditation should I do? Should I ask the Self, “Who am I?” or meditate on the Mantra?

Maharaj: You are to recite the Mantra. Aham Brahmasmi, “I am Brahman”, Soham, there are so many. Every lineage uses different words. The principle behind it is, that through the Mantra, you can identify yourself. These are key-words, through which you are hammering your Selfless Self. As long as I am living as a man or a woman, there will be bodily limitations,

Q: Why is the Realization of Ultimate Truth so scarce and rare?

Maharaj: See, “Realization” means Conviction. “Realization” means Spontaneous Conviction. At present, we are saying, “I am somebody”, “I am a man or woman”, and that is illusion. So I am talking about that Realization, that Spontaneous Conviction: “I am Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. I am nothing to do with the world”.

This is an illusory world. The moment Presence clicks with the body, you can see the world. Where is the world prior to beingness? That means the entire world is projected out of your Presence. Therefore for teaching purposes, I define, That which cannot be defined, as “Unidentified” Identity, “Invisible” Identity, “Anonymous” Identity. It cannot be imagined. You cannot guess what it is like. This Reality is supposed to be totally absorbed.

11. Why Did Spirit Forget Itself?

Q: What is the benefit of the Naam Mantra and initiation into the lineage?

Maharaj: The Naam Mantra invites the attention of the Meditator, and reminds you that you are Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. This is the beginning stage, the foundation. You have forgotten your identity, always measuring yourself in the body-form. Basically, you are not the body-form, you are shapeless. You could say that we have lost our memory, and accepted the body as our identity, which it is not. To dissolve the body-identity, there is initiation: “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”.

Q: Why did Spirit forget itself?

Maharaj: There is no reason at all. Spirit does not know that, “I am Spirit”. Spirit is the name given to the Presence, the Invisible Presence, Power, Energy. Does electricity know, “I am lighting up all these things”? There is no reason “Why Spirit?”. We are trying to reason and guess, using the intellect. Your Presence in the world is Spontaneous Presence.

Q: Do you teach that mula-maya, all is a dream?

Maharaj: What “maya”? There is no maya. Maya is a concept.

Q: Correct. But mula-maya?

Maharaj: Maya is the name given to the illusory concepts.

Q: Okay, great. And you teach that?

Maharaj: What is that maya? What was maya prior to beingness? Was there any maya there? Maya is illusion, an illusory concept.

Q: Of course. So, you teach that existence is like a dream?

Maharaj: Of course, of course. It is not that “I think” it is a dream. It is a fact! Not “I think”. It is a fact! It is Reality! The entire world is projected out of your Presence. All things appear upon your Presence. It is not my thinking, it is universal, a universal fact.

12. Is Love a Concept?

Q: Is love a concept as well?

Maharaj: Of course! Everything is a concept, without exception. When did you come across love? “Love” and “affection” are concepts which appeared upon your Presence. When the Spirit clicked with the body, love, and affection, appeared before you. What is love? Prior to beingness there was no love. After leaving the body, will there be any love? As long as we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, love, affection, and many other concepts, will be there. My mother, my father, my husband, my wife, my sister, my brother, my Master, my God – thousands of concepts rule our lives.

When the body dissolves, there is nothing there, no concepts, no relations. All relations are body-based relations, and you are not the body at all, you were not the body at all, you are not going to remain the body at all, because you are Ultimate Truth, Final Truth, Final Reality. Absorb this Reality with meditation. Reading, talking and listening are not enough.

Q: I think of bliss, and impersonal love, as sort of the same thing. And to me, when I experience that, it is a fact for me. But then at other times I forget it, and then it is no longer a fact.

Maharaj: Do not underestimate yourself. There is nothing to forget, and nothing to remember. Dissolve that so-called “I”!

13. Mind Means the Flow of Thoughts

Q: When I do the meditation, I can’t help but have thoughts coming through. What do I have to do to stop the thoughts?

Maharaj: It is the nature of the mind. The mind means the flow of thoughts. You are witnessing the thoughts. You are different from the thoughts. You are witnessing, both good and bad, thoughts. Do not try to control the thoughts, just let them be. let them be. Suppose you are sitting here indoors, and then something happens outside. You would just ignore it. Thoughts are flowing all the time. It is up to you, to choose which ones to accept, and which ones to ignore.

14. Body-Based Knowledge

Q: Maharaj, why are we so scared to find this Ultimate Truth?

Maharaj: It is not like that. Because we have had so many concepts engraved upon us, we have accepted that “I am somebody”, “I am a man” or “I am a woman”. After Conviction, you will know that you are not the body at all.

Q: So, we are all Brahman, the Brahman itself. Is that correct? That is the premise?

Maharaj: It is more than a premise. It is a fact! Stop measuring yourself as the body-form. The bodies have different appearances. Q: No problem, so that is the premise. So the question that goes begging is: Why is one Brahman willing to harm another Brahman, if we are one and the same?

Maharaj: Because this is body-based knowledge. Brahman is not harming anything. Does the sky harm any other sky? Does the American sky harm the Indian sky? Sky doesn’t know, “I am sky”, Presence doesn’t know, “I am Presence”, Brahman doesn’t know, “I am Brahman”. Brahman is a word given to that Ultimate Truth that you are. The Invisible Listener within you is Ultimate Truth. It is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. It is not an individual. There is no duality at all.

Q: So, can one say that it is okay for this Brahman, to harm that Brahman?

Maharaj: No, no. There is no, “I am Brahman, I will harm another Brahman”. There aren’t two different Brahmans.

Q: Okay, so it is one Brahman. But there are two separate bodies. If I harm this body in some way, do I just turn around and say it’s okay, because we are all one and the same?

Maharaj: Egoistic concepts are there: “I am someone”. Erase that “someone”. Brahman does not harm, cannot harm, anyone else.

Q: But if harm should happen – and I think you said earlier, that nothing is really being done – then no deeds are being done, ultimately.

Maharaj: There is no doer, and there is no deed. We are measuring ourselves in the body-form, and therefore, all these concepts appear. I am talking about that Invisible Presence within you, where there is nothing. Nothing is there: no thoughts are there, and no concepts are there. The concept Brahman is also not there. And as I told you, Brahman is just the name given to that Ultimate Truth. Except your Selfless Self, there is no Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. So, Brahman is not harming some other Brahman – like, “this Brahman is different from that Brahman”.

Q: Okay, so in other words, what you do to others, you are doing to yourself, right?

Maharaj: As long as you are considering yourself in the body-form, these concepts will keep appearing. There is no other. No other exists! It is only because we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, that the concepts of “he” is there, “she” is there, “it” is there, and, therefore, they appear. Prior to beingness were any of these concepts there?

Q: But, if somebody harms someone?

Maharaj: When did you come across another, a someone? Prior to beingness, was there “someone” there? And, after leaving the body, is there going to be someone there?

Q: Okay, what if this body harms another body...?

Maharaj: I am shouting. I have to keep shouting at you! Because you are measuring yourself in the body-form, therefore, you are under the impression that there are different bodies. There are different houses, but the sky is one. This is called a bungalow, and this is a cottage. They are called by different names. If all the houses collapse, what would happen to the sky? Nothing! Stop considering yourself to be a separate entity or individual. It is because of this misidentification, that all these concepts keep on appearing, and causing you problems.

Spirit or Presence is One. It is only our bodies that are different. It is the basic thing. Since we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, all these concepts appear. It is only the bodies that are different.

The human body is an opportunity for you to identify yourself. Every moment is very important, very valuable. Complete concentration, complete involvement is most important. We are not accepting this. Everybody knows, “I am not the body at all”. Everybody knows that. Some day or other, willingly or unwillingly, we are to leave this body. What remains?

15. Egoistic Meditation

Q: Can you please say something about a practice that is silent, without words, that supports the aware Presence in recognizing itself?

Maharaj: After Conviction, there will be spontaneous silence. At present, there is no silence, only violence, because we have too many body-based concepts, clambering, and chattering continuously. Directly, or indirectly, we have become victims of our mind, ego, and intellect. To identify yourself in a real sense, intense meditation is needed.

Q: Should the Naam Mantra be recited continuously, after initiation?

Maharaj: Recite the Naam Mantra at all times, continuously, at every available moment. You need not sit in one position to do it. Attend to your duties, your work, and while you are doing this, keep reciting the Mantra at every opportunity.

Q: And will it still the mind, so that the mind is not all over the place?

Maharaj: The mind is always stinging you, pinching you from behind. Concentrating on the Naam is a kind of cleaning process. The mind will not let you concentrate on yourself. So, perseverance is needed at the beginning.

Q: Vipassana Meditation does not use a Mantra. It is basically about observing the breath, and observing the bodily sensations. What are your thoughts on that?

Maharaj: It provides a temporary relief. You can practice Vipassana for a time – one week, two weeks, or one month, but after leaving the Vipassana Centre, you will be back where you started. Again, you will find yourself at the same place.

Q: But what if you practice vipassana every day? I mean, what are your thoughts on vipassana versus...

Maharaj: The principle behind vipassana, or any practice, is to identify yourself in a real sense. Whatever practice you are doing, is based on the principle of identifying yourself, in the true sense. These are processes. Vipassana is a process, and meditation is also a process. But meditation is a strong process, through which, you can identify yourself, within a short time. It enables you to discard all the illusory concepts, and uncover your identity in a simple, quick and direct way.

Q: But in vipassana meditation there is no mantra.

Maharaj: Go ahead, do vipassana meditation if you wish, but you are posing yourself in the body-form, and then, doing some vipassana meditation, therefore, it is meaningless. “I am somebody who is doing vipassana meditation”. This is egoistic meditation. You are to forget about your bodily identity. “I am doing some sadhana”, “I am doing some meditation”, That “I” must dissolve. The process of meditation will dissolve that “I”.

Through the meditation, you are inviting the attention of the Invisible Meditator within you, that you are Ultimate Truth, you are Final Truth. You are hammering yourself, non-stop.

Q: In I Am That, Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj says, “A quiet mind is all you need. When the mind is quiet, all else happens, as it should”. Does it matter, therefore, how one quiets one’s mind?

Maharaj: After knowing your Selfless Self, the mind will not remain. The existence of the mind appeared upon your Presence. The existence of the mind, ego, and intellect appeared upon your Presence. Presence does not have any mind, ego, or intellect. And therefore, try to identify yourself in a real sense. These are the words. I am conveying this to you, through words. After Conviction, the mind, ego, and intellect will not remain. Where was the mind prior to beingness? Where will the mind be after leaving the body? The mind does not have an independent identity. You have given birth to the mind, the ego, and the intellect. Without your Presence, how can you identify these?

Through the meditation, you will be able to control your mind. The mind will be controlled spontaneously. Eventually, you will be thoughtless, as you were prior to beingness.

The mind means the flow of thoughts. There are continuous thoughts flowing which you define as the “mind”. The thoughts enter the mind, and travel to the intellect. The intellect makes a decision, and then the ego implements that decision. This is the process, the functioning of the mind, ego and intellect. It is of no concern to you because you are separate from all that.

16. One Master

Maharaj: All questions will be solved within you. You do not need to go anywhere to see any Master, I tell you this because that Masterly essence is within you. My Master, Nisargadatta Maharaj, says, “I am not making you a disciple, I am making you a Master”. You are already a Master, but you have forgotten your identity.

Q: I am confused about the best time to activate the Inner Master, and do Self-enquiry.

Maharaj: I’ve told you that “Inner Master” and “Outer Master” are concepts. There is no difference between the internal Master and the external Master. We say internal Master and external Master, just for understanding purposes. There is no difference between any “internal Master” and “external

Master”. The Master is the Master! One Master! There is no inner, and no outer, no external or internal.

17. The Naam Mantra

Q: Who is eligible to receive the Naam Mantra?

Maharaj: Everybody!

Q: Are there any requirements for that?

Maharaj: If you wish to receive the Naam Mantra, then you should be sincere. I am not expecting anything from you, but you should be sincere, in your acceptance of this sacred Mantra. It happens so often that things which are given free of charge, are not considered to be of any value. I am not expecting anything from you except your involvement, which is most important, nothing else. It is not a problem for me to give the Naam Mantra, but there should not be any ill-faith, or anything like that. Be serious about the Naam Mantra.

Q: How do you practice it?

Maharaj: I will guide you. You are to recite the Mantra according to your breathing. Synchronise the Mantra with your breath.

Q: Because sometimes it feels like we are torturing ourselves.

Maharaj: It is not necessary to torture yourself. It is a very simple thing. Why torture the body? It is a simple thing. It is your knowledge, not the knowledge of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman. The Invisible Listener within you is called Ultimate Truth, but you are neglecting it, you are underestimating yourself. You say, “God is great,” “Oh God bless me” – okay, no problem. But if your Presence is not there, how can you identify God? To say “God” your Presence is essential. It is a prerequisite. If there is no Presence in the body, who will talk about the God? Who will talk about this world?

At the initial stage, I am insisting on meditation because we have forgotten our identity.

You may have read a good number of books, and you may have listened to a number of Masters, but you are not reading, and not listening, as if they were the Listener’s story, the Reader’s story. Your story! The Master is narrating your story. Therefore, listen to it as your biography. Read Selfless Self as your story. It is your biography!

Q: Can you also recite Om Nama Shivaya, or some other mantra as well?

Maharaj: Recite one mantra, one mantra only. But do not take one mantra from one Master, and then go to another Master for some other mantra. Have some loyalty or faith in your mantra. Any mantra will do. Do not have a wavering mind, “Today I will get one mantra from this Master, and tomorrow, I will get another one from that Master”. Collecting mantras is meaningless!

Q: In the morning, if you have a habit of ten minutes...

Maharaj: Okay, no problem. With full faith, full involvement. Any mantra will do. Aham Brahmasmi is okay, Shivoham – any mantra. But, be faithful, and recite it with full trust.

18. Playing with Words

Q: I am kind of confused. You say that nothing comes from something, and then something becomes nothing?

Maharaj: I said that everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves back into nothing. Everything came out of nothing, and everything dissolves within nothing.

Q: But how can something become nothing? And nothing become something?

Maharaj: We are playing with the words. Try to identify yourself, so that this question will not arise in your mind. These are the words. I repeat, this is language, through which you are conveying yourself. We have created language. “Something”, “nothing”, “everything” -these are only words. The basic principle behind these words is that you try to identify yourself. Try to identify yourself, the Invisible Listener within you. Instead of analyzing the words, all these spiritual words, try to identify yourself: Who is the analyst? Who wants this knowledge? What is the purpose of this knowledge? To what extent is this knowledge helpful?

Suppose someone has a lot of knowledge. Will that knowledge be helpful at the time of leaving the body? You have lots of knowledge, you have read so many books – fifty years of sadhana, seventy years of sadhana, of whatever kind. Just question yourself, “After reading all these books, after approaching all these Masters, after gathering all this knowledge, will all this really help me, when it is my time to leave the body?” You should be fearless at that time. That moment should be a happy moment: “I am not dying, there is no death. I am unborn”.

Spirituality will give you the spontaneous courage to approach any problem. Thoughts are coming and going, negative thoughts come and go, depression, anxiety, sadness, etc, come and go. But after Conviction, you will ignore all these negative thoughts. They are momentary, like passing clouds. The clouds come, and the clouds go, but you are there, and there only. You are not going anywhere. The sun is always shining!

19. The Six Signs of Realization

Maharaj: Yesterday we were talking about the principle of spirituality, and the purpose of spirituality. You know that the purpose of spirituality is to identify oneself in a real sense. What is the reason behind identifying ourselves in a real sense? We identify ourselves as the food-body, and that is not Reality. The body-form is not our Reality.

I am not saying that you are to neglect your food-body. This is the medium through which you can identify yourself. There are so many concepts from childhood till today: “I am born”, “I am a man or woman”, social concepts, religious concepts – and within this circle we are living our life.

SEPTEMBER 17, 2016 SILVER SPRING, U.S.A.

“Bow down to That through which you know yourself.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

***

After identifying yourself perfectly, dramatic changes will take place within you. These are called the signs of Realization. Spiritual Science teaches that there are six signs, or symptoms, of Realization. Seekers often ask: “How can I identify whether I am Realized or not? What is the sign of Realization? What is the sign of Enlightenment?” After Conviction, after absorbing the knowledge of Reality, some changes will take place.

Shama means to forgive and forget. If anything happens against your mind, you will not get irritated, or become angry. Dama means tolerance or patience. Tolerance will arise spontaneously from within. Where petty matters used to irritate us, where there was even some violence inside us, now, patience will take its place. You will feel it. If an incident happens against your mind, you won’t be irritated. There will be tolerance and patience.

Titiksha means just to know the Reality. You are eager, anxious to know the Reality – “Who am I?” Suppose someone is talking about Reality, Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master. You have the ability to discern, the capacity to discern what you are listening to, calmly and quietly.

Uparati means that there is no longer any attraction for the world. There are so many worldly attractions: publicity, or power and fame, money and sex, etc. After Realization, there will not be any greed or attraction to the world. You are living in the world, but there is complete calm and quiet.

And then there is bhakti which means devotion, total devotion. After knowing the Reality there is total devotion. And finally, there is shraddha which means full trust and faith. You can use these as a barometer to gauge your progress.

After Spontaneous Conviction, these changes will occur. Prior to, and after beingness, at that time, there was no anger, nothing was there. These signs will appear spontaneously. You will be very calm and very quiet.

I sometimes tell this story, the example given by Gautama Buddha, which you may know. The story goes that there was a lady, who took on the challenge of irritating the Buddha, and so, she began abusing him with foul language. Gautama stayed calm and quiet. Eventually, the lady grew irritated, and said, “Why are you not getting angry? Why are you not getting irritated?” And he replied, “Oh mother, you have offered me something, and I have not accepted it. With whom does it remain?” This means that the abuse stays with the abuser. It is up to you whether you accept, or reject these illusory concepts.

There is a similar story, here in Maharashtra. There was a saint called Saint Eknath. He was a very calm, and quiet saint. So, one person took on the same challenge, “I will succeed in making him irritated”.

Every day Saint Eknath went to the nearby river to bathe. On his way back, this person would spit on him. Calmly and quietly, Saint Eknath went back to the river. This happened forty times. Eventually, having failed to irritate Saint Eknath, that abuser became irritated, and eventually bowed down to Saint Eknath. What did Saint Eknath say? “I bathed forty times because of you.” This is patience and tolerance. Saint Eknath then invited him for lunch!

What am I trying to convey with these stories? There will be a big change! Any violence that is there just now, will disappear spontaneously. It can happen. There will always be silence, and no violence. You will feel it, after Conviction. You will feel it. That is the principle of spirituality. Listening, talking, and approaching different Masters will not help you. It will confuse you. Some changes are needed. Only then, will real silence and peacefulness permeate. There will not be any tension. You will be free of the illusory circle in which you were living your life.

Why is there tension? We have expectations, and if they are not fulfilled, tension and irritation appear. Everybody has so many expectations, from family, from friends, from society. It is the nature of the mind.

All expectations and needs came along with the body. Body-based-knowledge is not tolerable. It is a food-body that will survive, for as long as you supply it with food and water.

It is an open fact that this body is not going to remain constant. Spirit or Presence, wants to continue living. That is its nature. Your Presence only knows itself through the body. Meditate! It is only through meditation that you can identify yourself, and have Conviction. No meditation = No Conviction! Knowledge will be absorbed totally. And, therefore, I am repeating: dry knowledge, dry discussion on spirituality are all meaningless. Even if we spent months or years talking together, it would all be meaningless. It is your identity that you need to uncover, not the identity of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God or Master.

No one but you can identify yourself. And this can only be done through meditation! The Master reminds you of your identity, but the rest is up to you!

20. Meditation is the Anti-Virus Software

Q: In your book, Selfless Self, you said that meditation is like a spiritual broom. It is a nice image.

Maharaj: Yes, correct, correct. It is the anti-virus software. Our files are corrupted files. There are so many concepts in them. Though we know our identity, and though we know Reality, there are still some concepts around. Because of some internal weakness, these concepts continue to flow and exploit us.

What exactly is it that we want from spiritual knowledge? What is the principle? You want peace. You cannot find peace. Negative thoughts are always infiltrating. There is violence within us. We say, “Oh, I’m okay, I’m really okay”, but there is something inside that is burning. That burning should stop.

For a long, long, time we have been posing as a man, or as a woman, in the body-form. You have totally accepted that “I am the body”. But now you know that you are not the body at all, and never were! The purpose of spiritual knowledge is to identify yourself. When you identify yourself, there will be an abundance of peace and happiness.

Knowledge is meaningless. There was no knowledge prior to beingness, and there will be no use of it, after leaving the body. Knowledge means just to identify oneself, in a real sense. We are identifying ourselves in the body-form, and that is illusion. And again, I reiterate that identification is not possible without meditation. To remove one illusion, we need the help of another illusion. To remove one thorn, we need to use another thorn. Then, we will throw both thorns away.

21. Selfless Self Has No Concerns

Q: So you do the bhajans, you do the meditation, you do the practice, and eventually it occurs… the penny drops – that you know who you are. You know you are not the body, and you know that the world does not even exist. And then you don’t care, is that right? You don’t even care what happens? So, if the body hurts, or if the body has great pleasures, or if the body is angry, or the mind is angry, it has nothing to do with who I am. And that is the end, that is the finality?

Maharaj: All these actions and reactions are there because we are not identifying ourselves. The moment you identify yourself, nothing will be there. The body does not get angry. If there were no Presence, then how can a dead body get angry? Prior to beingess, did you know about anger? And, after beingness, will there be any anger there?

Q: For me, sometimes, if there is anger in the mind, that anger has nothing to do with me, because I am the ocean, not the individual. And so I see that certain things I take the touch of, like...

Maharaj: Thoughts are flowing inside, and you are taking on ego. You are witnessing the thoughts – good thoughts and bad thoughts. Who is the witness?

Q: Be the witness of the best and the worst.

Maharaj: Your Spontaneous Presence is the Witness, the Invisible Witness. Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence is the Witness that is witnessing all these things. Everything appears upon your Presence. Presence does not have any anger.

Q: I guess what I am trying to say, is that pain and anger, do not seem to be of any concern.

Maharaj: Of course! Selfless Self has no concerns. You are totally different. These feelings came with the body. Prior to body-based-knowledge, there was nothing. We did not know what anger or anxiety was! Nothing was known to us. Who wants peacefulness? Who wants happiness? Who wants a fearless life? Does the body want a fearless life?

Q: The “I am” wants peacefulness. “Paul” wants peacefulness.

Maharaj: That “I am” concept appeared upon your Presence. If your Presence were not there, who will have anything to say about “I am”? That Invisible Presence, Power, Energy, is needed for you to say “I am”. A dead body cannot say “I am”!

Q: Correct, yeah.

Maharaj: If the Seer is not there to see the world, the world cannot be seen. Everything that is seen is reflected out of your Spontaneous Presence. To say, or do, or think, or feel, for any action to take place, your Presence is needed. I am calling it by the name “Presence”. To identify something you have to use some name – Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, or Master – these are the names given to the Supernatural Power within you.

I am inviting the attention of the Invisible Listener within you, that has been called by many different names. But remember! You are that Supernatural Power. You are not separate from That. You Are That!

Do not underestimate yourself. You have great power, tremendous power. But all the time, we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, and that is illusion. It is not your fault, but because of your long association with the body, you have become one with the body.

You are Ultimate Truth. It is a fact. You are unborn. Birth and death are connected to the body-knowledge only, and not to you. But the problem is that you are not accepting the facts. To aid acceptance, meditation is needed, and your deep involvement.

Do not torture your body. Why torture the body, in order to know your identity? Take some time out for you. Be involved! Look at you! “Yes, I want to know myself! Who am I? If I am not the body, who am I?” Ask the question. Find the answer within! Find the courage to find the answer.

22. There is No Difference Between You and I

Q: When you feel pain, pleasure or confusion, or when you feel great pleasures, or confusion, it is of little consequence, is that correct? Or, how would you say it? When there is pain in the body for you, or pleasures, or temptations, or...?

Maharaj: There is no difference between you and I. We are not individuals. It is only these bodies that are different. Presence is One. You are measuring yourself in the body-form. I am not measuring myself in the body-form, so there is no difference between you and me. “You”, “I”, “he”, “she” – these are only words.

Q: Yeah. I have seen it where you can meditate beyond pain.

Maharaj: Meditation will dissolve all your illusory concepts. All your illusory concepts are supposed to dissolve. That is the most important thing! Dry talk or dry discussion, will not help you. Even if you go to thousands of Masters, it will still not help you. You must approach your own Master. Give importance to your own Master. We are trying to find so many Masters, and you are neglecting your own Master. Recognize, respect, and bow to your Inner Master.

It is a fact that everything is within you. God, Brahman, Atman are not separate from you. If you were to see thousands of Masters, if you were to deny yourself, following strict ascetic practices, and torture your body, nothing will happen. These are only temporary pastimes, spiritual entertainment. You have got to solve your own questions within yourself.

You are to devote some time, have strong faith within you. All the time, we are dependent upon somebody else, thinking, “God will help me,” or “some Master will help me.” Help yourself, by pleasing your own Master within you.

Have some courage! Spirituality gives you the courage to identify yourself. We lack courage. Everybody wants to use some artificial limbs. Stand on your own feet. There is nothing wrong with you. You can fly on your own, without wings. In the beginning it is okay, just like a child depends upon his parents. But, now you have grown up.

23. Knowledge is Free of Charge

Q: In your book you said, “Be yourself and everything is okay”. How do you “be yourself”?

Maharaj: Yes, it is a fact! You have accepted body-knowledge. “Yourself” means Selfless Self, through which you are talking just now, and identifying some concepts. Self is not separate from you. “Yourself”, “myself”, these names have been given. It is Selfless Self. These are only words.

There are so many Masters saying things in many different ways. Instead of analyzing the words of these Masters, pay attention to what they wanted to convey. Understand the message they were trying to give.

The message is “Except your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, and no Master”. That is the gist of all spirituality. Remember this! It is a fact! Be bold! Have the courage to accept the Reality! You will find dramatic changes taking place. As I have told you, the six qualities of Realization will appear within you. Where you feel some irritation and violence, there will be complete silence, complete silence and peacefulness. Your tolerance will increase. There will no longer be an attraction for the world. Why be attracted to the world, when it is illusion? This can happen. The only thing you have to do is devote some time for yourself, for Selfless Self, not for any Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, or Master. Knowledge is free of charge. Value it! If someone charges five thousand dollars or something, you will say, “Oh, he is a great Master.”

One seeker came to me. His Master was a Hatha Yoga Master. His Master charged him five lakh rupees in foreign currency. Why? He had pierced his ear, and done this, and that. Why is this needed? Wearing different clothes, garlands, and so on, decorating the body? Or, a pierced ear! Why are they decorating the body? Prior to this world, did you come with a decorated body? Or, a pierced ear!

I am not criticizing anyone. This happens because we depend on others, to be able to know ourselves. We are not trying to know ourselves. We are not trying to know, “Who am I?” This is the main question. That question can only be solved within you because you are the source of this identity. Therefore, I define it as “Unidentified, Invisible, Anonymous Identity”. There is no name; you can’t guess what it is. If I am talking about something, that Invisible Listener is listening. There is a flow of thoughts. You are witnessing those thoughts. Who is that? And therefore, I have told you, “Be with you always” because your Presence is Ultimate Truth.

Do not accept illusory thoughts. Thoughts are flowing – why struggle with the thoughts? We are struggling with the thoughts, “Why this? Why that?” It is the nature of the body.

Q: But that’s difficult...

Maharaj: Why is that difficult? You can identify thoughts. Those things which you do not accept, forget about them! If a number of dishes are given to you, you say, “I don’t want this, I don’t want that, I want this food only,” correct? Do not flow along with the thoughts. Don’t follow the mind, let the mind follow you. This will happen through the meditation. Give yourself some time for You! Reading books, and listening to everybody else, will not work. Listen to your own voice, your inner voice. You must listen to your own voice. It will happen, if you are calm and quiet.

Q: But how do you know that the inner voice that you hear is not from your body?

Maharaj: The body is only a medium. You are witnessing thoughts. You are witnessing the dream, you are watching the dream. Who is watching that dream? You are asleep, the body can’t watch. Who has created the dream-world? Have you decided, “Today I’ll see this dream, and tomorrow I’ll see that dream”? You see the sky, the oceans, the gods, and so many things. Who has created that dream-world? Similarly, when the Presence clicked with the body, you were able to see this dream-world. The body does not create any dreams. It is the combination of Presence and the body, just like the combination of the matchbox and the stick. When the matchstick strikes the matchbox, you see the fire. Fire is everywhere, just like the five elements are everywhere. American water is not separate from Indian water. Is the American sky different from the Indian sky? Because there are different bodies, we say, “This is one, and that is another one.” Presence is One.

24. Come Forward!

Maharaj: After Conviction, all your concepts will dissolve. There are so many concepts engraved upon us! “There is a God”, “you are going to die”, “last birth”, “future birth”, “hell”, “heaven” – what are all these things? Who knows hell and heaven? We can’t remember anything about this present birth, so why are we talking about our previous birth? We talk about sin, virtue, and all these things. We are blindly signing, “Yes sir, yes sir”. Why? You are not guilty at all, so why build a guilty conscience? There is no deed, there is no doer. I am placing the facts before you. And again, I am repeating that the only source is meditation, through which you can identify yourself in a real sense. You will build courage from this strong foundation. You will get spiritual courage to embrace the Reality. We are afraid of everything because of a lack of courage.

Q: In the book Selfless Self, you say, “Be how you were prior to beingness”. In the practical world, how do you do that?

Maharaj: Just think about this intellectually. How were you prior to beingness, and how will you be after leaving the body? Is this body Reality? Eventually, we must leave this body, so what is the use of knowledge? Knowledge means to identify oneself in a real sense. We are not doing that. We consider ourselves as body-forms.

You are formless, you are shapeless, it is a fact. When Presence clicked with the body, you said “I”. So many illusory concepts are wrapped around us. We have accepted these concepts blindly. To remove them, we need meditation. Everything will become clear within you through the meditation. When I say that meditation is the anti-virus software, it means that all the viruses will be cleared. Again, I am repeating: Nothing is impossible. You need not depend upon anyone else, even myself. Therefore, Nisargadatta Maharaj says, “I am not making you a disciple, I am making you a Master”, because that Masterly essence is within you. The Master is not separate from you. We are confused because of our body-based knowledge. This is a food-body.

In the beginning, strong devotion is required, and confidence is needed – “I can do it! I know the Reality. I am the source of this world. The entire world is projected out of me.” This is not an egoistic thought, it is a fact. If there is no Presence, who will talk about the world? Who will talk about God? And with this solid base, all your illusory concepts will be dissolved, and there will emerge complete silence and peace. Whatever happens, whatever you do, “It’s okay”. Since you are holding the body, some things will happen against you. There may be unpleasant atmospheres, just like the clouds that are coming and going. But You are there, and there only. You will not be touched by anything.

Q: Sometimes during meditation, I have this fear. I don’t know what the fear is about, but I have some kind of fear. Why is that?

Maharaj: Because of the pressure of concepts, illusory concepts. Directly, or indirectly, we have accepted the body as our identity, and, therefore, there is fear. Where was that fear prior to beingness? And, after beingness, will there be any fear?

Does a dead body have any fear? There is no fear. Because of the influence of the body, the Spirit wants to survive for a long, long time. Spirit does not know that, “I Am Spirit”.

Q: Dear Maharaj, first of all I would like to show my respect for you. I came here a little bit late, so I apologize. But I want to say, that I no longer have any more questions. I want to thank you for helping me develop the Conviction with the identification with Presence.

Maharaj: Nothing is impossible. I repeat, nothing is impossible for you. You just have a lack of courage, “How can it happen?” Siddharameshwar Maharaj says, “Take a step forward, and I will take the next step for you. “Take the first step, and I will take the second one”. This means come forward. Whatever has happened until now, just forget it. Now that you know the Reality, why not accept the Reality? Reality is not separate from you.

Q: Sri Ramakant, there is a seeing that is very peaceful, and there is a seeing, where things lose their substance, but it is so peaceful, so peaceful. But sometimes underlying that, there is a fear of losing the attachments, the emotional attachments that we have, when people around you are saying, “You don’t care about me, if you are not worried about me”. That is the way love is being taught, and somehow there is a little part there, that is afraid of losing that attachment. But like you said, Selfless Self feels peace, and its seeing is peace. Does it take time to move out of that fear, where you lose that old way of seeing things?

Maharaj: What is happening is that concepts are taking possession of your body. When there is no alertness, no awareness, then concepts take possession of your body, and there will be fear. Therefore, meditation and reciting the Mantra etc. are needed. Because through that, you are reminding yourself all the time that: “I am Brahman”, so that there will be no fear.

SEPTEMBER 18, 2016 SILVER SPRING, U.S.A.

“STOP! Put the books away. Go Within. Read your own book. Your Inner Guru is Almighty.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

25. Nothing is Happening

Maharaj: We have been discussing spirituality for the past two days now. You have the basic knowledge. I do not want to repeat the same thing again and again. You just have to absorb the knowledge, try to know Reality. Just try to identify yourself. It is very easy to discuss spirituality. It is more difficult to absorb it.

What exactly do we want? If you do not know what you want, you will carry on drifting, roaming, here and there. And therefore, today’s message is: try to identify the Invisible Listener within you which is Ultimate Truth. The Master-Key is meditation. All the illusory concepts are supposed to be totally dissolved. Until you have the Conviction that, “I am not the body, I was not the body, and I am not going to remain the body”, Reality will not be clear.

Q: According to the Vedic understanding of the evolution of consciousness, we first have to understand who we are, that is, the unbounded awareness. Then, perception refines over time to perceive finer and finer levels of creation, until one perceives the infinite, and sees that there is no difference between That and that which I am. Is this a sequence that happens over time, or can it happen all at once?

Maharaj: Nothing is happening. This is the Spontaneous Projection of your Ultimate Truth. Nothing has happened, and nothing is going to happen. You are not the doer, and there is no deed.

Up until now, we have been measuring ourselves in the body-form, and that is illusion. So many questions, like this one, appear upon your Presence. Try to identify that Invisible Presence within you. You are not the body, there is no shape, there is no nothing.

26. Meditation, Prayers and Bhajans

Maharaj: To have Conviction, to absorb this knowledge, you have to undergo the basics of meditation. There isn’t any other way. Questions, counter-questions, and analysis, all this is just temporary spiritual entertainment.

Q: Is there any specific way to do meditation?

Maharaj: Meditation means concentration and self-involvement. It does not mean sitting, and chanting, say, “Ram, Ram, Ram, Ram”. Identify yourself! Sit quietly and calmly, and see what is happening. Who is witnessing the thoughts? What is that? It is not the body. It is your Nameless, Supernatural Power.

Q: So, meditating means...

Maharaj: Meditation means just to identify yourself. Invite the attention of the Invisible Meditator within you, that you are Brahman. Nothing is there except your Self.

Q: And the same question about the bhajans...

Maharaj: Yes, yes, prayers and bhajans are required, because this is the weak, or sensitive point of the Spirit. These bhajans create an atmosphere. As we play the various instruments, we create an atmosphere. Spiritual Science says it is the sattva guna. There are three gunas: sattva, raja, and tama.

Q: Should we sing a specific kind of bhajan, or will any general bhajan do?

Maharaj: Sing any bhajans you wish, that bring you happiness and peace. Like everything else, the bhajans is only another medium, through which you are awakening your Inner Master, and drawing closer to Selfless Self. There will be spontaneous peacefulness, not artificial peacefulness, not peacefulness through any material cause. There will be abundant peace, and overflowing happiness.

Do not underestimate your Selfless Self. That grand secret is within you. You have been ignoring yourself because of your concepts, and expectations, that have kept you in the world. You have been living within the circle of concepts. Break out of the circle. Meditation will give you the courage to break free.

Every single being wants a peaceful life, a happy life, a fearless life, a tension-free life. It is a fact. You can have it! It is yours for the taking.

27. Be Simple, Be Normal

Q: My mind keeps asking, “Why am I here? To be of service? Or, “Why am I here in the physical body, if I am already Brahman?”

Maharaj: That which says “my mind”, is different from the mind. You are not the mind at all. You are watching your mind, identifying your mind, experiencing your mind. The mind is separate from you. You are supplying energy to your mind. You can control your mind. It happens, it is the nature of the mind. The thoughts are flowing. You are separate from the thoughts. You are thoughtless.

Q: Maharaj, over the last couple of years, my sadhana has progressed quite a bit. More so just sitting in dnyana, seeing the seer, knowing the knower. Basically being able to pivot the mind backwards, in the state of awareness. There is a statement by Nisargadatta Maharaj: “Patience and perseverance are most important at that stage”. So, I have been continuing like this for the last couple of years, and now I can do it for about two hours a day. What next?

Maharaj: There is no next. No next is there, nothing is there. Does the sky have any “next” or “first”, or “earlier”? Think about it. Your Presence is just like the sky or the space. It is everywhere like the five elements. Mind, ego, intellect – these concepts appeared upon your Presence. I am inviting the attention of that Presence through which you say, “my mind, my ego, my intellect.” All relations, all requirements, all needs – who wants all these things? Where was that mind prior to beingness? There was no ego, and no intellect, prior to beingness.

I am placing before you various words in different ways. Try to identify the principle behind these words. This is not dry, spiritual knowledge. It is the Listener’s Truth. The Listener is Ultimate. You are Ultimate Truth. You are the destination. The Absolute is within you.

28. The Body is a Magic Box

Maharaj: Try and absorb what you have heard. We have so many body-based questions because of the mistaken conviction that you are somebody. You are not somebody, you are everybody. Your Presence is everywhere, just like the space or the sky. You are not limited to the body. The body is an external cover. You can use your body, just like these clothes. We clean our clothes, and take care of our clothes.

Your sadhana is necessary for the beginning stage only. After Conviction, sadhana is not needed. When you begin your practice, you are like the toddler, who needs a walker to help him walk because he is just learning, and still not strong enough to stand on his own feet. So, similarly, we need aids, props and support in the beginning, until all our concepts are wiped out, and we are established in Ultimate Truth. Have a dialogue with Selfless Self. Convince yourself of your true identity, your Reality.

This body is a magic box. This is a magic box that contains unimaginable power within it. But we are neglecting that because we are always looking out there. We have some concepts of an external Power: “There is a God out there, and He is administering the whole world. It is with His grace and with His power, that I am living”. All this is okay, however, it is not true! There is no external power. There is no other power but you! Have some faith within your Selfless Self! Be calm and quiet. Just see what is there! It is just glimpses of “I”, without any shape or form.

At the beginning stage, sadhana is required, meditation is required, to rid yourself of all your body-based concepts, and absorb the knowledge. Sadhana is necessary until Spontaneous Conviction.

29. If you are Realized, Make Others Realized

Q: Maharaj, will anyone carry on the lineage after you?

Maharaj: It is not like that. The lineage is a spontaneous lineage. We call it a “lineage”, but this lineage does not have any individuals, and no specific personalities. And, it is also an illusion. This Master, that Master, that other Master, this is okay. We have this concept, when we are living in this body-form.

Siddharameshwar Maharaj, my spiritual Grand-Master, says, “If you are Realized, make others Realized. If you are peaceful, make others peaceful.” There are no hard and fast rules. If you are Realized, unroll your rug or mat, and start talking. Share the knowledge, but, do not turn spirituality into a business. Do not make a business out of spirituality. This knowledge is free. It is free knowledge.

We do not expect anything from anyone. We have an ashram also. Visitors who wish to give a spontaneous contribution, may do so. There are no demands. This is the discipline of our lineage which states in no uncertain terms, “not to demand a single rupee, from any person, or any devotee, for personal use, or any other purpose”. So then, the question is often asked, “How are you maintaining the ashram?” From spontaneous contributions given by local devotees. There is no donation box in our ashram. Why is money required? What is the use of that money? Okay, you need it for maintenance, but not in the name of spirituality.

So if you are Realized, make others Realized. But do not do so with any commercial motives.

30. Spirituality Gives You Courage

Q: If one is no longer identified with the body, and knows what he is, will he no longer feel any pain, and the fear associated with the world?

Maharaj: Undergo the meditation! There is fear because we have developed body-based-concepts. What is the fear?

Q: I mean, responsibility for acting in the world.

Maharaj: Okay. Yes, yes, of course. Spirituality will give you courage. After Identification, you will have courage, and know how to sail through your family life, and your daily, routine life. Be alert, particularly during the meditation, when some negative concepts and atmospheres will, no doubt, appear. Be firm and resolute. Do not give up. Ignore whatever arises, because you know that it is the nature of the mind and, therefore, it is not worthy of your attention. Concentrate fully! Give your complete attention to Reality alone! Have the Conviction that your body-form is not your identity at all. It is a dead body!

Without your Spontaneous Presence, the body has no value...“take it away, take it away”! The Seer must be there to enable any seeing. The Seer must be there, for you to see the world. This means that you are the central point. You are the source of this whole world. Presence is needed to identify everything, and to say, “this world”, “God”, etc.

Q: Pretty soon I am going to have an operation, and I am going to get a pain shot. But this time I am not going to try to meditate. I mean, I will meditate, too, and recognize that I am not the one feeling the pain because I am spaceless, timeless, not an object that can be touched. However, I would like you to comment on that. I will get the pain shot! I used to try to meditate and not use the pain shot. Now I say to heck with that, what’s the difference? I’ll just take it. If there is a headache, I’ll take an aspirin. What’s the difference? It is just the way the knowledge is happening, so it is no big deal. But I would like to hear your comments on that.

Maharaj: These are physical problems. If there are physical problems, accept the help of the doctors. But, at the same time, meditation will give you a lot of courage, to bear all these negative experiences, disease, and all these intolerable things. Where previously there was intolerance, now, unbearable things will become bearable. This happens after Conviction. Since we are holding the body, headaches are bound to be there, depression is bound to be there, illness of various sorts are bound to be there, therefore, accept the doctors’ help. “Oh, I am a spiritual man, how can I ask the doctor for help!”

The body is the medium through which you can identify yourself, so, do not neglect your body. I request everyone not to neglect their bodies. Go and see a doctor, if you need to. This is a food-body. You must supply food, water, and nourishment to it, while at the same time, don’t be attached to it. “I am not the body, I was not the body, and I am not going to remain the body”. It is an open fact. But, we are not accepting it, and therefore, there is painfulness. Directly, or indirectly, we have given importance to the body. It’s okay, you can use the body, but remember that you are the Holder of the body!

Guidance From Sri Ramakant Maharaj OCTOBER 11, 2016

Jai Guru,

There will be miraculous or dramatic changes appearing. Exceptional blissfulness, peacefulness, fearlessness, no tension, and all these, without any material causes.

This is a sign of absorbing the Reality within you, instead of playing with the spiritual words – Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, mind, ego, intellect, maya, Brahman, destiny, last birth, future birth, karma, or religion, past life, future life, consciousness or subconsciousness, subtle bodies, and so on. It is a fact, that prior to beingness, nothing was there. After leaving the body nothing will remain. Spirituality is required to identify the Unidentified Identity, or to have the Spontaneous Conviction that the food-body is not your identity at all. Why play with the so-called spiritual words? What we see is the Seer’s projection. If the Seer’s Spontaneous Presence is not there in the food-body, who will identify the world?

In brief, whatever we see and experience is totally illusion, but the Spontaneous Seer through the food-body is Reality, where there is no experience, no experiencer, and no witness. It is beyond imagination, and beyond logical or intellectual guessing. Everything came out of nothing, and everything will dissolve within nothing. And you know better. Language was created within the circle of the human body. When the Spontaneous Presence touched with the body, the

experience of “I” appeared upon your Presence. A name was given to us, either male or female, and instantly, we started measuring ourselves as, “I am somebody”, along with the existence of the mind, ego, and intellect, which appeared through the food-body and started functioning. Since the food-body experience is not tolerable, one started to seek happiness, peacefulness, a tension-free life, and a fearless-life through material causes. When it is found that these material causes only give temporary relief, then human beings turn to spirituality, through which one can identify oneself in a real sense. The various illusory concepts dissolve spontaneously.

As you know, in the beginning, an external, Realized Master is necessary. As a matter of fact, external and internal Masters are spiritual concepts. However, at the initial stage, it is necessary, until one has Spontaneous Conviction. Furthermore, meditation and sincere involvement in spirituality, as well as complete trust and strong faith in the Master, are all necessary. As I told you earlier, after Spontaneous Conviction, all the activities remain untouched by, or unconcerned with, the illusory world.

So, all spiritual discussion is just like talking about the unborn child. Nothing has been happening and nothing is going to happen, and hence there is no need to refer to any spiritual book. There is no need to approach so many Masters, after the Conviction of Unidentified, Anonymous, Invisible Identity. My Sadguru, Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj, used to say, “How you were prior to beingness, and how you will be after leaving the food-body, remain like that.” Furthermore, avoid playing with the spiritual words. Avoid analyzing or debating the words, as language has been created only to enable conversation, and to share our thoughts.

I think I have tried my level best to convince the devotees. With regards and blessings to all.

Jai Sadguru!

OCTOBER 03, 2016, COLUMBIA, U.S.A.

“When happiness is no longer required, you have reached the destination.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

31. All Miraculous Experiences Appear Upon Your Presence

Maharaj: Meditation is the base. Though it is not Ultimate Truth, it is the base, the foundation, which is absolutely necessary until you have the Conviction of Selfless Self.

Literary knowledge and oral knowledge, will not help you, because you are holding this human body. Even though we are formless and shapeless, we started considering ourselves as body-forms. Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence is like the space or the sky. But that Conviction is missing. And, in order to have this Conviction, one should undergo intense meditation. Meditation is your base, your foundation. Don’t make excuses. Just do it!

The body is not tolerable. Body-based-knowledge is not tolerable. To make it tolerable, we resort to material things like power, money, and sex, and all sorts of other things. In them, we find temporary relief! To come out from these body-based concepts, meditation, and reciting the Mantra, are most important. Although the Mantra is a concept, these Sanskrit words have a lot of power. The efficacy of the Naam Mantra has been proven, time and time again, by our great lineage Masters, as well as by the immediate effects, often visible in the majority of seekers.

In the process of your meditation, involvement, and your strong devotion, sometimes miraculous experiences happen. They may be positive, or negative, miraculous experiences. I will give you an example from Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj. It will help your focus.

Early on, Nisargadatta Maharaj was very rich. He owned about ten shops. His finances were in very good shape, when in 1933, or so, he came across Siddharameshwar Maharaj. One of his friends took him to see Siddharameshwar Maharaj. At that time, he said, “I will not believe in any body-based Sage or Saint. I am not going to bow down to him”. But he went there, listened, and then experienced a miraculous inner change. His base was already solid. He was so deeply impressed, that he bowed down to Sri Siddharameshwar spontaneously. His association with Siddharameshwar, lasted for about three years.

I am describing Nisargadatta Maharaj’s experiences to help you focus on your devotional life. After 1939, or thereabouts, he left his routine life, and set out to experience the spiritual world. He faced so many unbearable problems. He left his family and everything else behind. He had numerous shops and apartments which were rented out, etc. But, he was driven to experience this spiritual knowledge. In the course of his spiritual adventure, he faced many negative experiences. He had no money, and he was wandering here and there, physically exhausted.

At one point, he found himself in some barren land where there was no water. There was nothing! Completely exhausted, he said he thought it was going to be the last moment of his life. But then, in that desolate, barren land, he could see a cottage, in the far distance.

Here, I am talking about devotional experiences, that appear when you are deeply involved in spirituality. Though it is not knowledge, and not Reality, this kind of miraculous incident does happen.

He had seen this cottage, and so, with great difficulty, went there. There was an old man there, who gave him some food, bread, and water. Soon after that, he left. After taking a few steps, he looked back. The cottage was nowhere to be seen. It had disappeared.

Nisargadatta Maharaj rarely gave us examples of his miraculous experiences. But I learned from him. After this experience, he wrote a poem: “My Master became a cottage for me. My Master became food for me. My Master became water for me”.

This can happen to anyone. Your Master can manifest in any shape or form, when you are in difficulty. But you must have strong faith, within yourself, and in your Master. When you have strong devotion and deep involvement, then this kind of miraculous experience can happen.

They can be positive or negative. “Negative experiences” mean that you will have some negative or depressive thoughts. There may be difficulties, just like in Nisargadatta Maharaj’s case, where he faced so many problems in his life, so many problems, beyond one’s imagination. But, he never ever lost his faith in his Master. His knowledge was very strong, exceptional, firm. He had total Conviction.

He had other positive, miraculous experiences, as well. He rarely talked about them, but one day, while he was sitting at his shop, he started pouring water from his teapot to passers-by. People started forming queues. It turned out that they were

being healed and cured by that water. But Siddharameshwar Maharaj warned him, “What are you doing? This is not knowledge. It is not Reality. It’s distracting you from Reality”. So he stopped doing this!

In this dialogue, what I am telling you, is that after a time spent in meditation, reciting the Mantra, and absorbing the knowledge, with strong devotion, there may be some miraculous experiences. It is not knowledge. It is not Reality. It is not Ultimate Truth. The point is that you could be distracted from Reality. If there is any ego still lurking, you may think, “Yes, she has had this miracle because of me”. Or, maybe when you are with someone, a miracle takes place. You may then think to yourself: “Oh, I have so much power!” Beware! This will inflate the ego even more. Be careful! Take precautionary measures in the process of your devotional spirituality.

If during your devotion, such experiences occur, do not give them too much importance. All miraculous experiences appear upon your Presence. That Presence, that Invisible Presence, Anonymous Presence, is Ultimate Truth. Miracles have no value. It is the nature of our human body, of the human being. If you see miracles performed in front of you, you may bow down and say, “Oh, you are a very great man.” But no one is performing those miracles. They are within you. You have tremendous power, but do not take on any ego around them. Nisargadatta Maharaj did not take any credit. He did not accept any prestige, “If it happens, it is because of my Master. I am not doing any miracles.” He never took on any ego.

The reason I am drawing your attention to this, is that because of your strong devotional life, these things may happen. Recognize them as progressive steps, and keep going. Don’t be caught by them. Do not indulge in them for long. Do not stop there, keep moving forward, climbing until you reach the mountain peak. Involve yourself in devotion and spirituality till Conviction. I am alerting you, making you cautious, in the process of your devotional life, your spirituality. Ignore these experiences – they are not Reality.

32. Power is Inbuilt in You

You will go through so many experiences, miraculous experiences, magical experiences. You may also get some power. It happens. But do not use, or misuse, that power. You have miraculous power, but that is not Ultimate Truth.

Power is also a by-product of your deep, spiritual involvement. You will feel it. And again, this may give the ego, the subtle ego an opportunity to enter again: “I have the power. I can do something”. That ego must be smashed to pieces, so that it does not have the opportunity to rear its head again.

Does anyone have any questions? Feel free to ask! Don’t worry! This is friendly chatting. I am not delivering spiritual lectures, and considering myself to be some “great spiritual Master”. Our bodies may differ, but the same Spirit is in us all.

Q: Maharaj, I have been doing different practices for many years, and different mantras come up in different contexts. That has been my practice, if you will. So, would you advise me now to just stick with one mantra, your Mantra?

Maharaj: Recite the Mantra that I have given you. It is said that this Mantra comes from Dattatreya. There is tremendous value, importance, power, energy with this Mantra. It creates some vibrations inside. When you are reciting the Naam Mantra, you will forget your body-identity. You will become one with the Mantra. What is the meaning of the Naam Mantra? “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. It is not referring to something else, something other. It is practical, it is your Reality. You have forgotten your Reality. You are reminding yourself of your Reality, so whatever mantra you have – it may be any mantra – some say Aham Brahmasmi, Shivoham, Soham, stay loyal to it.

33. The Master Appears

Maharaj: Until you have Conviction, until you remain untouched by the world, untouched by the body-based knowledge, you need to meditate! As I have already mentioned, during your meditation and involvement, you may encounter a few miraculous experiences.

Spiritual knowledge talks about three types of positive miraculous experiences that can occur: darshan, sparshan, and sambhashan. Darshan means that after having strong involvement in spirituality, you see your gods, goddesses, and Masters near you, and around you. You will get that sight, that transference of sight. Sparshan means that you will feel the touch of your Masters. Suppose you find yourself in some difficulty, you will feel them placing their hand on your head. Sambhashan means that sometimes, your Master, your God, is talking with you.

You will have some experiences. It is a fact, it happens. It is a sign of your strong devotion. Don’t be sidetracked by these experiences. The ego is bound to distract you, at any and every available opportunity. Nisargadatta once said, “Suppose you have some miraculous power. You may use it once or twice, but then, maybe the third time you use it, nothing will happen, and you will then despair.

You are a Master. You are already a Master. I am not telling you this for the sake of pleasing you. It is a fact that you have forgotten your identity, and therefore, the only thing I am doing is reminding you of That Identity, by inviting your attention to your Reality, and keeping you focussed on it all the time. That Invisible Listener within you is the Master of Masters. It is everywhere like the space or the sky. It is like the five elements – fire is everywhere, water is everywhere, sky is everywhere. You are the projector of the five elements, but you do not know it.

Take a dream-experience, for example. In a dream you see all the five elements. You see water, you see the sun, the moon, everything. Not only that, but you see yourself also. You are in deep sleep, but you are watching that dream, you are acting in that dream. Who has created that dream-world? Who is witnessing that dream-world? Who is experiencing that dream-world? Just think about it. It is the same thing here. Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence projected this entire world. If there is no awakening in the morning, who will talk about the world? Who will talk about all these Masters? Who will talk about God?

So, directly or indirectly, you are the base of this world. You are Ultimate Truth, you are Final Truth. You need not go anywhere to find the gods and the goddesses. Devote some time for meditation. This is the solution, the only solution. If we go on for hours together with dry knowledge, if you read so many books, visit so many Masters, you will only get temporary relief. Learn to concentrate on the Concentrator, the Invisible Concentrator.

The Listener and Speaker are one. Do not discriminate. Be with you all the time. Do not depend upon anyone else.

34. The Ball is in Your Court

Q: You talk about the spontaneous release of really strong emotions, and I have been experiencing that. I am wondering if that can also apply to physical symptoms?

Maharaj: Yes, yes, it happens. As you move closer and closer, to your Selfless Self, it happens. It is good, because you are experiencing those emotions.

Q: The emotions have been pretty intense sometimes, like rage coming out of nowhere, and lasting for half an hour, and then just subsiding. But it is the physical stuff that I was a little more perplexed about.

Maharaj: When one has strong involvement in spirituality, so many emotional feelings of love and affection appear spontaneously. This is part and parcel of your Spirit, of your spiritual knowledge, because you are full of love and affection. Exceptional peacefulness is there. With your strong devotion and meditation, there will be total peacefulness and total silence. No confusion, no confusion – all confusion will dissolve. There will be exceptional silence. You will remain untouched by the world.

Q: I have a broken body, Maharaj, I have a disease. I have an addiction to the medication for this disease, a broken back. I wake up in the morning, and I am in so much pain. The medication affects my meditation, but if I do not take the medication, then I am in so much pain. Will I succeed with the meditation? Can I do it?

Maharaj: Yes, you have to do it. Your tolerance and patience will increase. Since you are holding the body, the body is bound to have problems. There are physical, and mental problems, appearing. You will find some courage, power and energy to tolerate all these things. Not even that, I am telling you, you will overcome all the physical problems you have as well.

I will tell you a true story about Guru Ranade, a disciple of Bhausaheb Maharaj. About a hundred years back, Guru Ranade was suffering from tuberculosis, and in those days, TB was an incurable disease. His mother took him to see Bhausaheb Maharaj. After meditating, as he was instructed to do, Guru Ranade was surprised to find himself completely cured. Really, it was a miracle. This can happen to you because you have immense power. What I want to tell you, the principle behind this, is that you have tremendous power. Anything can happen, and you will find the courage to tolerate, all these body-based concepts, all these body-based problems.

And therefore, I am insisting, at the beginning stage, that you devote some time for meditation. It is very basic. Discussion alone is not sufficient. Now the ball is in your court. Meditate! Go deep within. Be self-involved, nothing more! There are no conditions or restrictions as to what you should eat or do. Just meditate!

Through the meditation, you will identify yourself in a real sense. All these concepts have appeared upon your Presence, bringing confusion. They have obscured your identity.

35. Devotion is Acceptance

Q: How do you increase your devotion? I mean, how does one become more devoted? If you find that you get distracted by the world, and then forget to meditate?

Maharaj: Accept the Reality. Reality is placed before you. It is the Reality of the Invisible Listener within you. When you accept this totally, that is devotion.

Your body is called a “woman”. Are you saying, “I am a woman, I am a woman, I am a woman”, all the time? Of course not. You accepted it. I say you are Brahman, but you are not accepting it. You say, “Oh, you must be making fun of me!”. I am placing before you the Listener’s Reality, but you are not accepting it. But when someone says something you do not like, you immediately accept it, and react. So it is now up to you, to accept the Reality that is placed before you.

Why go here, and there, in search of Masters? “Oh! God bless me, Oh! God bless me”. Why? To say “God” your Presence is required. If there is no Presence who will talk about “God”? Are you not the father of God, the mother of God? “God” is a concept. Okay, it is not bad. I am not criticizing that “God” concept. But if your Presence is not there, who will talk about the God? How can you talk about God and the Masters? The moment that Spirit clicked with the body, you started identifying the entire world. The entire world is projected out of your Presence. It is a fact.

And therefore, I keep insisting: To have this Spontaneous Conviction regarding your Selfless Self, you are to undergo the meditation. Again, I repeat, meditation is not only sitting. Be devoted to your meditation. Devotion means total involvement. If you recite the Mantra all the time, you will experience something miraculous. You will feel some exceptional peacefulness. Worldly things will be of no concern to you whatsoever.

36. No Hard and Fast Rules

Q: I have a technical question about the mantra. A person can recite the mantra, while breathing in and breathing out?

Maharaj: See, when you are sitting for meditation, at that time this principle [reciting the first half of the mantra along with the in-breath, and the second half along with the out-breath] is there. The rest of the time you can recite the mantra as it is. Be simple.

Q: So if I can do five...

Maharaj: Yes, no problem. Sit as per the instructions that have been given to you. As for the rest of the time, you can recite the Mantra as it is. Be normal. And even then, there is no hard and fast rule. This is the beginning stage, like when you are a student, learning a foreign language. You are told to write “a” like this, “b” like this, “c” like this. Then, after progressing through the various stages, you are no longer a student, you are a master of that particular language.

So, when you are sitting for meditation, sit in this fashion for half an hour, one hour, two hours or more, it depends on your daily routine. And if you recite the mantra along with your breathing it will have a greater effect. There will be more absorption. But throughout the rest of the day, you can recite the mantra as it is, not concentrating on the breathing, or sitting crossed-legged. Your meditation will, after some time, continue spontaneously within you. Unbeknown to you, even in deep sleep, that meditation will continue. You are at the initial stage, but, you still have to do it. No one can do it for you. Be practical!

37. Physical Needs Have Nothing to do With Reality

Q: Does a certain type of diet help calm your mind? Like a vegetarian or sattvic diet? Not too many spices?

Maharaj: No, there is no question of diet. It is not a concern. Your physical needs have nothing to do with Reality. Whatever you eat, whatever you do, whatever you like to make the body feel good, whatever your requirements, is of no concern to your Presence, or Spirit. Whether you eat vegetarian or non-vegetarian food, is of no concern. It is nobody’s concern! You are not the body. Give the body what it needs, and what it wants, in moderation. Whether you drink pure water or tap water, is of no concern. Identifying yourself is the only concern you need have. That is of paramount importance!

The questions keep coming because you have so many concepts. Meditate and bring an end to all this illusion. Clear out the clutter!

Q: What about Yoga asanas? Is it just another body-based concept then?

Maharaj: Yoga is good for health. It will help you. Pranayama, for example, has some good effects. There are various types of yoga: padmasana can also bring some good effects. Yoga can help you.

38. The Mantra is a Concept

Q: There is a lot of chaos and drama in my family during the course of the day, and I am trying to repeat the Mantra during all this drama, because in Reality there is really nobody there.

Maharaj: Correct, correct.

Q: I just want to be clear: I don’t have to focus on the in-breath or out-breath, while I am repeating the Mantra during the day? As long as I am aware and repeating the Mantra, that is all I have to do?

Maharaj: Correct! And remember that the Mantra is to be used only at the initial stage, until you have Conviction. At the Ultimate stage, it is not necessary to recite the Mantra, or do any practice. It will happen spontaneously.

What is a mantra? It is a reminder of your true identity, and helps you to identify yourself. Where was that mantra prior to beingness? Was there a mantra when you came into this world? Will there be a mantra after you leave the body? The mantra is also a concept. It is illusion. Having said that, you have to do it in the beginning. There is no way round this.

Q: Maharaj, I do have one question. I know you said choose one mantra, and stick with that. What I am finding, is that I am equally drawn to two. The Naam Mantra, because I received it from you, and also, “I am Brahman, Brahman I am”. I am doing one quite intensely for a week, and then I switch to the other one. I can’t seem to decide.

Maharaj: You have taken the Naam Mantra?

Q: Yes.

Maharaj: Recite the Naam Mantra only. It has the same meaning. Don’t confuse yourself!

Q: Okay, thank you. So I will stick with that one.

OCTOBER 17, 2016, COLUMBIA, U.S.A.

“Meditation will bring silence, and end the mind’s violence.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

39. Slowly, Silently, Permanently

Maharaj: After Realization, after Spontaneous Conviction, you will be completely calm and quiet. Whatever happens, you will remain calm and quiet throughout. There will be exceptional tolerance and bliss. All your desires will vanish. There will be no desires, no mind, no ego, and no intellect. It will happen spontaneously.

You will become completely free. Even though you are using this body, either as a male or female, you will remain detached. You will live in alertness, knowing that the body is temporary. And you will use it, as you might use an instrument.

For you to say: “I understand that I am not the body”, is intellectual understanding. And that is not enough. Meditation is the basic thing. You have to devote some time to meditation. “Some time” means, at least one hour! Allot at least one hour out of 24 for meditation, during which time, you are trying to identify the Unidentified Identity within you. It is only through the meditation process, that the Reality will be totally absorbed within you.

Through the Naam Mantra you are hammering yourself. Slowly, silently, and permanently, all your desires, expectations and needs, will miraculously dissolve. You will be completely free, completely free, completely silent, silent, silent.

Intellectual understanding is insufficient, because everything is within you. You cannot identify yourself in a real sense without using the tool, or medium of meditation. Spirituality, Reality, is not separate from you.

Some people come here, and say, “I have been practising spirituality for thirty or forty years”. There is some subtle ego there: “I have been doing this or that”. You are not the doer! There is no deed! Nothing is there. So, at the first stage, this bodily identity must dissolve, totally and spontaneously. It will happen. Nothing is impossible. You will find the courage to let go of the known, and dive into the unknown. There is nothing to fear, the Master is protecting you.

You have been playing with the spiritual words: Atman, Paramatman, thousands of words. You have been playing at being “spiritual beings”. This is a waste of time. Maybe you have a lot of knowledge. Maybe you are a master of knowledge. That’s okay. But, you still do not know who you are. You have not identified yourself with this knowledge. It has not enabled you to identify yourself. It has only given you intellectual stimulation, and a spiritual massage. You can become an Einstein in the spiritual field, but that will not stop your fear and trembling on your deathbed.

You are formless Presence. You were formless Presence. You will remain as formless Presence. Dissolve the concepts of “death” and “birth”. Dissolve all the desires. It will happen. We have many subtle, subtle desires. Therefore, instead of studying spirituality, try to digest that spirituality within you. It is not separate from you. As long as we continue to count ourselves as the body-forms, spirituality will appear to be different from us, separate from us. When spirituality is absorbed, at that stage, there will be no “I”, “you”, “he”, or “she” -there will be nothing there!

40. Read Your Story

Q: Should I stop reading Selfless Self, or Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj’s books? Is it best to stop all reading at some point?

Maharaj: Do not stop reading! You can read these spiritual books, but read them, as if you were reading your own biography. Read it, as your own story! When you are reading books by different Masters: Nisargadatta Maharaj, Siddharameshwar, etc, read them in this way. They all use their own unique style of language, but ultimately, they convey the same message: “Except for Selfless Self, there is no other God”.

There are many spiritual books out there, describing the different bodies, subtle, causal, this and that body... Where were these bodies prior to beingness? Why concern yourself with all these “bodies”? The principle behind spiritual knowledge, is that this body belongs to the five elements. You are the projector of these five elements. Where were these five elements prior to beingness? The sky is there, the earth, the wind, sun and light. So, these five elements came along with the body. Where were the five elements prior to beingness? Will you know about these elements, after beingness? There will not be anything there. Nothing will be there.

All the knowledge, whatever knowledge you have, will dissolve along with the body. So, why play with the words? All spiritual words are only indicators, that invite the attention of the Invisible Listener, that you are Ultimate Truth.

41. What You See is Illusion, That Through Which You See is Reality

Maharaj: There is no form. Was there a form prior to beingness? We do not know the answer to the question “Who am I?” To say “I am”, some Presence is needed. Where was that “I” prior to beingness? That Conviction – and I am not just talking understanding – that Conviction is supposed to appear spontaneously. And, as I keep telling you, this can only happen with strict meditation. It is the base. There is no need for any kind of asceticism. There is no need to visit temples or Masters. Approach your own, Inner Master. You are neglecting your own Master because you are measuring that Master in the body-form.

Knowledge is everywhere. That is called Realization. It is Unidentified, Invisible, Anonymous Identity. There is no name. You can’t see it, but you will feel it. What you see is illusion. That through which you see is Reality. The entire world is projected out of the Invisible Seer within you. You need a big dose of spiritual courage to accept the Reality.

42. There is Fire Everywhere

Maharaj: There are thousands of questions. The answer is within you. There is only one answer: Except your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman. They are all concepts which appear upon your Presence. Even “I am Brahman” is a concept, which appears upon your Presence. Presence does not know “I am Presence”. So, instead of studying spirituality, try to absorb what you have listened to, so far. It is the Listener’s story, the Listener’s identity. This body is an opportunity for you. Do not waste time. It is invaluable, your Presence is invaluable. Through the body you can identify that “I”.

A combination of Presence, and the body is needed. When Presence touched with the body, you said “I”. This combination is like that of a matchbox and stick. When the two make contact, you can see the fire.

Be practical! You have a lot of theory. You are not required to study any spiritual books. “The five elements, the four bodies” – why concern yourself with all of this theory – the “four bodies”, and all the rest of it? “Consciousness”, “unconsciousness”, “awareness” – this is only word-play. It will not give you happiness. It is momentary, spiritual entertainment. You are separate from the five elements. When your Presence appears, the whole world is projected, including the five elements. You are the father and mother of the five elements.

43. Why Fill Your Pockets?

Maharaj: We have so many desires. “I want this, that, and the other thing”. Human beings don’t come to the world with any pockets. They do not leave the body with pockets either. Therefore, why fill your pockets in between?

This means that prior to beingness, there was nothing. Now there is so much anxiety, greed and hedonism, for want of a better word: “I want this. I want that”. Who wants all these things, and what do you want them for? How long do you imagine you are going to use all these things? You are after money, sex, power and many other material wants. These are all temporary solutions to alleviate your unease. They offer only a brief respite from body-knowledge discomfort.

Q: The Conviction, the Spontaneous Conviction, can happen at any time. It does not necessarily happen during meditation. Is that correct?

Maharaj: It happens spontaneously. After Conviction, all the body-based-knowledge dissolves. It is very, very interesting. Go deep and deep and deep within Selfless Self, and you will find peacefulness, “Oh! I Am That!”

Q: Deeper and deeper into meditation?

Maharaj: After meditating, using these sacred words, all the concepts will melt. Your body-identity will be dissolved. And you will see within yourself, “My beingness is everywhere, and in every being. My Presence is everywhere”. That Spontaneous Conviction will appear within you.

44. Whatever Experience Appears is Illusion

Q: So during the course of the day, when all these family members are around...

Maharaj: Yes, yes, it’s okay. There are many family members around in a dream also.

Q: They are not really there, right?

Maharaj: [Maharaj smiles] I am not asking you to neglect your family members. But at the same time, there should be the Conviction that, “I am nothing to do with all these things”, as if you are acting in some drama. I will give you a little example: You are acting in a drama, playing a role. You are playing a very nice role. Everyone is very impressed. But at the same time, you know that “I am nothing to do with this role. I only have to act for two or three hours”. Convince yourself in this way! Knowledge is there, a lot of knowledge is there. In the light of that knowledge of Reality, you have to convince yourself.

Q: I have noticed that since reciting the Naam Mantra, I have become more inwardly focused, and much quieter. I am still able to take care of my duties, but I am very detached, and much more efficient. It seems like my energy is more inside, much more at peace. So it has been a good experience. I think I understand a little bit of what you are talking about. I don’t know about Spontaneous Conviction, but there has been a big switch, a big change since being given the Naam Mantra.

Maharaj: As long as we are measuring ourselves in the body-form, whatever experiences appear are illusion. If you feel “I am Brahman”, it is also illusion. Whatever feelings you have, appear upon your Presence, and are, therefore, illusory.

45. Presence is a Prerequisite

Q: I came across the teachings of Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj about ten years ago. It had an impact on my beingness, but I wasn’t really able to handle it. So over the last ten years, I have mainly practised on the Sufi path. The teacher was familiar with the lineage of Sri Ramakrishna also. Last year I came back to reading Sri Nisargadatta, as well as your wonderful book, Maharaj.

Maharaj: After reading so many books, we need to absorb that knowledge. Knowledge is just Reality, your Reality, the Listener’s Reality, the Reader’s Reality. That “I” must dissolve.

That “I” appeared upon your Spontaneous Presence. If Presence were not there, who will talk about the “I”? And as I told you, except your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, no Master. The Invisible Listener within you is the Master. It does not have any special identity. To say “I”, your Presence is required. If Presence were not there, who will talk about that “I” and who will talk about “God”? To say “God”, your Presence is required. The body can’t say, “this is God”. If there is no Presence, the body can’t act. This is a dead body. The Invisible Presence, the Invisible Listener within you, is that through which you can identify the world. That means the entire world is projected out of your Invisible Presence. If Presence were not in the body, who will talk about the world, and God, and everything?

Who knows Krishna? Prior to beingness, did you know Krishna? Did you know of any God? Did you know any Master? Did you have any spiritual knowledge? Nothing. And after leaving the body, of what use will Krishna be to you? All gods and goddesses are concepts. I am not criticizing those concepts. However, I am placing before you the Invisible Identity within you, which is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Krishna, or whatever name is given to That nameless identity.

Presence is a prerequisite. One cannot say “Lord Krishna” without the power of your Presence. If your Presence were not there, who will talk about Lord Krishna? We know the picture, “Oh, this is Lord Krishna”. Somebody told us, or we saw it in some book, that “this is God, this is Rama, this is Krishna, this is something else” But prior to beingness, did you know anything about all this? Be clear! After leaving the body will you know anything about these divinities? Will you know anything about any Master, or God?

We are using the body to identify these gods and goddesses. Instead, try to identify the Invisible Reader within you. We are collecting information through the books. This information is not going to help you to know yourself. Don’t keep reading, reading. Don’t keep on visiting the Masters, without absorbing what they are trying to convey. What is their message? It is that there is nothing except your Selfless Self. There is no other God, but you.

We are trying to identify God through the body-form. What is the use of this God? In order for us to have some peace, we visit temples and churches. We pray to the gods!

Body-based-knowledge is not tolerable, and that is why we need these gods and goddesses.

Try and see the Master within you. Why don’t you see that Krishna within you? Because your body-identity is in the way. Why is meditation required? Again, I will say, because through meditation, you are hammering yourself, you are inviting the attention of the Invisible Meditator within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. You are Final Truth. That is the base. This is your foundation.

46. We Love Ourselves the Most

Maharaj: You are to undergo some meditation. That is most important for you. Do you have a Master? Have you had a Master previously?

Q: When I was sixteen years old I met a man, and he taught me how to play the tabla. He told me about Sri Ramakrishna. I lived with his family for a little while, and then, after that, he directed me to the Vivekananda Vedanta Society. And after that, I met some other teachers, too.

Probably one of the most important teachers was from the Sufi lineage. He was also very familiar with other lineages. And then, of course, reading the works of Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj. But I feel that all of this has led me to you, Maharaj. When you say that this is the final destination, I believe it emphatically, with all my heart. What you teach, and what you are saying about who we are is the final destination. I feel I do not need to go anywhere, anymore. Even if I had not had the opportunity to meet you, I would still feel that way.

Q2: I think you have just expressed a lot of our feelings in here. After decades of searching, to finally know, “Here is my Master”. It is just such a blessing.

Maharaj: Constant meditation is most important. Any words will do: Aham Brahmasmi, Shivoham - through which you are inviting the attention of the Invisible Concentrator within you. This is the beginning stage. You already have all the basic knowledge. You have read I Am That, you have read Selfless Self, and through them you have spiritual understanding. After reading the books, absorb that knowledge. It will happen spontaneously within you, because you are the source of this world. Your Spontaneous Invisible Presence is the projector of this world. If there is no Seer, who will talk about the seen? It is very, very simple and clear.

Q: I have been thinking about what questions I would ask you when I saw you, but not many questions came to mind. As I said before, your words are so clear in the book Selfless Self. My only question would be to ask you – and for this I would be eternally grateful – if I might receive the Naam Mantra from you, to help dissolve the body-knowledge that you talk about, and to strengthen the Conviction even more so.

Maharaj: I will give the Naam Mantra to you. But you must follow it strictly. There should not be a wavering mind.

Whatever you have listened to, and read so far, absorb it, digest it – that is number one. Secondly, you must have the Conviction, that “I was not the body, I am not the body, and I am not going to remain the body”. That Conviction will appear spontaneously. How will it appear? It will appear after continuous meditation.

After Conviction, you will not be affected by things so much. You will be more detached. At the moment, feelings are there, sometimes very strong feelings are there, because of all our relations and relationships, which we have given so much importance to, and taken for reality.

“My father”, “my mother”, “my husband”, “my child”, it is okay, it happens. It is natural because we have had a long association with the body, so that if something bad happens to our loved ones, we feel sorry, very sorry. But because we have so much love and affection for the body, we seem to love ourselves more than our relatives.

Do you know the story of the monkey and her infant? There is a flood, so a monkey and her infant are forced to climb up a tree. As the water continues to rise, the monkey tries to climb further up the tree. Eventually, she can’t climb any further. She tries to lift the infant above the water, but the water reaches up, up, and up. Finally, she becomes desperate, and stands on the infant. It is a terrible story! The point is that you have that instinct of self-preservation, for your body, that trumps everything else.

47. I am Sharing This Knowledge With the Grace of My Master

Q: Maharaj, you said in the book, Selfless Self that Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj taught you, or showed you, how to read the Dasbodh book. But you never said what he taught you, or how he taught you how to read.

Maharaj: Ah, yes, I used to go every day to Nisargadatta Maharaj’s house. The regular reader was not there, so, my Master, asked me to read the Dasbodh. I was reading it with a very quiet voice, so he said, “Your voice should be able to reach the ears of ten thousand people!”

He taught me many things. What I am today, I am, because of him alone. My whole education and everything was due to him. He always gave practical advice. One evening, when I was at Maharaj’s place, he asked me what I was doing, and whether I had a job, or if I intended to pursue further education? I did not know how to reply to him.

He asked me, “What do you mean by spirituality? Touching the Master’s feet? Placing garlands on the Master?

Clapping? This is not spirituality. Do something in life. Why don’t you join the college?”

I was not in a position to join the college because of some financial problems, but he insisted, “Enrol at the college! Do not come to me! Do not bring any garlands! Do not bring any prasad!” Coincidentally, one of Sri Nisargadatta’s senior devotees was also the Registrar of a nearby college. So, Maharaj asked him, “Take this boy into your college!” It was with great difficulty that I joined college, as I had previously received very low marks in my exams. He used to say, “Do something! You should continue learning until the age of forty”. And so, I continued my education until I was forty years old.

My Master treated me just like his child. My college graduation, my law graduation, all these degrees belong to Maharaj.

And with the grace of my Master, I am sharing this knowledge with everybody. And, I am saying the same thing to you that Siddharameshwar used to say: If you are Realized, make others Realized. Spread your rug or mat, and start sharing the knowledge. But on no account, commercialize it. Why should you ask for money? It is free knowledge. This knowledge is free knowledge. It is your innate knowledge.

OCTOBER 26, 2016, COLUMBIA, U.S.A.

“God only exists because your Presence is there first. If there is no Presence, who can talk about God? God is your baby.”

Sri Sadguru Ramakant Maharaj

48. In the Beginning, There is Bound to be a Struggle

Q: I struggle with so many distractions when I meditate. I sit there, and I do not want to meditate.

Maharaj: Concentrate on the meditation. Meditation is the only medium, through which all your concepts will dissolve. In the beginning, there is bound to be a struggle. As I have told you, the mind, the ego, and the intellect, and a lot of concepts, will rebel against you.

There is a nice example given by Nisargadatta Maharaj. Suppose you own a property, and you have several tenants living there. You want to regain possession of the rooms, so

you ask them to leave. While leaving the premises, the tenants will start to abuse you, because they have been staying there for so many years. If suddenly you say, “I want possession of the premises”, they will abuse you.

It is the same thing here. There have been many, many concepts since your childhood days. After some prolonged meditation, the bad elements, or the bad concepts, will rebel against you. This story is just for understanding purposes. Don’t take anything that I say literally!

Some unsettling things may happen, but understand, that this is a cleaning process. It does not have any spiritual importance, but it will happen in the beginning. When the seeker/devotee takes the Naam Mantra for meditation, there are some forces at work, trying to distract you from the Reality. It may be your mind, ego, or the intellect. All the while, they have been using your energy, and consequently, have made us their slaves. You have given so much importance to the mind. “Don’t go against my mind…!” The subtle ego is strong, and the subtle intellect. Be the Master of the mind, ego, and intellect.

Do not struggle with your thoughts. Do not struggle with your mind!

49. Stop All This Thinking. Be Totally Blank!

Q: When I get to this place of feeling presence, the concepts drop and I just feel this pure experiencing, where there is this confusion and a lost feeling. And there is some resistance that comes, and I can be like that for maybe five minutes, ten minutes, some length of time where I feel like I can’t function in the world. And then there is some part of me that is scared, that doesn’t want to lose its individuality or identity, because it can’t even fathom that. And then suddenly I go, “Wow”, and I come back to “I’ve just got to be this person and do my thing”.

I feel like I have gotten to that place so many times, but then this resistance comes. It is almost like there wants to be some bargaining, “Can I just hold onto a little piece?”

Maharaj: You are experiencing all these things. This is the struggle of your thoughts, of your concepts. And you know the struggles that are going on inside. All these struggles appear upon your Presence. Prior to beingness, there was no struggle. This struggle appears upon your Presence because of that concept, “I am somebody”. So, do not fight with the concepts, do not fight with the mind, do not struggle with the mind. Thoughts are coming, and going. You are scared of letting go of the concept, “I am somebody” because you are attached to this illusion. It is all you know. That is why meditation is needed, to reduce the power these concepts have over you.

Therefore, meditation is most important. Meditation plays a very good part. In the beginning, you have to undergo the meditation, and then all your concepts will be dissolved. You will remain unconcerned with all the thoughts, untouched by the whole world. Because, except your Selfless Self, nothing is there. All these concepts, body-based concepts, appear upon your Presence. These are layers. You are experiencing all these concepts. “Why am I experiencing so many things here?” – these are layers upon your Presence, and they will be cleared away with meditation. Meditation gives you courage to control all these things. It will happen spontaneously. Nothing is impossible for you. You have become a victim of your own concepts.

Q: Yeah, like even right now...

Maharaj: Be strong! Have some courage – You can do it! Do not underestimate yourself! When the Master says, “You are Brahman”, you are Brahman, so live like Brahman, not like a man or woman. It is open fact, it is Reality. Forget everything, and be with you. The Master is not separate from you. God is not separate from you.

Q: Even right now, I can feel the resistance. I mean, I feel presence and I feel resistance, and I just have this little awareness that this resistance is a game, just like it is a game.

Maharaj: Stop all this thinking. Be totally blank!

Q: Yes, that is the part that scares me.

Maharaj: Be as you were prior to beingness. Were there any thoughts there? Are you a woman or a man? After leaving the body, do all these thoughts remain? Nothing remains! Why struggle with the thoughts? Why struggle with the concepts?

Try to absorb this Reality, that is already within you. Be bold, have some courage. I am placing before you the facts of your existence, your Reality, the Listener’s Reality, not the Reality of Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, or Master. Live like a Master, live like a God. It is your identity.

You have supernatural power, tremendous power, miraculous power, but you are not using it. With courage, you can overcome any problem whether it is physical, mental or spiritual. All your problems will be resolved.

50. There is No Waking, and There is No Sleeping

Q: For me, I find that the Mantra itself is very easy, and it is something I can slip into and stay focused with. I mean, I could do it all day, but what I have discovered is that very quickly the body becomes energetically unsettled, and I do not sleep well. My sleep becomes very restless, and eventually I just get too tired to function and have to stop, take a break for a few days, and let everything equalize.

So what I am trying to find – you call the Mantra the prescription – and what I am trying to find, is the right dosage for me. So, is it half an hour a day, and then I take a break, or is it an hour? But then I find myself getting sucked in, and end up doing three hours, and then I am not sleeping well.

Maharaj: Don’t count the hours!

Q: Well I don’t specifically, but I kind of generally.

Maharaj: The Mantra will dissolve the egoistic “I”. That “I” is to dissolve. That is its purpose.

Q: Yeah, but right now the “I” doesn’t like not sleeping.

Maharaj: Because you are measuring yourself in the body-form. There is no waking, and there is no sleeping. There is no consciousness, and there is no unconsciousness. All concepts are related to the body only. Prior to beingness, was there any sleep? Was there any waking? Was there any consciousness? There were no concepts, and no “I”.

Q: You talk about spiritual courage.

Maharaj: You must have courage to accept the Reality. Have strong faith in yourself, and in your Master.

Q: When I take a break from the Mantra, I just kind of be with the “I am”…

Maharaj: Why take a break from the Mantra? These words are always alerting you to the illusory concepts. They are reminding your Selfless Self. So, recite the Mantra until you have Spontaneous Conviction, “I was not the body, I am not the body, I am not going to remain the body”. After Spontaneous Conviction, there will not be any concepts that will have any power over you. Nothing will impress you, or depress you!

51. The Great Saint is Within You!

Maharaj: I am not asking you to continuously say “Ram, Ram, Ram”, or spend hours reciting the mantra. Try to have Conviction. Accept the fact, the Reality within you. This body was once a child, then it became a young man, and eventually, it will be an old man. Is this your Reality?

Who is going, and who is coming? Who is taking birth, and who is dying? All these concepts are related to the body only. And as you know, you were not the body at all, you are not the body at all.

We are not here to criticize or to get involved in criticism. This is not a debate, we are not trying to prove anything. But practical spirituality is most important. Practical spirituality means what? That knowledge, that Reality is supposed to be absorbed totally within you. At that moment, you will forget the entire world. You will be untouched by the world. Though you are living in this world, you are untouched by the world. You are unconcerned with the world. All relations, everything came along with the body only.

Everything will dissolve along with the body. This means that everything came out of nothing, and everything will dissolve within nothing. In between, you feel that “I am something”. That “something” is supposed to dissolve.

After Conviction, you will be totally fearless. Problems will be there, but your problems will be reduced, dissolved, and you will take them in a light fashion. So, be strong, and have the courage to accept the Reality. Satsang alone is not sufficient. If you listen to so many Masters, and attend numerous different satsangs, it is pointless! [Maharaj shakes his head]. Have satsang with yourself! You have to please your Self. Please your Self! The Saint is not separate from you. The Master is not separate from you. The Great Saint is within you. There is no Saint except your Selfless Self. There is no Master except your Selfless Self. So, stop measuring yourself in the body-form. Beyond that, there is nothing. This is the Reality. It is Ultimate Truth, Final Truth. Try to absorb, what you have listened to so far.

Do not ignore your responsibilities. This is a human body, so you need to live as a human. Don’t be inhuman! Show love and affection to your family members, and take care of them.

We know ourselves through the body, “I am somebody”. The body is the medium, not Ultimate Truth. It is a food-body. As long as you are supplying food and water, it will grow. Be loyal to yourself, and be faithful to yourself, and your Master. But the Master is not in any form. He is a formless Master.

Strong involvement is necessary. It is often said that when we come into this world, we do not bring anything, and that when we leave this world, we do not take anything with us. It is a common statement. Why, therefore, become a victim of all these concepts? “Mind”, “ego”, “intellect”, so many chakras are there, kundalini, etc, so many words are available. What chakra? What kundalini? What deed? What karma or destiny?

We are under the pressure of so many concepts. Where were all these concepts prior to beingness? Who knows what “karma” is? Who knows what “religion” is? Prior to beingness, was there any religion? Prior to beingness, what religion did you belong to? Did you know anything about the gods or the goddesses? We do not know ourselves. What will happen after leaving the body? All the same questions are asked, again and again. “What is the next birth after death going to be?” What birth is there? Who knows? So, do not become a slave of your own concepts.

Meditation and spiritual knowledge give you the courage to live happily. Whatever pain and misery may be there in this life, can be overcome through the meditation.

52. Where Everything Ends, There You Are

Q: When I sit for meditation, I sit deliberately to concentrate and focus. And for the rest of the day, I just try to repeat the Naam in the background. I feel like I am making some progress with that, but I want that courage.

You tell me I am Brahman, and I believe you. What does my body need to do, to convince itself to get the Conviction? Because I’m there, I am ready, but letting go… It just seems that whenever I am about ready to let go, somebody else comes at me with another problem, and I bounce back into the dream, instead of focussing on Reality.

Maharaj: Be normal! There are so many things around you. Whether to take the touch, or not, is up to you. Accept the sting, or don’t accept the sting! You are your own Master. There are a lot of thoughts flowing inside, and you are watching all these thoughts. Do not respond, to each, and every thought. It is the nature of the mind, the nature of the body. The thoughts are flowing.

Where all thoughts end, there you are. Where everything ends, there you are. Where were all these thoughts prior to beingness? Will there be any thoughts after leaving the body? Will there be any fighting, struggle or chaos? No, there will not be anything!

Directly or indirectly, we have accepted “I am the body”, “I am somebody”, “I am doing this thing, I am doing that thing”, “I am a devotee”, “I am a disciple”, “I am a Master”, “I am Brahman”, and all these things. That “I am” must go! That concept “I am” appeared upon your Spontaneous, Invisible Presence, and Presence does not know that, “I am Presence”. It is just like the space or the sky, everywhere. The five elements do not know “I am the five elements”. Water does not know “I am water”. The earth does not know “I am earth”. The sky does not know, “I am sky”. You are the Projector of the five elements. When the Spirit clicks with the body, the five elements are projected. The entire world is projected. You are the father of this world, you are the mother of this world.

All these concepts have appeared upon your Invisible Presence, where there is no pain and no pleasure. Body-knowledge is not tolerable, therefore pain is there. This is a food-body. Prior to beingness, and after leaving the body, there is no pain, and no pleasure. Does a dead body have any pleasure or pain? No! That means: You were not the body, you are not the body, you are not going to remain the body. So you ask, “Then who am I?” It is called Brahman, Atman, Paramatman, God, Master, that you are, the Supernatural Power. These are only words. You are beyond words.

Q: So, I can do my duties, my family duties, be the mom, the wife, and the glue, actually, that holds the family together, and makes them all stand upright, and at the same time, simultaneously, I can detach and watch this as a dream. In other words, do my duty, but pull back, and watch it more as a dream. I guess it is about giving myself acceptance not to be the pillar for everyone around me, and that is where the lack of courage is. It is just frustrating getting pulled back into that dream when you really don’t want to be there. And just when you think, “Oh!” somebody has got another problem and something else for you to solve. And that is where I find the difficulty for me comes. I didn’t sleep for a while and was exhausted. But now I go to sleep reciting the Naam, and I do not have any more problems.

Maharaj: In the beginning it happens. It is a cleaning process. All the concepts are being eliminated. Your so-called mind, ego, and intellect are stinging you, pricking you from the backside. That internal force is trying to distract you from the Reality. It happens in the beginning. Because, directly or indirectly, we have a lot of body-concepts. It will take some time.

But do not ignore your family responsibilities. We are human beings. Spirituality is not a restriction, a bondage, or a blockage. Don’t just say “I am Brahman, I am Brahman, Brahman, Brahman”. Who will give you food while you say, “I am Brahman”? You need to attend to your duties, and responsibilities, but at the same time, there should be Conviction.

53. You Are Ultimate Truth

Maharaj: Now you can ask any question that you want. Am I the only one talking? This is chatting, spiritual chatting. I am not here to give dry lectures on spirituality.

Q: I still experience pleasure and pain.

Maharaj: Pleasure and pain are connected with the body. Where was that pleasure and pain prior to beingness? After leaving the body, who will know anything about pleasure and pain? So long as we are holding this human body, we will be connected with pleasure and pain. But, there is no pleasure and no painfulness.

Q: Maharaj, for the last couple of years with my sadhana, nothing has given me more pleasure, than just abiding as awareness or presence. And the positive benefits of the sadhana have been that it has become a lot easier. There are the synchronicities and coincidences, and there are no problems really, more so, just challenges. Life has become a lot simpler. But on the flip side, my aim has been to try and extend the duration of my sadhana. So it used to be about an hour and a half, now it is two hours, and I am trying to step it up. But it takes my whole day to get that two hours, and I enjoy this more than anything else.

Maharaj: It is not necessary to meditate for one or two hours. One minute is sufficient for you! I am advising meditation. What is the purpose of meditation? You are inviting the attention of the Invisible Meditator within you, that you are Ultimate Truth. Except your Selfless Self, nothing is there. That Conviction is supposed to appear spontaneously. No special sadhana is required. Sitting for one hour, two hours, ten hours, has no meaning. One moment is sufficient. That “I am” is to dissolve! Behind what you are doing, behind that deed, there is some base there, a trace of “I am”: “I am somebody”, “I am doing sadhana”, “I am a devotee”. Dissolve that “I am”.

Q: Maharaj, I call it sadhana, but it is really...

Maharaj: Okay, I can understand. I am not blaming you. It happens in every case. But I say sadhana is not necessary. What you have learned, what you have listened to through various sources, try to absorb it totally. It is an open fact, that except your Selfless Self, there is no God. What is the purpose of sadhana? What is the purpose of devotion? What is the purpose of meditation? What do you want to achieve? What is the goal? What is Ultimate Truth? What is Final Truth? You are Final Truth. You are Ultimate Truth.

Encouragement From Sri Ramakant Maharaj NOVEMBER 2, 2016

Jai Guru,

After strong involvement in spirituality through meditation, a flow of illusory concepts, will appear upon your Spontaneous Invisible Presence, and instantly disappear. Continue with your normal spiritual practice, which will result in all the concepts vanishing, including Brahman.

How were you prior to beingness? There was no experiencer, no experience, and no witness. Though you are living with the body, you will remain unconcerned with the illusory world. There will be complete peacefulness, happiness, and fearlessness; no feelings of existence, and hence no confusion. All identities will disappear, including mind, ego, and intellect, which is miraculous, and cannot be expressed in words. In brief, you are very close to the top of the spiritual mountain, so do not look back, and do not share whatever is happening in your spiritual life.

Your Spontaneous Presence is everywhere, just like the sky or the space, where there is no individuality, where experience and the experiencer dissolve or disappear. No body-essence remains. I think that you no longer require excessive practice or sadhana, because Ultimate Truth or Reality has been absorbed within you. Do not pay attention to whatever is happening, or not happening, in this illusory world. Whatever I have conveyed to you for your spirituality is enough.

When you have strong devotion, your crazy mind rebels against you, to distract you from your Reality. Do not struggle with the mind. That good or bad thoughts are flowing, is just the nature of the mind. Do not pay so much attention to your mind, ego, and intellect. As you know, so many unpleasant incidents happen in your life, but with your strong spiritual willpower you can overcome all these problems. Furthermore, with the blessings of Sadguru, your “so many unpleasant problems” are solved miraculously. What more do you want? Sadguru krupa is always with you.

Why worry? Be normal, be simple, be humble, be always with you. Concentrate deeply and fully in meditation. Continue reciting the Naam Mantra. Be peaceful, be tension-free, be happy, be fearless all the time. In this human life, there is more pain and less pleasure. Almost all the spiritual saints face a lot of problems, but with their strong devotional power, they overcome all their unpleasant situations. Do not be a slave of your mind!

With your strong devotion and faith in Sadguru, you can easily control your mind, ego, and intellect. Sadguru bhakti has strong shakti power.

With blessings to all,

Jai Sadguru!

PART THREE How The Master Changed My Life

***

Hopefully, my testimony will inspire sincere seekers around the world, as so many of us have lost faith because of the hardships of life. My greatest encounter in this existence is Sri Ramakant Maharaj. Finally, I came face to face with the knower of all hearts manifesting Himself in a physical body. Having received the Naam Mantra felt like the detonation of the atomic consciousness inside of me.

My seeking came to an end. The supposedly heavy cloud hanging around my head, started to dissolve slowly, but surely. My power and faith was regenerated. It is a matter of great grace and merit to come across such a rare one.

There are many mystical experiences from the meditation – colourful and bright light! The circumstances around me suddenly became very favourable – from having no job, I am now doing the job of my dreams, and my physical health is improving a lot.

***

After seeking for about twenty years, I came across Maharaj’s teachings, and the book, Selfless Self. It truly had such an impact on me, but for some time, there was also quite a resistance to it, especially the Mantra and the Bhajans! I was so “stuffed” with concepts from so much reading, that it took a while for the “dissolving” process to allow the humbleness that was needed, to truly embrace Maharaj’s words. The teachings have impacted my “illusory” life in so many ways, especially that there is no longer any drama or conflicts at all. Having total trust and faith in Maharaj, and the teachings is just essential. I can honestly say I feel this sense of “me” dissolving more each day. Bhajans, Mantra meditation and reading Selfless Self is truly a way of life for me now. There is nothing more important! And, because of this, all my “duties” get done effortlessly, in such a natural way. My gratitude to Maharaj is beyond words.

What is unique about Sri Ramakant Maharaj? He is not just another teacher or Master, offering his own brand of knowledge. He has no intention of filling our heads with knowledge! Quite the opposite, in fact. He is here to remove all the illusory knowledge that we have accumulated over a lifetime, so that the light of Self can shine once more. The process is one of subtraction, not addition. When I met Sri Ramakant Maharaj, I knew that “I” had reached the end of the road, and entered into Reality, that has no beginning, and no end: Ultimate Reality, Ultimate Truth – I Am That, without saying it.

***

When you hear the Master, Sri Ramakant speaking, you know it is Truth. He found me at last, after searching for over thirty years. I finally found a living Realized Master, and life has not been the same since. I am happy and contented all the time, full of laughter and joy.

***

The seemingly, endless agony of yearning for a true Sadguru like Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj finally blossomed in discovering Sri Ramakant Maharaj’s existence. So, I eagerly rushed to Him and was truly satsified. So, to all the yearning hearts, I implore you to dive deep into this rarest of Knowledge.

***

I missed Nisargadatta Maharaj. I was not around for Ramana Maharshi. I wasn’t going to miss Sri Ramakant Maharaj. In his presence, I was left speechless. I took the Naam Mantra and it literally, blew my mind! I am empty, thoughtless and beyond happy! I cannot say any more, except that I am eternally grateful to my Master.

***

My search started when I was about twenty years of age. Two years ago, I visited Sri Ramakant Maharaj in Nashik Ashram. I knew he was the one to bring my search to an end. He did! Every day, I feel so fortunate and so blessed because I know who I am.

***

When I came across Sadguru Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj’s famous book, I AM THAT, I could not go past the first two chapters. I could somewhat feel the value of what was conveyed, but could not relate enough to it. So I left the book altogether and went in other directions.

A decade after that, I met his disciple, Sadguru Sri Ramakant Maharaj, and after a few months listening to him, meditating, remembering, practicing the Mantra, I opened I AM THAT again and was surprised: I could easily relate to it and started benefitting from it. Maharaj’s simple and relentless hammering and the wisdom of Sadguru Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj, what a combination!

Maharaj is teaching with absolute straightforwardness, utter simplicity, infinite patience and care. It is evident that Sadguru Sri Ramakant Maharaj is totally given over to his Master Sadguru Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj. He is moving his

Master’s teaching forward to reflect the needs of the devotees of our time and help them transform the easily available intellectual knowledge into actual, living knowledge. He is a lawyer that gives the courage to fight one’s case for freedom. He is a doctor that helps dispel the disease and recover the original health. He is, as he once said, the garbage man, calling for your trash!

The Master is completely dedicated, selflessly giving away his energy, time and resources without counting, keeping the oath of the Lineage not to accept any material advantage from devotees. I feel truly blessed that he took my hand. If not, I would probably still be roaming around, in search of myself!

Since meeting Maharaj in late 2015, I have been following His advice diligently with both, daily sitting meditation and recitation of the Guru Mantra, as often as possible. This has been an intense, spiritual journey with many adversities – physical (including surgery), professional, emotional and family-related difficulties, that I faced along the way. The intensity of the meditation is sometimes a bit too much for the physical body to bear.

At times, it has been a struggle to balance my professional, hectic work schedules, and meditation, alongside family members clinging to conventional religion. This has provided much distraction and resistance, since they are not spiritually mature enough to understand, or accept the truth of Advaita. As Maharaj states so often, this is a “cleaning process” that must be undergone in order to get closer and closer to Selfless Self.

Along the way, despite all of the external problems, there has been so much spiritual bliss, and some profound experiences have resulted from the meditation, including expansive and empty states of Samadhi, feelings of body lightness, and growing devotion to our Master. Although Spontaneous Conviction has not resulted yet, full intellectual conviction has occurred. The Master keeps encouraging me, by confirming that I am getting closer and closer to the Ultimate Goal. Thank you.

***

My professional life is incredibly challenging – daily work with dying patients, and assisting in their immense suffering. At times the stress and anxiety I’ve experienced with this, has been such a weight to carry that I’ve searched for so much meaning in all this.

But since meeting Maharaj, and in reading Selfless Self – everything is lighter. Even though I share in these worldly experiences, I am less and less affected by them.

It is a privilege to care for the dying, but I am constantly reminded with ever deepening clarity, of the meaning behind Maharaj’s words “Who is dying?” and “There is no doer and no deed.” Though I continue to encounter loss and grief, recitation of the Naam Mantra keeps me centred, and away from the mental turbulence that can appear with my work.

I’ve stopped searching. Jai Guru.

***

Maharaj has had a tremendous impact on my life. My spiritual progress had plateaued, and coming across Him has been like the catalyst between my “B.C.” and “A.D.” I would like to share the most notable experience I have had since coming to know Him.

It began the day Maharaj returned to India from his trip to the U.S. in 2016. Shortly before going to bed, and a few hours after meditating that evening, spontaneously it occurred to me that my mind was very quiet. I tried forcing myself to have a thought and it was quite difficult, like trying to lift a

heavy object. I could just barely have some thoughts, but generally my mind was still. There were no feelings of anxiety, even when I did manage to think about something that usually gave me anxiety. This felt very uplifting, and had put me on the verge of tears. I went to sleep, wondering if I would still be in this state in the morning. I was, but then I wondered if I could still do my job properly, because I’m a translator and, of course, I need to be able to translate and type.

When I got started with my work, to my amazement, even though I wasn’t thinking about how to translate the words, the correct translations just came out of me, as my eyes looked at the computer screen, and my fingers typed. So, not only could I still do my job, I actually had the most productive day I had ever had, as I was able to work with no thought required. All other activities flowed effortlessly as well.

Later on, my mind became totally quiet. It felt like sitting alone in a cavernous auditorium. There was just silence, to a degree I wouldn’t have believed before. No fears, no anxieties! In this silence, I realized how many subtle thoughts and impressions we have that contribute to the typical human state of fear and anxiety.

In the weeks before, I could somewhat reduce the mind’s activity by exerting effort, like flexing a muscle, but now it was like no such effort was needed, because no thoughts were arising. Furthermore, even when there was a flurry of activity around me, such as people talking, and moving about, everything felt dreamlike and inherently empty, like a void. I felt indescribable spaciousness, like the entire universe was emanating from me – not my body, but my true identity as the screen of consciousness that is Selfless Self. There was no “I” thought, just everything happening, which felt like in essence a nothingness. I can’t really capture it all in words.

This experience came to an end four days after it began, but I haven’t been the same since. My recollection of that state continues to act as a beacon. This is all thanks to Maharaj, and for this, and everything else I have boundless gratitude toward Him.

***

The instruction is very simple: you were not the body, you are not the body, and you will not continue to be the body. Real Self-enquiry only began at that moment Everything that happened in this body I put under the gaze of Self-enquiry: Where was this emotion (or thought), before the birth of this body? Where will you go, when you have to leave the body? Immediately, everything is absorbed in the Absolute Presence. No more roads, no more Gurus, no more teachings, I placed my head at the feet of Maharaj.

I believed in Maharaj. I believed and practised with great determination: meditation, self-inquiry, chanting the Bhajans. A strong Conviction suddenly appeared: if you say “Jai Guru”. with deep respect and love, towards the Masters of this Sampradaya, you do not need anything else. With Love...

RAJA-DHI RAJ SADGURUNATH SRI RAMAKANT MAHARAJ KI JAY!

***

After having read so many books and scriptures, after having met prominent gurus and teachers, and after having numerous divine experiences, there came a moment, amidst personal crisis and desperation, that I first felt inspired to travel to India, not as a tourist, but for the express purpose of sitting at the feet of a real Jnani. I was not seeking more knowledge, or another experience, I was searching for the end of both. I only wanted true peace, real happiness, and Absolute Truth. Sri Ramakant Maharaj provided the key that was necessary to unlock those inner treasures.

Although I was only with Maharaj for a few short weeks,

his Presence and teachings made a lasting impression. His message is concise and direct, so much so, that the mind has difficulty accepting that Reality can be so simple. For this reason, Maharaj prescribes meditation for preparing the mind to absorb the Ultimate Truth. Maharaj stressed the need for Conviction, and he repeatedly admonished us to actively convince ourselves, by continually remembering that truth.

He never asked for money or promoted himself; he only asked that we did not waste time with endless wandering from books to teachers, to holy sites. He had revealed the essence of the scriptures, and the preaching of the saints. This is the final stop. This is where we exit the train and make our home, the home we never truly left. It is our very self.

Sri Ramakant Maharaj’s words are now a constant inner voice. “The speaker in me, and the listener in you, are one and the same.” Maharaj is not a guru external to me; he is the Master within me. As doubts arise, I hear him say, “I am not making you a disciple; I am making you a Master. The Masterly Essence is already within you.” When meditation feels difficult, Maharaj encourages me: “Be strong! Have confidence! You are the Master of the mind!” When I feel confused, Maharaj reminds me, “You are absolute truth. There is no ‘I’ or ‘you’. There is nothing except for your Selfless Self.” All sense of separation and limitation, are slowly dissolving, as I hear his voice. “You are like the sky. There are many houses, but only one sky. If the house falls, is the sky hurt? There are many bodies, but only one Self. You are not in the world; the world is in you!” Maharaj’s speech is always giving, and never taking. “Become enlightened, and help others become enlightened, but never make it a business.” I am forever grateful for Maharaj’s constant hammering. Jai Sadguru!

***

Some months, ago I stumbled upon the discourses of Sri Ramakant Maharaji, and I was captivated by his message which was very simple, bold, direct, and potent. I am no stranger, to a wide variety of Indian philosophies, and yogic teachings, by many masters and gurus, but still Maharaji’s message stood out, as an unusually no-nonsense insight into the true nature of our identities. Next, I read his book Selfless Self, and was even more convinced that he was one, who spoke not about a philosophy, but from his own experience. Soon I decided I must see for myself, if he was for real.

I came to his ashram in the hope of seeing him, and hearing his discourses first hand, but upon my arrival, I discovered that the Master had recently become ill, and had just returned from the hospital with strict orders to have complete rest. However, he did attend the evening satsang on my first day there, and though his body was weak, and he did not speak, his Presence was powerful. I continued to attend the ashram satsangs each day, though Maharaji was unable to attend.

Though I had requested the Naam Mantra earlier in the week, it was uncertain if that was going to happen due to his bodily weakness. On my last night at the ashram, I was informed the Maharaji had graciously agreed to meet with me in his home, to give the Naam Mantra. Very soon, I found myself there, as he prepared me for initiation. He placed his hand on my head, and spoke the Naam Mantra, and though his voice was weak, the strength of his Conviction resounded with a Bang! The Naam Mantra said everything that there was to say. Any disappointment I may have harboured from not being able to hear him give discourses, immediately vanished, as I understood that this is what I came to receive.

***

As truth is beyond words, there’s not much to say about Sri Ramakant Maharaj, but if I were to try to put it into words, I’d say that it was a beautiful thing seeing silence speak. That meeting in Oneness is imprinted in my Heart forever.

***

Sri Ramakant Maharaj returned attention back to the Reality, and away from ‘body-knowledge’. Slowly, silently and permanently, courage was provided, and with each step there was a growing peace, exceptional silence, and a deepening conviction of the Ultimate Truth: “Except Your Selfless Self, there is no God, no Brahman, no Atman, no Paramatman, No Master, no Disciple, nothing is there”. I bow to Selfless Self through Sri Ramakant Maharaj, and all the lineage Masters. Jai Sadguru!

***

I really don’t know why I have had the great fortune to meet Sri Ramakant Maharaj! But having been accepted, and initiated, has made such tremendous difference. The greatness of a Sadguru cannot be overstated, and the power of the Naam Mantra, cannot be overvalued. For those who long for Self-Realization, I implore you, drink in these words of Divine Wisdom, submerge yourself in them. As keen and earnest as you are, in equal measure will the unfolding process within you take shape. Better still, read this book thoroughly, and through it, you will be in the Presence of Sri Ramakant Maharaj

***

I am so, so grateful to my Master! My life transformed completely, after being in contact with Maharaj’s teachings. It is totally changing my whole frame of reference, of what I thought life was about. Yes, I was most certainly full of ego (an egomaniac), and for me (although I wouldn’t have admitted it at the time), my goals were to be rich and famous!

It was shortly after my marriage break-up, that I was introduced to spirituality, through Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj’s I Am That. This was interesting to me, as it offered some relief – a different way of looking at things, than I had ever thought of before. Gradually, my interest grew, and eventually, I had the good fortune of being able to meet Sri Ramakant Maharaj. Taking initiation, and receiving, (and attempting to put into practice), his teachings, has totally changed my life in ways that I could never have imagined.

The Master’s constant hammering that I am not the body, is working. The Mantra meditation is acting just like Maharaj said it would, and dissolving the concepts. It is so freeing to let go of so much baggage. The stronghold that the illusory ego had over me, seems to be subsiding, slowly. But it is not all plain sailing. Sometimes, I slip back a bit, and some old behavior, doubts, thoughts and feelings creep in. But then I realize with a jolt, the sense of bondage and heaviness that these concepts bring.

When something in life feels a bit clunky, sticky, heavy, difficult or charged etc., I find that Maharaj’s voice pops into my head, saying something like: “You are not the body”, or “who want’s this?”. Sometimes it might be a line from one of the devotional songs like Chidananda – “there is no father, no mother, no brother, no sister” -and this reminds me that everything is illusion.

In practical terms, I am getting so much strength, stability and calmness thanks to Maharaj’s teachings. What comes with this, too, is an immense sense of freedom and fun. I am finding more and more of my time, to be perfectly happy and amused for no reason – it’s a kind of spontaneous thing. Thank you Maharaj!

***

Having known of, and knowing Ramakant Maharaj for two and half years, I can only say that this is it! As the personal effort decreases, the Reality increases. There is no need of anything else. So simple and direct and actually effortless, (if you let it), the “practice” of keeping Selfless Self in mind proceeds and the illusion recedes. My search ended with Ramakant Maharaj, and the blessings are endless. Jai Guru!!!

***

Ramakant Maharaj is the first Master I have ever bowed to. That says it all!

***

The waves are dancing all around. I am the wave too, up to this point. My daily prayer is: “Let me fall into the Ocean where I will not dance any more as a wave, but be one with the Ocean.” The Master says you are not the body, mind or intellect. You are the Oneness! Just believe and trust the Master completely. Total trust in the Master’s words is the key to Final Reality. I bow down, and touch my Master’s feet, for this divine teaching.

***

Outside of your Selfless Self there is no Master! That teaching was made a living experience, when I met Ramakant Maharaj. It was not primarily transferred at one of the satsangs we had, or when Maharaj shared the Nama Mantra. One evening, he invited the visiting devotees for chai at his house, and we spent an hour there in quiet chitchat. Walking to the hotel afterwards in silence, I recognised that what I had encountered within myself in deepest meditation, and Maharaj, who had been sipping chai across the room, were one and the same.

That I’m sitting here, typing these words, can be conceptual; the unity between Maharaj and me is beyond doubt.

***

Since I was very young, I’ve been trying to understand what I am. I went through various masters and teachings, until I came across Advaita Vedanta and the book, I Am That of Nisargadatta Maharaj. This book was a great revelation, with the lucidity and clarity of the teachings. Nisargadatta stole my heart, and from then on, I would always talk to him, and tell him that, if I had to find a living teacher, he would lead me to him.

So, by chance, the Ramakant Maharaj page appeared on my Facebook. I went to look, and immediately went to Nashik, in February 2018. I felt immense joy and peace in the Ashram, with the bhajans, the teachings, and the simplicity. I noticed in the presence of Maharaj, that all questions, without exception, come from identification with the mind-body. And for the first time, I understood with my heart, what Nisargadatta meant when he said: “I only trusted my Master and followed what he told me”. Maharaj always emphasizes: nothing exists except the Self. But we do not really trust what he says. Having the honour of knowing Ramakant Maharaj was the greatest gift. He is always with me, in my heart. Trusting the Guru, and his instructions is everything. Om Shanti. Jai Guru Sri Ramakant Maharaj!

***

Since coming across the teachings of Ramakant Maharaj in his book Selfless Self, I knew I had to go and meet him, as I had never heard or read anything like that before. Since then, I have been following the practice with great determination, of meditation, Self-enquiry and chanting the bhajans. And, just like Maharaj said, a strong Conviction is emerging. Now my searching is over, and there is no longer anything missing in my life. No more roads and no more gurus!

***

I have been searching for decades, but now my search has ended with Ramakant Maharaj. I have met so many Masters but He is the only one who has shown me that the answers are all within me. His teaching showed me, that all the knowledge and concepts that I had accumulated, were in fact blocking the Truth. Thank you Maharaj for helping to discard this illusory baggage. Now I know what Maharaj means when he says “You are a free bird!”

***

There are three experiences that I would like to speak about. My first experience with Sri Ramakant Maharaj was through a photograph that a friend sent to me. I didn’t know who the man was in the photo, but I felt an immediate attraction. Some time later, I found out that he was Sri Ramakant Maharaj. That photo opened the door.

Naturally, I searched the internet for Sri Ramakant Maharaj, and found a website dedicated to the Master. I contacted the administrators, and they got back to me right away. We immediately became heart friends – perhaps Maharaji’s blessings! I owe a lot to these two wonderful beings One of them has now joined the Lineage’s Masters, in the open space, formless heart. He left this world. His story is a wondrous one.

The second experience of Maharaj and the teaching occurred when I had a dream of Sri Ranjit Maharaj (I know that sometimes it is said, that we shouldn’t publicly reveal certain dreams, but in this case I feel it is appropriate.) Ranjit Maharaj came to me in a dream and bestowed upon me the Naam Mantra of the Lineage that He and Ramakant Maharaj belong to. I didn’t know that it was the Lineage Mantra. A year later, when Ramakant Maharaj initiated me into the Naam Mantra, it was in the exact same way and mantra that Ranjit Maharaj had done previously, in the dream. I told this to Ramakant Maharaj as I wetted tears of joy, amazement and heartfelt gratitude.

The third experience relates again to a photo. I have a photo of Ramakant Maharaj that I use for Puja when I travel. One afternoon, I was reciting the “Afternoon Bhajans”. I lit a candle in front of the photo, after reciting the bhajans (the photo was not in a frame. I had it propped against Maharaji’s book Selfless Self). I left the room for a short period. When I returned, I noticed the photo had fallen over. When I lifted it up it had been burned by the candle. Low and behold an upside-down heart had been burned into the photo right beside the head of Maharaj, and his beautiful smiling face.

All this revealed to me, beyond the shadow of a doubt, the truth of Maharaji’s teachings, “that Guru resides in the space of the heart always”. The true Guru is eternally the heart – beyond form, formless, beyond space and time. But also right here in this space at this time, here and now always. Thank you, Maharaj, for the gift of your Presence and teachings. I bow to Thee! Jai Sadguru.

***

When I met Maharaj, I knew he was true straight away, and thus fell for him spontaneously.

I had the good fortune to meet various sages in my life and knew that the sense of presence and bliss is vital in determining whether a sage is true, or not. A real sage’s words never repeats learned knowledge from books. What he says is his own and flows spontaneously and fully original from his lips. And so it was with Maharaj!

During my visit, tears flowed from my eyes. “Melting” is what Maharaj called this phenomenon when I asked him about it. It had to do with the power behind his words. There was something crisp and electric about them, and they were spoken in a most direct sense. It is incredibly rare that one is spoken to as Brahman, as who I really am. I surrendered this body to His feet all the time.

I came to understand that all the practices have to do with vibrations. Whether they were Maharaj’s words, the Mantra or the Bhajans, their vibration made the Awareness more subtle, not only in the waking state, but also in the dream state, and in deep sleep. Maharaj says that the repetition of the Mantra becomes spontaneous after a while.

Over time, the Seer became aware of a tiny dot in Nothingness. That dot expanded extremely rapidly from Nothingness and when my room came into focus, thoughts came in, and with thought, my room expanded even further! This left me with the direct insight, that the word is nothing but a thought rising from Nothingness, a process that happens every morning in an instance. Most extraordinary!

Every afternoon we sing about this phenomena in the Bhajans: “In a sesame seed the whole universe remains, and God also remains there. The owner of the whole universe stays inside a small sesame seed, ‘house’. This smallest seed contains all three worlds.

Saint Tukaram says, “in one tiny drop (or one small seed), are the whole three worlds”.

If you read this in a book, it is impossible to comprehend, and it will remain a concept. But If you have seen for your Self it will remain with you for ever. Maharaj says, it will reveal itSelf spontaneously from within you! Jai! Guru Maharaj, my gratitude is too big for a word, but contained in a tiny seed!

***

I began my search in earnest for a “living”, True Master. Shri Nisargadatta had passed. I felt I had sadly “missed the boat” with Shri Nisargadatta Maharaj, by only a few years. But I was too late. He never mentioned, “Who?” would follow in His footsteps, or follow Him upon His death. I silently pined over His death for many years, but also was so happy to have found the Lineage books. I kept the Masters’ books by my side, highlighted and pencilled arrows on every page. These books would be my Master. They were tattered and torn, but worth their weight in gold. I still prayed one day, to meet my Master before leaving this world.

Years passed, and I came across a book entitled Selfless Self by Sri Ramakant Maharaj, a direct disciple of Sri Nisargadatta. I began to read it, and could not believe my eyes! This book spoke to me, in the same way “I AM THAT” spoke to me! I felt so blessed to find it! “Selfless Self” was FILLED to the brim with Truth and Wisdom, complete with instructions on the way to become Realized! The Naam Mantra! I was in heaven!

I finally met my Master, and received the Naam Mantra. I was beyond elated, overwhelmed, and could not speak much, if at all – as being in Maharaj’s Presence was overwhelming! I had wished for this Truth my entire life, and knew I was now “face to face” with Truth and Reality! My life has changed since that wondrous and glorious day, and all for the better. Nothing in life can match Maharaj. No matter what is happening in my family life, or in this illusory world, I have the powerful tool of the Naam Mantra, to keep me calm and unaffected. The Naam Mantra is extremely powerful, and not to be taken lightly. Maharaj teaches that meditation with Mantra is key; Master reveals ALL the secrets and leaves nothing to the imagination.

So, I heard Truth after Truth that resonated with this form I hold, and slowly the process of Realization began. Watching Him is a meditation, in and of, itself…such a generous and kind spirit is Maharaj.

In the form known as Maharaj, he teaches, and he hammers the Truth into His devotees. The Spontaneous Knowledge we have all searched for, happens – everything and all we need to know is within. Be With You! He confirms there is no one, or nothing there; nothing at all. Master exudes a special kind of ethereal kindness, and is unaffected by whatever is happening around Him, or problems of a personal nature. There is no body; no mind. We are One…no need to be concerned about death and dying because we were never born. Deeper understanding comes with practising the Naam Mantra.

In the years that followed, I have seen progress in my practice. There are many more days of joy and happiness now – and for no particular reason! No more deep concerns that used to seem so real. For this, I owe thanks and deep devotion to Maharaj. Shri Ramakant Maharaj.

Maharaj is a True Master of Truth, sharing freely everything one needs, in order to be free. We are not the body and we are not the mind; we are free…It is a simple Teaching, but it is up to each one of us to fully absorb the knowledge. And as I continue on in this world, there is peace within. I can now be a witness to what is happening, without being affected by it. The simple Truth is that after following the teaching of Dear Ramakant Maharaj, and appreciating and respecting both the Naam Mantra, as well as our Dear Maharaj, the one who is ready, can never look back to the old ways of living. You become transformed to Reality.

Words are inadequate, to describe the process of the beautiful change that just “happens” after meeting a Self-Realized Master. One cannot argue with Truth, and Maharaj is pure Knowledge and Truth. I aspire to reach His level. There is simply nothing left to want, or to desire after receiving the Naam Mantra.. I recite the sacred Naam Mantra every day, and nothing could be more beautiful. Your own inner Master will start talking… until there are no more questions. “I” am still in awe. Thank You, Shri Ramakant Maharaj, for a lifetime dream come true!!! My sincere devotion will never leave Your Feet; Your Footprints are forever engraved in my heart. Thank You, Master. You are the beginning, and the end. We are One. Jai Sadguru!

***

Meeting Maharaj, and reciting the Guru Mantra has changed my life. Before I used to feel so much anxiety, rage, anger and frustration, but these have now subsided to a huge extent, and now I really know what living in the present is! Even when strong emotions may start to rise, my attention goes to the Mantra.

My anxiety has reduced to the maximum extent, and I now know the meaning of spontaneous living in the present. Though I did not have any dramatic experiences during meditation, all my concepts are getting peeled away, like the peeling of an onion. Whatever is happening, there is an understanding that everything is happening spontaneously.

***

Words cannot express the transformation that has taken place, since discovering Sri Ramakant Maharaj. There is no longer a sense of time. The days and nights, weeks and years, just flow spontaneously. Everything flows, and unfolds, with a heart that is bursting with joy, and peace, that surpasses all understanding. There are no thoughts, only a vast emptiness that is filled with pure happiness, ecstasy and laughter. I did not know that it was possible, to be empty and full at the same time. I used to think I knew so much. Then, I discovered that I did not know anything at all. Knowing that there is nothing to know, is the greatest liberation! I bow to my great, and humble Master, with immense respect and gratitude!

GLOSSARY

Aham Brahmaasmi Mantra meaning "I am Brahman", "I am Ultimate Reality".

Amrut Nectar.

Atman The Supreme Self.

Atma Nivedanam Bhakti Highest Devotion, Self-Surrender.

Bhajans Devotional songs, Worship.

Bhakti Devotion.

Brahman The Absolute, Ultimate Reality.

Darshan Vision(s) of the Divine.

Dattatreya Adi-Guru (First-Guru) of the Navnath Sampradaya, considered as the incarnation of The Divine trinity of Brahma, Visnu, and Shiva.

Dharma Cosmic order, Divine Law.

Diksha Initiation.

Gunas Attributes, qualities. The three gunas: Rajas, Sattva, Tamas.

Hatha Yoga A system of yoga for gaining control over the physical body and life-force.

Karma Action, cause and effect.

Jnani Knower.

Krupa Blessing, grace.

Mahasamadhi The Great Merging, the final samadhi. The Ultimate goal of the spiritual seeker.

Maya Illusion.

Mukti Liberation, freedom.

Mula-Maya The primary illusion. Origin, root, base illusion.

Naam Mantra Mantra used by the Navnath Sampradaya Lineage, meaning "I am Brahman, Brahman I am".

Neti-neti "Not this, not this" method of enquiry.

Para, Pashyanti, Madhyama and Vaikhari The four levels of speech.

Prasad Food used as a religuous offering.

Rajas Excitable, activity, restlessness, egoism. One of the three gunas.

Samadhi Oneness with Self. Rapturous absorption.

Sadhana Spiritual practice.

Sadguru Highest and transcendent spiritual Guru, True Guru.

Sannyasin Renunciate.

Satsang Association with the wise, meeting in Truth.

Sattva Illuminating, pure. One of three gunas.

Shivoham Mantra meaning "I am Shiva", "I am Ultimate Reality".

Shakti Spiritual power, spiritual energy.

Shama, Dama, Titiksha, Uparati, Bhakti, Shradda Six sign of realization.

Soham Mantra meaning "I am That", "I am Ultimate Reality".

Swarup Reality, One's own form, nature.

Tamas Restraining - darkness, inertia, passivity.

Vipassana A method of meditation used in some forms of Buddhism, involving concentration on the body and it's sensations.

Our Beloved Sadguru Sri Ramakant Maharaj Mahasamadhi, 31 August 2018, 11.23am, Mumbai.